<volume id="J02">
 <paper id="1000">
 <title>Computational Linguistics, Volume 28, Number 1, March 2002</title>
</paper>

<paper id="1001">
 <title>Binding Machines</title>
 <author><first>António</first><last>Branco</last></author>
</paper>

<paper id="1002">
 <title>A Critique and Improvement of an Evaluation Metric for Text Segmentation</title>
 <author><first>Lev</first><last>Pevzner</last></author>
 <author><first>Marti A.</first><last>Hearst</last></author>
</paper>

<paper id="1003">
 <title>Generating Referring Expressions: Boolean Extensions of the Incremental Algorithm</title>
 <author><first>Kees</first><last>van Deemter</last></author>
</paper>

<paper id="1004">
 <title>Syllable-Pattern-Based Unknown-Morpheme Segmentation and Estimation for Hybrid Part-of-Speech Tagging of Korean</title>
 <author><first>Gary Geunbae</first><last>Lee</last></author>
 <author><first>Jeongwon</first><last>Cha</last></author>
 <author><first>Jong-Hyeok</first><last>Lee</last></author>
</paper>

<paper id="1005">
 <title>Squibs and Discussions: The DOP Estimation Method is Biased and Inconsistent</title>
 <author><first>Mark</first><last>Johnson</last></author>
</paper>

<paper id="1006">
 <title>Book Reviews: Tree Adjoining Grammars: Formalisms, Linguistic Analysis and Processing edited by Anne Abeille and Owen Rambow, Reviewed by Geoffrey K. Pullum; The Theory and Practice of Discourse Parsing and Summarization by Daniel Marcu, Reviewed by Udo Hahn; Natural Language Semantics by Keith Allan, Reviewed by Rodger Kibble; Intonation: Analysis, Modelling and Technology edited by Antonis Botinis, Reviewed by Martine Grice; Polysemy: Theoretical and Computational Approaches edited by Yael Ravin and Claudia Leacock, Reviewed by Jean Véronis; Abduction, Belief and Context in Dialogue: Studies in Computational Pragmatics edited by Harry Bunt and William Black, Reviewed by Matthew Stone; Relationships in the Organization of Knowledge edited by Carol A. Bean and Rebecca Green, Reviewed by Gregory Grefenstette</title>
</paper>

<paper id="1007">
 <title>Briefly Noted</title>
</paper>

 <paper id="2000">
 <title>Computational Linguistics, Volume 28, Number 2, June 2002</title>
</paper>

<paper id="2001">
 <title>Near-Synonymy and Lexical Choice</title>
 <author><first>Philip</first><last>Edmonds</last></author>
 <author><first>Graeme</first><last>Hirst</last></author>
</paper>

<paper id="2002">
 <title>The Combinatory Morphemic Lexicon</title>
 <author><first>Cem</first><last>Bozsahin</last></author>
</paper>

<paper id="2003">
 <title>Class-Based Probability Estimation Using a Semantic Hierarchy</title>
 <author><first>Stephen</first><last>Clark</last></author>
 <author><first>David</first><last>Weir</last></author>
</paper>

<paper id="2004">
 <title>Incremental Construction and Maintenance of Minimal Finite-State Automata</title>
 <author><first>Rafael C.</first><last>Carrasco</last></author>
 <author><first>Mikel L.</first><last>Forcada</last></author>
</paper>

<paper id="2005">
 <title>Book Reviews: Spotting and Discovering Terms through Natural Language Processing by Christian Jacquemin, Reviewed by Sophia Ananiadou; Automatic Summarization by Inderjeet Mani, Reviewed by Chris D. Paice; Efficient Processing with Constraint-Logic Grammars Using Grammar Compilation by Guido Minnen, Reviewed by Suresh Manandhar; The Language of Word Meaning edited by Pierrette Bouillon and Federica Busa, Reviewed by Mari Broman Olsen; Empirical Methods for Exploiting Parallel Texts by I. Dan Melamed, Reviewed by Ted Pedersen; Sentence Comprehension: The Integration of Habits and Rules by David J. Townsend and Thomas G. Bever, Reviewed by Matthew W. Crocker</title>
</paper>

<paper id="2006">
 <title>Publications Received</title>
</paper>

 <paper id="3000">
 <title>Computational Linguistics, Volume 28, Number 3, September 2002</title>
</paper>

<paper id="3001">
 <title>Automatic Labeling of Semantic Roles</title>
 <author><first>Daniel</first><last>Gildea</last></author>
 <author><first>Daniel</first><last>Jurafsky</last></author>
</paper>

<paper id="3002">
 <title>Periods, Capitalized Words, etc.</title>
 <author><first>Andrei</first><last>Mikheev</last></author>
</paper>

<paper id="3003">
 <title>Toward an Aposynthesis of Topic Continuity and Intrasentential Anaphora</title>
 <author><first>Eleni</first><last>Miltsakaki</last></author>
</paper>

<paper id="3004">
 <title>The Disambiguation of Nominalizations</title>
 <author><first>Maria</first><last>Lapata</last></author>
</paper>

<paper id="3005">
 <title>Squibs and Discussions: A Note on Typing Feature Structures</title>
 <author><first>Shuly</first><last>Wintner</last></author>
 <author><first>Anoop</first><last>Sarkar</last></author>
</paper>

 <paper id="4000">
 <title>Computational Linguistics, Volume 28, Number 4, December 2002</title>
</paper>

<paper id="4001">
 <title>Introduction to the Special Issue on Summarization</title>
 <author><first>Dragomir R.</first><last>Radev</last></author>
 <author><first>Eduard</first><last>Hovy</last></author>
 <author><first>Kathleen</first><last>McKeown</last></author>
</paper>

<paper id="4002">
 <title>Articles Summarizing Scientific Articles: Experiments with Relevance and Rhetorical Status</title>
 <author><first>Simone</first><last>Teufel</last></author>
 <author><first>Marc</first><last>Moens</last></author>
</paper>

<paper id="4003">
 <title>Automatic Summarization of Open-Domain Multiparty Dialogues in Diverse Genres</title>
 <author><first>Klaus</first><last>Zechner</last></author>
</paper>

<paper id="4004">
 <title>Efficiently Computed Lexical Chains as an Intermediate Representation for Automatic Text Summarization</title>
 <author><first>H. Gregory</first><last>Silber</last></author>
 <author><first>Kathleen F.</first><last>McCoy</last></author>
</paper>

<paper id="4005">
 <title>Generating Indicative-Informative Summaries with SumUM</title>
 <author><first>Horacio</first><last>Saggion</last></author>
 <author><first>Guy</first><last>Lapalme</last></author>
</paper>

<paper id="4006">
 <title>Using Hidden Markov Modeling to Decompose Human-Written Summaries</title>
 <author><first>Hongyan</first><last>Jing</last></author>
</paper>

<paper id="4007">
 <title>Squibs and Discussions: Human Variation and Lexical Choice</title>
 <author><first>Ehud</first><last>Reiter</last></author>
 <author><first>Somayajulu</first><last>Sripada</last></author>
</paper>

<paper id="4008">
<title>Book Reviews: Early Years in Machine Translation: Memoirs and Biographies of Pioneers edited by W. John Hutchins, Reviewed by Warren J. Plath; Patterns of Text: In Honour of Michael Hoey edited by Mike Scott and Geoff Thompson, Reviewed by Graeme Hirst; Word Frequency Distributions by R. Harald Baayen, Reviewed by Geoffrey Sampson; Data-Driven Techniques in Speech Synthesis edited by R. I. Damper, Reviewed by Thierry Dutoit; Empirical Linguistics by Geoffrey Sampson, Reviewed by Steven Abney; Computational Nonlinear Morphology with Emphasis on Semitic Languages by George Anton Kiraz, Reviewed by Markus Walther</title>
</paper>

<paper id="4009">
 <title>Briefly Noted</title>
</paper>

<paper id="4010">
 <title>Publications Received</title>
</paper>

<paper id="4011">
 <title>Author Index</title>
</paper>

<paper id="4012">
 <title>Title Index</title>
</paper>

</volume>