<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<collection id="2010.iwslt">
  <volume id="keynotes" ingest-date="2021-09-06" type="proceedings">
    <meta>
      <booktitle>Proceedings of the 7th International Workshop on Spoken Language Translation: Plenaries</booktitle>
      <address>Paris, France</address>
      <month>December 2-3</month>
      <year>2010</year>
      <venue>iwslt</venue>
    </meta>
    <paper id="1">
      <title>Is machine translation ripe for <fixed-case>EU</fixed-case> translators?</title>
      <author><first>Josep</first><last>Bonet</last></author>
      <url hash="8d7ba5dd">2010.iwslt-keynotes.1</url>
      <attachment type="presentation" hash="d4801acd">2010.iwslt-keynotes.1.Presentation.pdf</attachment>
      <bibkey>bonet-2010-machine</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="2">
      <title>Hierarchical phrase-based translation with weighted finite state transducers</title>
      <author id="bill-byrne"><first>William</first><last>Byrne</last></author>
      <url hash="d94b823d">2010.iwslt-keynotes.2</url>
      <attachment type="presentation" hash="d4801acd">2010.iwslt-keynotes.2.Presentation.pdf</attachment>
      <bibkey>byrne-2010-hierarchical</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="3">
      <title>Resources for adding semantics to machine translation</title>
      <author><first>Jan</first><last>Hajič</last></author>
      <url hash="8d7ba5dd">2010.iwslt-keynotes.3</url>
      <bibkey>hajic-2010-resources</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="4">
      <title>The Quaero program: multilingual and multimedia technologies</title>
      <author><first>Jean-Luc</first><last>Gauvain</last></author>
      <url hash="8d7ba5dd">2010.iwslt-keynotes.4</url>
      <bibkey>gauvain-2010-quaero</bibkey>
    </paper>
  </volume>
  <volume id="evaluation" ingest-date="2021-08-06" type="proceedings">
    <meta>
      <booktitle>Proceedings of the 7th International Workshop on Spoken Language Translation: Evaluation Campaign</booktitle>
      <address>Paris, France</address>
      <month>December 2-3</month>
      <year>2010</year>
      <venue>iwslt</venue>
    </meta>
    <frontmatter>
      <url hash="a0a90169">2010.iwslt-evaluation.0</url>
      <bibkey>iwslt-2010-international</bibkey>
    </frontmatter>
    <paper id="1">
      <title>Overview of the <fixed-case>IWSLT</fixed-case> 2010 evaluation campaign</title>
      <author><first>Michael</first><last>Paul</last></author>
      <author><first>Marcello</first><last>Federico</last></author>
      <author><first>Sebastian</first><last>Stüker</last></author>
      <pages>3-27</pages>
      <url hash="299877d6">2010.iwslt-evaluation.1</url>
      <abstract>This paper gives an overview of the evaluation campaign results of the 7th International Workshop on Spoken Language Translation (IWSLT 2010)1. This year, we focused on three spoken language tasks: (1) public speeches on a variety of topics (TALK) from English to French, (2) spoken dialog in travel situations (DIALOG) between Chinese and English, and (3) traveling expressions (BTEC) from Arabic, Turkish, and French to English. In total, 28 teams (including 7 firsttime participants) took part in the shared tasks, submitting 60 primary and 112 contrastive runs. Automatic and subjective evaluations of the primary runs were carried out in order to investigate the impact of different communication modalities, spoken language styles and semantic context on automatic speech recognition (ASR) and machine translation (MT) system performances.</abstract>
      <bibkey>paul-etal-2010-overview</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="2">
      <title><fixed-case>A</fixed-case>pp<fixed-case>T</fixed-case>ek’s <fixed-case>APT</fixed-case> machine translation system for <fixed-case>IWSLT</fixed-case> 2010</title>
      <author><first>Evgeny</first><last>Matusov</last></author>
      <author><first>Selçuk</first><last>Köprü</last></author>
      <pages>29-36</pages>
      <url hash="e86282a4">2010.iwslt-evaluation.2</url>
      <abstract>In this paper, we describe AppTek’s new APT machine translation system that we employed in the IWSLT 2010 evaluation campaign. This year, we participated in the Arabic-to-English and Turkish-to-English BTEC tasks. We discuss the architecture of the system, the preprocessing steps and the experiments carried out during the campaign. We show that competitive translation quality can be obtained with a system that can be turned into a real-life product without much effort.</abstract>
      <bibkey>matusov-kopru-2010-appteks</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="3">
      <title>The <fixed-case>DCU</fixed-case> machine translation systems for <fixed-case>IWSLT</fixed-case> 2010</title>
      <author><first>Hala</first><last>Almaghout</last></author>
      <author><first>Jie</first><last>Jiang</last></author>
      <author><first>Andy</first><last>Way</last></author>
      <pages>37-44</pages>
      <url hash="c09146e2">2010.iwslt-evaluation.3</url>
      <bibkey>almaghout-etal-2010-dcu</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="4">
      <title>N-gram-based machine translation enhanced with neural networks</title>
      <author><first>Francisco</first><last>Zamora-Martinez</last></author>
      <author><first>Maria Jose</first><last>Castro-Bleda</last></author>
      <author><first>Holger</first><last>Schwenk</last></author>
      <pages>45-52</pages>
      <url hash="f969b581">2010.iwslt-evaluation.4</url>
      <bibkey>zamora-martinez-etal-2010-n</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="5">
      <title><fixed-case>FBK</fixed-case> @ <fixed-case>IWSLT</fixed-case> 2010</title>
      <author><first>Arianna</first><last>Bisazza</last></author>
      <author><first>Ioannis</first><last>Klasinas</last></author>
      <author><first>Mauro</first><last>Cettolo</last></author>
      <author><first>Marcello</first><last>Federico</last></author>
      <pages>53-58</pages>
      <url hash="bf667fdb">2010.iwslt-evaluation.5</url>
      <abstract>This year FBK took part in the BTEC translation task, with source languages Arabic and Turkish and target language English, and in the new TALK task, source English and target French. We worked in the framework of phrase-based statistical machine translation aiming to improve coverage of models in presence of rich morphology, on one side, and to make better use of available resources through data selection techniques. New morphological segmentation rules were developed for Turkish-English. The combination of several Turkish segmentation schemes into a lattice input led to an improvement wrt to last year. The use of additional training data was explored for Arabic-English, while on the English to French task improvement was achieved over a strong baseline by automatically selecting relevant and high quality data from the available training corpora.</abstract>
      <bibkey>bisazza-etal-2010-fbk</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="6">
      <title>The <fixed-case>GREYC</fixed-case>/<fixed-case>LLACAN</fixed-case> machine translation systems for the <fixed-case>IWSLT</fixed-case> 2010 campaign</title>
      <author><first>Julien</first><last>Gosme</last></author>
      <author><first>Wigdan</first><last>Mekki</last></author>
      <author><first>Fathi</first><last>Debili</last></author>
      <author><first>Yves</first><last>Lepage</last></author>
      <author><first>Nadine</first><last>Lucas</last></author>
      <pages>59-65</pages>
      <url hash="380c7600">2010.iwslt-evaluation.6</url>
      <abstract>In this paper we explore the contribution of the use of two Arabic morphological analyzers as preprocessing tools for statistical machine translation. Similar investigations have already been reported for morphologically rich languages like German, Turkish and Arabic. Here, we focus on the case of the Arabic language and mainly discuss the use of the G-LexAr analyzer. A preliminary experiment has been designed to choose the most promising translation system among the 3 G-LexAr-based systems, we concluded that the systems are equivalent. Nevertheless, we decided to use the lemmatized output of G-LexAr and use its translations as primary run for the BTEC AE track. The results showed that G-LexAr outputs degrades translation compared to the basic SMT system trained on the un-analyzed corpus.</abstract>
      <bibkey>gosme-etal-2010-greyc</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="7">
      <title><fixed-case>I</fixed-case>2<fixed-case>R</fixed-case>’s machine translation system for <fixed-case>IWSLT</fixed-case> 2010</title>
      <author><first>Xiangyu</first><last>Duan</last></author>
      <author><first>Rafael</first><last>Banchs</last></author>
      <author><first>Jun</first><last>Lang</last></author>
      <author><first>Deyi</first><last>Xiong</last></author>
      <author><first>Aiti</first><last>Aw</last></author>
      <author><first>Min</first><last>Zhang</last></author>
      <author><first>Haizhou</first><last>Li</last></author>
      <pages>67-72</pages>
      <url hash="8771a4af">2010.iwslt-evaluation.7</url>
      <bibkey>duan-etal-2010-i2rs</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="8">
      <title>The <fixed-case>ICT</fixed-case> statistical machine translation system for <fixed-case>IWSLT</fixed-case> 2010</title>
      <author><first>Hao</first><last>Xiong</last></author>
      <author><first>Jun</first><last>Xie</last></author>
      <author><first>Hui</first><last>Yu</last></author>
      <author><first>Kai</first><last>Liu</last></author>
      <author><first>Wei</first><last>Luo</last></author>
      <author><first>Haitao</first><last>Mi</last></author>
      <author id="yang-liu-ict"><first>Yang</first><last>Liu</last></author>
      <author><first>Yajuan</first><last>Lü</last></author>
      <author><first>Qun</first><last>Liu</last></author>
      <pages>73-79</pages>
      <url hash="843f1889">2010.iwslt-evaluation.8</url>
      <bibkey>xiong-etal-2010-ict</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="9">
      <title>The <fixed-case>INESC</fixed-case>-<fixed-case>ID</fixed-case> machine translation system for the <fixed-case>IWSLT</fixed-case> 2010</title>
      <author><first>Wang</first><last>Ling</last></author>
      <author><first>Tiago</first><last>Luís</last></author>
      <author><first>João</first><last>Graça</last></author>
      <author><first>Luísa</first><last>Coheur</last></author>
      <author><first>Isabel</first><last>Trancoso</last></author>
      <pages>81-84</pages>
      <url hash="d33f26a9">2010.iwslt-evaluation.9</url>
      <abstract>In this paper we describe the Instituto de Engenharia de Sistemas e Computadores Investigac ̧a ̃o e Desenvolvimento (INESC-ID) system that participated in the IWSLT 2010 evaluation campaign. Our main goal for this evaluation was to employ several state-of-the-art methods applied to phrase-based machine translation in order to improve the translation quality. Aside from the IBM M4 alignment model, two constrained alignment models were tested, which produced better overall results. These results were further improved by using weighted alignment matrixes during phrase extraction, rather than the single best alignment. Finally, we tested several filters that ruled out phrase pairs based on puntuation. Our system was evaluated on the BTEC and DIALOG tasks, having achieved a better overall ranking in the DIALOG task.</abstract>
      <bibkey>ling-etal-2010-inesc</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="10">
      <title><fixed-case>ITI</fixed-case>-<fixed-case>UPV</fixed-case> machine translation system for <fixed-case>IWSLT</fixed-case> 2010</title>
      <author><first>Guillem</first><last>Gascó</last></author>
      <author><first>Vicent</first><last>Alabau</last></author>
      <author><first>Jesús-Andrés</first><last>Ferrer</last></author>
      <author><first>Jesús</first><last>González-Rubio</last></author>
      <author><first>Martha-Alicia</first><last>Rocha</last></author>
      <author><first>Germán</first><last>Sanchis-Trilles</last></author>
      <author><first>Francisco</first><last>Casacuberta</last></author>
      <author><first>Jorge</first><last>González</last></author>
      <author><first>Joan-Andreu</first><last>Sánchez</last></author>
      <pages>85-92</pages>
      <url hash="bc17b356">2010.iwslt-evaluation.10</url>
      <abstract>This paper presents the submissions of the PRHLT group for the evaluation campaign of the International Workshop on Spoken Language Translation. We focus on the development of reliable translation systems between syntactically different languages (DIALOG task) and on the efficient training of SMT models in resource-rich scenarios (TALK task).</abstract>
      <bibkey>gasco-etal-2010-iti</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="11">
      <title>The <fixed-case>KIT</fixed-case> translation system for <fixed-case>IWSLT</fixed-case> 2010</title>
      <author><first>Jan</first><last>Niehues</last></author>
      <author><first>Mohammed</first><last>Mediani</last></author>
      <author><first>Teresa</first><last>Herrmann</last></author>
      <author><first>Michael</first><last>Heck</last></author>
      <author><first>Christian</first><last>Herff</last></author>
      <author><first>Alex</first><last>Waibel</last></author>
      <pages>93-98</pages>
      <url hash="514af2fa">2010.iwslt-evaluation.11</url>
      <bibkey>niehues-etal-2010-kit</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="12">
      <title><fixed-case>LIG</fixed-case> statistical machine translation systems for <fixed-case>IWSLT</fixed-case> 2010</title>
      <author><first>Laurent</first><last>Besacier</last></author>
      <author><first>Haitem</first><last>Afli</last></author>
      <author><first>Thi Ngoc Diep</first><last>Do</last></author>
      <author><first>Hervé</first><last>Blanchon</last></author>
      <author><first>Marion</first><last>Potet</last></author>
      <pages>99-104</pages>
      <url hash="c9f3cf1f">2010.iwslt-evaluation.12</url>
      <bibkey>besacier-etal-2010-lig</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="13">
      <title><fixed-case>LIMSI</fixed-case> @ <fixed-case>IWSLT</fixed-case> 2010</title>
      <author><first>Alexandre</first><last>Allauzen</last></author>
      <author><first>Josep M.</first><last>Crego</last></author>
      <author><first>İlknur Durgar</first><last>El-Kahlout</last></author>
      <author><first>Le</first><last>Hai-Son</last></author>
      <author><first>Guillaume</first><last>Wisniewski</last></author>
      <author><first>François</first><last>Yvon</last></author>
      <pages>105-112</pages>
      <url hash="3181d2f4">2010.iwslt-evaluation.13</url>
      <abstract>This paper describes LIMSI’s Statistical Machine Translation systems (SMT) for the IWSLT evaluation, where we participated in two tasks (Talk for English to French and BTEC for Turkish to English). For the Talk task, we studied an extension of our in-house n-code SMT system (the integration of a bilingual reordering model over generalized translation units), as well as the use of training data extracted from Wikipedia in order to adapt the target language model. For the BTEC task, we concentrated on pre-processing schemes on the Turkish side in order to reduce the morphological discrepancies with the English side. We also evaluated the use of two different continuous space language models for such a small size of training data.</abstract>
      <bibkey>allauzen-etal-2010-limsi</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="14">
      <title><fixed-case>LIUM</fixed-case>’s statistical machine translation system for <fixed-case>IWSLT</fixed-case> 2010</title>
      <author><first>Anthony</first><last>Rousseau</last></author>
      <author><first>Loïc</first><last>Barrault</last></author>
      <author><first>Paul</first><last>Deléglise</last></author>
      <author><first>Yannick</first><last>Estève</last></author>
      <pages>113-117</pages>
      <url hash="27b899a4">2010.iwslt-evaluation.14</url>
      <abstract>This paper describes the two systems developed by the LIUM laboratory for the 2010 IWSLT evaluation campaign. We participated to the new English to French TALK task. We developed two systems, one for each evaluation condition, both being statistical phrase-based systems using the the Moses toolkit. Several approaches were investigated.</abstract>
      <bibkey>rousseau-etal-2010-liums</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="15">
      <title>The <fixed-case>MIRACL</fixed-case> <fixed-case>A</fixed-case>rabic-<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>nglish statistical machine translation system for <fixed-case>IWSLT</fixed-case> 2010</title>
      <author><first>Ines</first><last>Turki Khemakhem</last></author>
      <author><first>Salma</first><last>Jamoussi</last></author>
      <author><first>Abdelmajid</first><last>Ben Hamadou</last></author>
      <pages>119-125</pages>
      <url hash="3ca1acf2">2010.iwslt-evaluation.15</url>
      <abstract>This paper describes the MIRACL statistical Machine Translation system and the improvements that were developed during the IWSLT 2010 evaluation campaign. We participated to the Arabic to English BTEC tasks using a phrase-based statistical machine translation approach. In this paper, we first discuss some challenges in translating from Arabic to English and we explore various techniques to improve performances on a such task. Next, we present our solution for disambiguating the output of an Arabic morphological analyzer. In fact, The Arabic morphological analyzer used produces all possible morphological structures for each word, with an unique correct proposition. In this work we exploit the Arabic-English alignment to choose the correct segmented form and the correct morpho-syntactic features produced by our morphological analyzer.</abstract>
      <bibkey>turki-khemakhem-etal-2010-miracl</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="16">
      <title>The <fixed-case>MIT</fixed-case>-<fixed-case>LL</fixed-case>/<fixed-case>AFRL</fixed-case> <fixed-case>IWSLT</fixed-case>-2010 <fixed-case>MT</fixed-case> system</title>
      <author><first>Wade</first><last>Shen</last></author>
      <author><first>Timothy</first><last>Anderson</last></author>
      <author><first>Raymond</first><last>Slyh</last></author>
      <author><first>A. Ryan</first><last>Aminzadeh</last></author>
      <pages>127-134</pages>
      <url hash="f0757e59">2010.iwslt-evaluation.16</url>
      <abstract>This paper describes the MIT-LL/AFRL statistical MT system and the improvements that were developed during the IWSLT 2010 evaluation campaign. As part of these efforts, we experimented with a number of extensions to the standard phrase-based model that improve performance on the Arabic and Turkish to English translation tasks. We also participated in the new French to English BTEC and English to French TALK tasks. We discuss the architecture of the MIT-LL/AFRL MT system, improvements over our 2008 system, and experiments we ran during the IWSLT-2010 evaluation. Specifically, we focus on 1) cross-domain translation using MAP adaptation, 2) Turkish morphological processing and translation, 3) improved Arabic morphology for MT preprocessing, and 4) system combination methods for machine translation.</abstract>
      <bibkey>shen-etal-2010-mit</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="17">
      <title>The <fixed-case>MSRA</fixed-case> machine translation system for <fixed-case>IWSLT</fixed-case> 2010</title>
      <author><first>Chi-Ho</first><last>Li</last></author>
      <author><first>Nan</first><last>Duan</last></author>
      <author><first>Yinggong</first><last>Zhao</last></author>
      <author><first>Shujie</first><last>Liu</last></author>
      <author><first>Lei</first><last>Cui</last></author>
      <author><first>Mei-yuh</first><last>Hwang</last></author>
      <author><first>Amittai</first><last>Axelrod</last></author>
      <author><first>Jianfeng</first><last>Gao</last></author>
      <author><first>Yaodong</first><last>Zhang</last></author>
      <author><first>Li</first><last>Deng</last></author>
      <pages>135-138</pages>
      <url hash="5c44a959">2010.iwslt-evaluation.17</url>
      <bibkey>li-etal-2010-msra</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="18">
      <title>The <fixed-case>NICT</fixed-case> translation system for <fixed-case>IWSLT</fixed-case> 2010</title>
      <author><first>Chooi-Ling</first><last>Goh</last></author>
      <author><first>Taro</first><last>Watanabe</last></author>
      <author><first>Michael</first><last>Paul</last></author>
      <author><first>Andrew</first><last>Finch</last></author>
      <author><first>Eiichiro</first><last>Sumita</last></author>
      <pages>139-146</pages>
      <url hash="b809ec4b">2010.iwslt-evaluation.18</url>
      <abstract>This paper describes NICT’s participation in the IWSLT 2010 evaluation campaign for the DIALOG translation (Chinese-English) and the BTEC (French-English) translation shared-tasks. For the DIALOG translation, the main challenge to this task is applying context information during translation. Context information can be used to decide on word choice and also to replace missing information during translation. We applied discriminative reranking using contextual information as additional features. In order to provide more choices for re-ranking, we generated n-best lists from multiple phrase-based statistical machine translation systems that varied in the type of Chinese word segmentation schemes used. We also built a model that merged the phrase tables generated by the different segmentation schemes. Furthermore, we used a lattice-based system combination model to combine the output from different systems. A combination of all of these systems was used to produce the n-best lists for re-ranking. For the BTEC task, a general approach that used latticebased system combination of two systems, a standard phrasebased system and a hierarchical phrase-based system, was taken. We also tried to process some unknown words by replacing them with the same words but different inflections that are known to the system.</abstract>
      <bibkey>goh-etal-2010-nict</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="19">
      <title><fixed-case>NTT</fixed-case> statistical <fixed-case>MT</fixed-case> system for <fixed-case>IWSLT</fixed-case> 2010</title>
      <author><first>Katsuhito</first><last>Sudoh</last></author>
      <author><first>Kevin</first><last>Duh</last></author>
      <author><first>Hajime</first><last>Tsukada</last></author>
      <pages>147-152</pages>
      <url hash="6713dbed">2010.iwslt-evaluation.19</url>
      <bibkey>sudoh-etal-2010-ntt</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="20">
      <title>The <fixed-case>POSTECH</fixed-case>’s statistical machine translation system for the <fixed-case>IWSLT</fixed-case> 2010</title>
      <author><first>Hwidong</first><last>Na</last></author>
      <author><first>Jong-Hyeok</first><last>Lee</last></author>
      <pages>153-156</pages>
      <url hash="66461393">2010.iwslt-evaluation.20</url>
      <bibkey>na-lee-2010-postechs</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="21">
      <title>The <fixed-case>QMUL</fixed-case> system description for <fixed-case>IWSLT</fixed-case> 2010</title>
      <author><first>Sirvan</first><last>Yahyaei</last></author>
      <author><first>Christof</first><last>Monz</last></author>
      <pages>157-162</pages>
      <url hash="6fca3c8f">2010.iwslt-evaluation.21</url>
      <bibkey>yahyaei-monz-2010-qmul</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="22">
      <title>The <fixed-case>RWTH</fixed-case> <fixed-case>A</fixed-case>achen machine translation system for <fixed-case>IWSLT</fixed-case> 2010</title>
      <author><first>Saab</first><last>Mansour</last></author>
      <author><first>Stephan</first><last>Peitz</last></author>
      <author><first>David</first><last>Vilar</last></author>
      <author><first>Joern</first><last>Wuebker</last></author>
      <author><first>Hermann</first><last>Ney</last></author>
      <pages>163-168</pages>
      <url hash="c5581e69">2010.iwslt-evaluation.22</url>
      <abstract>In this paper we describe the statistical machine translation system of the RWTH Aachen University developed for the translation task of the IWSLT 2010. This year, we participated in the BTEC translation task for the Arabic to English language direction. We experimented with two state-of-theart decoders: phrase-based and hierarchical-based decoders. Extensions to the decoders included phrase training (as opposed to heuristic phrase extraction) for the phrase-based decoder, and soft syntactic features for the hierarchical decoder. Additionally, we experimented with various rule-based and statistical-based segmenters for Arabic. Due to the different decoders and the different methodologies that we apply for segmentation, we expect that there will be complimentary variation in the results achieved by each system. The next step would be to exploit these variations and achieve better results by combining the systems. We try different strategies for system combination and report significant improvements over the best single system.</abstract>
      <bibkey>mansour-etal-2010-rwth</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="23">
      <title><fixed-case>T</fixed-case>el Aviv University’s system description for <fixed-case>IWSLT</fixed-case> 2010</title>
      <author><first>Kfir</first><last>Bar</last></author>
      <author><first>Nachum</first><last>Dershowitz</last></author>
      <pages>169-174</pages>
      <url hash="bd8bc16f">2010.iwslt-evaluation.23</url>
      <bibkey>bar-dershowitz-2010-tel</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="24">
      <title>Statistical pattern-based <fixed-case>MT</fixed-case> with statistical <fixed-case>F</fixed-case>rench-<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>nglish <fixed-case>MT</fixed-case></title>
      <author><first>Jin’ichi</first><last>Murakami</last></author>
      <author><first>Takuya</first><last>Nishimura</last></author>
      <author><first>Masao</first><last>Tokuhisa</last></author>
      <pages>175-182</pages>
      <url hash="767f65d3">2010.iwslt-evaluation.24</url>
      <bibkey>murakami-etal-2010-statistical</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="25">
      <title>The <fixed-case>TÜBİTAK</fixed-case>-<fixed-case>UEKAE</fixed-case> statistical machine translation system for <fixed-case>IWSLT</fixed-case> 2010</title>
      <author><first>Coskun</first><last>Mermer</last></author>
      <author><first>Hamza</first><last>Kaya</last></author>
      <author><first>Mehmet Uğur</first><last>Doğan</last></author>
      <pages>183-188</pages>
      <url hash="59db4886">2010.iwslt-evaluation.25</url>
      <abstract>We report on our participation in the IWSLT 2010 evaluation campaign. Similar to previous years, our submitted systems are based on the Moses statistical machine translation toolkit. This year, we also experimented with hierarchical phrase-based models. In addition, we utilized automatic minimum error-rate training instead of manually-guided tuning. We focused more on the BTEC Turkish-English task and explored various experimentations with unsupervised segmentation to measure their effects on the translation performance. We present the results of several contrastive experiments, including those that failed to improve the translation performance.</abstract>
      <bibkey>mermer-etal-2010-tubitak</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="26">
      <title><fixed-case>UPC</fixed-case>-<fixed-case>BMIC</fixed-case>-<fixed-case>VDU</fixed-case> system description for the <fixed-case>IWSLT</fixed-case> 2010: testing several collocation segmentations in a phrase-based <fixed-case>SMT</fixed-case> system</title>
      <author><first>Carlos</first><last>Henríquez</last></author>
      <author><first>Marta R.</first><last>Costa-jussà</last></author>
      <author><first>Vidas</first><last>Daudaravicius</last></author>
      <author><first>Rafael E.</first><last>Banchs</last></author>
      <author><first>José B.</first><last>Mariño</last></author>
      <pages>189-195</pages>
      <url hash="030eee39">2010.iwslt-evaluation.26</url>
      <abstract>This paper describes the UPC-BMIC-VMU participation in the IWSLT 2010 evaluation campaign. The SMT system is a standard phrase-based enriched with novel segmentations. These novel segmentations are computed using statistical measures such as Log-likelihood, T-score, Chi-squared, Dice, Mutual Information or Gravity-Counts. The analysis of translation results allows to divide measures into three groups. First, Log-likelihood, Chi-squared and T-score tend to combine high frequency words and collocation segments are very short. They improve the SMT system by adding new translation units. Second, Mutual Information and Dice tend to combine low frequency words and collocation segments are short. They improve the SMT system by smoothing the translation units. And third, GravityCounts tends to combine high and low frequency words and collocation segments are long. However, in this case, the SMT system is not improved. Thus, the road-map for translation system improvement is to introduce new phrases with either low frequency or high frequency words. It is hard to introduce new phrases with low and high frequency words in order to improve translation quality. Experimental results are reported in the French-to-English IWSLT 2010 evaluation where our system was ranked 3rd out of nine systems.</abstract>
      <bibkey>henriquez-etal-2010-upc</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="27">
      <title><fixed-case>ILLC</fixed-case>-<fixed-case>U</fixed-case>v<fixed-case>A</fixed-case> machine translation system for the <fixed-case>IWSLT</fixed-case> 2010 evaluation</title>
      <author><first>Maxim</first><last>Khalilov</last></author>
      <author><first>Khalil</first><last>Sima’an</last></author>
      <pages>197-203</pages>
      <url hash="d76499a8">2010.iwslt-evaluation.27</url>
      <bibkey>khalilov-simaan-2010-illc</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="28">
      <title>The <fixed-case>U</fixed-case>v<fixed-case>A</fixed-case> system description for <fixed-case>IWSLT</fixed-case> 2010</title>
      <author><first>Spyros</first><last>Martzoukos</last></author>
      <author><first>Christof</first><last>Monz</last></author>
      <pages>205-208</pages>
      <url hash="940867fd">2010.iwslt-evaluation.28</url>
      <bibkey>martzoukos-monz-2010-uva</bibkey>
    </paper>
  </volume>
  <volume id="papers" ingest-date="2021-08-06" type="proceedings">
    <meta>
      <booktitle>Proceedings of the 7th International Workshop on Spoken Language Translation: Papers</booktitle>
      <address>Paris, France</address>
      <month>December 2-3</month>
      <year>2010</year>
      <venue>iwslt</venue>
    </meta>
    <paper id="1">
      <title><fixed-case>CCG</fixed-case> augmented hierarchical phrase-based machine translation</title>
      <author><first>Hala</first><last>Almaghout</last></author>
      <author><first>Jie</first><last>Jiang</last></author>
      <author><first>Andy</first><last>Way</last></author>
      <pages>211-218</pages>
      <url hash="11724d3e">2010.iwslt-papers.1</url>
      <bibkey>almaghout-etal-2010-ccg</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="2">
      <title>An algorithm for cross-lingual sense-clustering tested in a <fixed-case>MT</fixed-case> evaluation setting</title>
      <author><first>Marianna</first><last>Apidianaki</last></author>
      <author><first>Yifan</first><last>He</last></author>
      <pages>219-226</pages>
      <url hash="d5e20ba9">2010.iwslt-papers.2</url>
      <bibkey>apidianaki-he-2010-algorithm</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="3">
      <title>Mining parallel fragments from comparable texts</title>
      <author><first>Mauro</first><last>Cettolo</last></author>
      <author><first>Marcello</first><last>Federico</last></author>
      <author><first>Nicola</first><last>Bertoldi</last></author>
      <pages>227-234</pages>
      <url hash="eac289d4">2010.iwslt-papers.3</url>
      <abstract>This paper proposes a novel method for exploiting comparable documents to generate parallel data for machine translation. First, each source document is paired to each sentence of the corresponding target document; second, partial phrase alignments are computed within the paired texts; finally, fragment pairs across linked phrase-pairs are extracted. The algorithm has been tested on two recent challenging news translation tasks. Results show that mining for parallel fragments is more effective than mining for parallel sentences, and that comparable in-domain texts can be more valuable than parallel out-of-domain texts.</abstract>
      <bibkey>cettolo-etal-2010-mining</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="4">
      <title>Improved <fixed-case>V</fixed-case>ietnamese-<fixed-case>F</fixed-case>rench parallel corpus mining using <fixed-case>E</fixed-case>nglish language</title>
      <author><first>Thi Ngoc Diep</first><last>Do</last></author>
      <author><first>Laurent</first><last>Besacier</last></author>
      <author><first>Eric</first><last>Castelli</last></author>
      <pages>235-242</pages>
      <url hash="3065d41d">2010.iwslt-papers.4</url>
      <bibkey>do-etal-2010-improved</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="5">
      <title>Analysis of translation model adaptation in statistical machine translation</title>
      <author><first>Kevin</first><last>Duh</last></author>
      <author><first>Katsuhito</first><last>Sudoh</last></author>
      <author><first>Hajime</first><last>Tsukada</last></author>
      <pages>243-250</pages>
      <url hash="220e6053">2010.iwslt-papers.5</url>
      <bibkey>duh-etal-2010-analysis</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="6">
      <title>The pay-offs of preprocessing for <fixed-case>G</fixed-case>erman-<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>nglish statistical machine translation</title>
      <author><first>Ilknur Durgar</first><last>El-Kahlout</last></author>
      <author><first>Francois</first><last>Yvon</last></author>
      <pages>251-258</pages>
      <url hash="fdb6dfa3">2010.iwslt-papers.6</url>
      <abstract>In this paper, we present the result of our work on improving the preprocessing for German-English statistical machine translation. We implemented and tested various improvements aimed at i) converting German texts to the new orthographic conventions; ii) performing a new tokenization for German; iii) normalizing lexical redundancy with the help of POS tagging and morphological analysis; iv) splitting German compound words with frequency based algorithm and; v) reducing singletons and out-of-vocabulary words. All these steps are performed during preprocessing on the German side. Combining all these processes, we reduced 10% of the singletons, 2% OOV words, and obtained 1.5 absolute (7% relative) BLEU improvement on the WMT 2010 German to English News translation task.</abstract>
      <bibkey>el-kahlout-yvon-2010-pay</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="7">
      <title>A <fixed-case>B</fixed-case>ayesian model of bilingual segmentation for transliteration</title>
      <author><first>Andrew</first><last>Finch</last></author>
      <author><first>Eiichiro</first><last>Sumita</last></author>
      <pages>259-266</pages>
      <url hash="73238ba2">2010.iwslt-papers.7</url>
      <bibkey>finch-sumita-2010-bayesian</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="8">
      <title>Faster cube pruning</title>
      <author><first>Andrea</first><last>Gesmundo</last></author>
      <author><first>James</first><last>Henderson</last></author>
      <pages>267-274</pages>
      <url hash="a4595fe2">2010.iwslt-papers.8</url>
      <bibkey>gesmundo-henderson-2010-faster</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="9">
      <title>Factor templates for factored machine translation models</title>
      <author><first>Yvette</first><last>Graham</last></author>
      <author><first>Josef</first><last>van Genabith</last></author>
      <pages>275-282</pages>
      <url hash="bb2f16b1">2010.iwslt-papers.9</url>
      <bibkey>graham-van-genabith-2010-factor</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="10">
      <title>Modelling pronominal anaphora in statistical machine translation</title>
      <author><first>Christian</first><last>Hardmeier</last></author>
      <author><first>Marcello</first><last>Federico</last></author>
      <pages>283-289</pages>
      <url hash="ad7e4bc8">2010.iwslt-papers.10</url>
      <abstract>Current Statistical Machine Translation (SMT) systems translate texts sentence by sentence without considering any cross-sentential context. Assuming independence between sentences makes it difficult to take certain translation decisions when the necessary information cannot be determined locally. We argue for the necessity to include crosssentence dependencies in SMT. As a case in point, we study the problem of pronominal anaphora translation by manually evaluating German-English SMT output. We then present a word dependency model for SMT, which can represent links between word pairs in the same or in different sentences. We use this model to integrate the output of a coreference resolution system into English-German SMT with a view to improving the translation of anaphoric pronouns.</abstract>
      <bibkey>hardmeier-federico-2010-modelling</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="11">
      <title>A combination of hierarchical systems with forced alignments from phrase-based systems</title>
      <author><first>Carmen</first><last>Heger</last></author>
      <author><first>Joern</first><last>Wuebker</last></author>
      <author><first>David</first><last>Vilar</last></author>
      <author><first>Hermann</first><last>Ney</last></author>
      <pages>291-297</pages>
      <url hash="81a1908e">2010.iwslt-papers.11</url>
      <abstract>Currently most state-of-the-art statistical machine translation systems present a mismatch between training and generation conditions. Word alignments are computed using the well known IBM models for single-word based translation. Afterwards phrases are extracted using extraction heuristics, unrelated to the stochastic models applied for finding the word alignment. In the last years, several research groups have tried to overcome this mismatch, but only with limited success. Recently, the technique of forced alignments has shown to improve translation quality for a phrase-based system, applying a more statistically sound approach to phrase extraction. In this work we investigate the first steps to combine forced alignment with a hierarchical model. Experimental results on IWSLT and WMT data show improvements in translation quality of up to 0.7% BLEU and 1.0% TER.</abstract>
      <bibkey>heger-etal-2010-combination</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="12">
      <title>Multi-pivot translation by system combination</title>
      <author><first>Gregor</first><last>Leusch</last></author>
      <author><first>Aurélien</first><last>Max</last></author>
      <author><first>Josep Maria</first><last>Crego</last></author>
      <author><first>Hermann</first><last>Ney</last></author>
      <pages>299-306</pages>
      <url hash="57811726">2010.iwslt-papers.12</url>
      <abstract>This paper describes a technique to exploit multiple pivot languages when using machine translation (MT) on language pairs with scarce bilingual resources, or where no translation system for a language pair is available. The principal idea is to generate intermediate translations in several pivot languages, translate them separately into the target language, and generate a consensus translation out of these using MT system combination techniques. Our technique can also be applied when a translation system for a language pair is available, but is limited in its translation accuracy because of scarce resources. Using statistical MT systems for the 11 different languages of Europarl, we show experimentally that a direct translation system can be replaced by this pivot approach without a loss in translation quality if about six pivot languages are available. Furthermore, we can already improve an existing MT system by adding two pivot systems to it. The maximum improvement was found to be 1.4% abs. in BLEU in our experiments for 8 or more pivot languages.</abstract>
      <bibkey>leusch-etal-2010-multi</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="13">
      <title>Real-time spoken language identification and recognition for speech-to-speech translation</title>
      <author><first>Daniel Chung Yong</first><last>Lim</last></author>
      <author><first>Ian</first><last>Lane</last></author>
      <author><first>Alex</first><last>Waibel</last></author>
      <pages>307-312</pages>
      <url hash="6ae69291">2010.iwslt-papers.13</url>
      <bibkey>lim-etal-2010-real</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="14">
      <title>Towards a general and extensible phrase-extraction algorithm</title>
      <author><first>Wang</first><last>Ling</last></author>
      <author><first>Tiago</first><last>Luís</last></author>
      <author><first>João</first><last>Graça</last></author>
      <author><first>Luísa</first><last>Coheur</last></author>
      <author><first>Isabel</first><last>Trancoso</last></author>
      <pages>313-320</pages>
      <url hash="3cddb8d2">2010.iwslt-papers.14</url>
      <abstract>Phrase-based systems deeply depend on the quality of their phrase tables and therefore, the process of phrase extraction is always a fundamental step. In this paper we present a general and extensible phrase extraction algorithm, where we have highlighted several control points. The instantiation of these control points allows the simulation of previous approaches, as in each one of these points different strategies/heuristics can be tested. We show how previous approaches fit in this algorithm, compare several of them and, in addition, we propose alternative heuristics, showing their impact on the final translation results. Considering two different test scenarios from the IWSLT 2010 competition (BTEC, Fr-En and DIALOG, Cn-En), we have obtained an improvement in the results of 2.4 and 2.8 BLEU points, respectively.</abstract>
      <bibkey>ling-etal-2010-towards</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="15">
      <title><fixed-case>M</fixed-case>orph<fixed-case>T</fixed-case>agger: <fixed-case>HMM</fixed-case>-based <fixed-case>A</fixed-case>rabic segmentation for statistical machine translation</title>
      <author><first>Saab</first><last>Mansour</last></author>
      <pages>321-327</pages>
      <url hash="22360126">2010.iwslt-papers.15</url>
      <abstract>In this paper, we investigate different methodologies of Arabic segmentation for statistical machine translation by comparing a rule-based segmenter to different statistically-based segmenters. We also present a new method for segmentation that serves the need for a real-time translation system without impairing the translation accuracy.</abstract>
      <bibkey>mansour-2010-morphtagger</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="16">
      <title>Comparing intrinsic and extrinsic evaluation of <fixed-case>MT</fixed-case> output in a dialogue system</title>
      <author><first>Anne H.</first><last>Schneider</last></author>
      <author><first>Ielka</first><last>van der Sluis</last></author>
      <author><first>Saturnino</first><last>Luz</last></author>
      <pages>329-336</pages>
      <url hash="86bef91a">2010.iwslt-papers.16</url>
      <bibkey>schneider-etal-2010-comparing</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="17">
      <title>Sign language machine translation overkill</title>
      <author><first>Daniel</first><last>Stein</last></author>
      <author><first>Christoph</first><last>Schmidt</last></author>
      <author><first>Hermann</first><last>Ney</last></author>
      <pages>337-344</pages>
      <url hash="890a6a3c">2010.iwslt-papers.17</url>
      <abstract>Sign languages represent an interesting niche for statistical machine translation that is typically hampered by the scarceness of suitable data, and most papers in this area apply only a few, well-known techniques and do not adapt them to small-sized corpora. In this paper, we will propose new methods for common approaches like scaling factor optimization and alignment merging strategies which helped improve our baseline. We also conduct experiments with different decoders and employ state-of-the-art techniques like soft syntactic labels as well as trigger-based and discriminative word lexica and system combination. All methods are evaluated on one of the largest sign language corpora available.</abstract>
      <bibkey>stein-etal-2010-sign</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="18">
      <title>If <fixed-case>I</fixed-case> only had a parser: poor man’s syntax for hierarchical machine translation</title>
      <author><first>David</first><last>Vilar</last></author>
      <author><first>Daniel</first><last>Stein</last></author>
      <author><first>Stephan</first><last>Peitz</last></author>
      <author><first>Hermann</first><last>Ney</last></author>
      <pages>345-352</pages>
      <url hash="df29e607">2010.iwslt-papers.18</url>
      <bibkey>vilar-etal-2010-parser</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="19">
      <title>Dynamic distortion in a discriminative reordering model for statistical machine translation</title>
      <author><first>Sirvan</first><last>Yahyaei</last></author>
      <author><first>Christoph</first><last>Monz</last></author>
      <pages>353-360</pages>
      <url hash="9d77f85d">2010.iwslt-papers.19</url>
      <bibkey>yahyaei-monz-2010-dynamic</bibkey>
    </paper>
  </volume>
</collection>
