<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<collection id="2012.freeopmt">
  <volume id="1" ingest-date="2021-08-22" type="proceedings">
    <meta>
      <booktitle>Proceedings of the Third International Workshop on Free/Open-Source Rule-Based Machine Translation</booktitle>
      <address>Gothenburg, Sweden</address>
      <month>June 13-15</month>
      <year>2012</year>
      <editor><first>Cristina</first><last>España-Bonet</last></editor>
      <editor><first>Aarne</first><last>Ranta</last></editor>
      <venue>freeopmt</venue>
    </meta>
    <frontmatter>
      <url hash="d95dd61c">2012.freeopmt-1.0</url>
      <bibkey>freeopmt-2012-international</bibkey>
    </frontmatter>
    <paper id="1">
      <title>The new machine translation: getting blood from a stone</title>
      <author><first>Martin</first><last>Kay</last></author>
      <url hash="5cc36802">2012.freeopmt-1.1</url>
      <bibkey>kay-2012-new</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="2">
      <title>An <fixed-case>IDE</fixed-case> for the Grammatical Framework</title>
      <author><first>John J.</first><last>Camilleri</last></author>
      <pages>1-12</pages>
      <url hash="b61423c7">2012.freeopmt-1.2</url>
      <abstract>The GF Eclipse Plugin provides an integrated development environment (IDE) for developing grammars in the Grammatical Framework (GF). Built on top of the Eclipse Platform, it aids grammar writing by providing instant syntax checking, semantic warnings and cross-reference resolution. Inline documentation and a library browser facilitate the use of existing resource libraries, and compilation and testing of grammars is greatly improved through single-click launch configurations and an in-built test case manager for running treebank regression tests. This IDE promotes grammar-based systems by making the tasks of writing grammars and using resource libraries more efficient, and provides powerful tools to reduce the barrier to entry to GF and encourage new users of the framework.</abstract>
      <bibkey>camilleri-2012-ide</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="3">
      <title>Evaluating <fixed-case>N</fixed-case>orth <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>ámi to <fixed-case>N</fixed-case>orwegian assimilation <fixed-case>RBMT</fixed-case></title>
      <author><first>Trond</first><last>Trosterud</last></author>
      <author><first>Kevin Brubeck</first><last>Unhammer</last></author>
      <pages>13-26</pages>
      <url hash="ce165c77">2012.freeopmt-1.3</url>
      <bibkey>trosterud-unhammer-2012-evaluating</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="4">
      <title>Choosing the correct paradigm for unknown words in rule-based machine translation systems</title>
      <author><first>V. M.</first><last>Sánchez-Cartagena</last></author>
      <author><first>M.</first><last>Esplà-Gomis</last></author>
      <author><first>F.</first><last>Sánchez-Martínez</last></author>
      <author><first>J. A.</first><last>Pérez-Ortiz</last></author>
      <pages>27-40</pages>
      <url hash="82fc25e3">2012.freeopmt-1.4</url>
      <abstract>Previous work on an interactive system aimed at helping non-expert users to enlarge the monolingual dictionaries of rule-based machine translation (MT) systems worked by discarding those inflection paradigms that cannot generate a set of inflected word forms validated by the user. This method, however, cannot deal with the common case where a set of different paradigms generate exactly the same set of inflected word forms, although with different inflection information attached. In this paper, we propose the use of an n-gram-based model of lexical categories and inflection information to select a single paradigm in cases where more than one paradigm generates the same set of word forms. Results obtained with a Spanish monolingual dictionary show that the correct paradigm is chosen for around 75% of the unknown words, thus making the resulting system (available under an open-source license) of valuable help to enlarge the monolingual dictionaries used in MT involving non-expert users without technical linguistic knowledge.</abstract>
      <bibkey>sanchez-cartagena-etal-2012-choosing</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="5">
      <title>An open-source toolkit for integrating shallow-transfer rules into phrase-based statistical machine translation</title>
      <author><first>V. M.</first><last>Sánchez-Cartagena</last></author>
      <author><first>F.</first><last>Sánchez-Martínez</last></author>
      <author><first>J. A.</first><last>Pérez-Ortiz</last></author>
      <pages>41-54</pages>
      <url hash="e3aca31e">2012.freeopmt-1.5</url>
      <abstract>In this paper, we present an open-source toolkit to enrich a phrase-based statistical machine translation system (Moses) with phrase pairs generated from the linguistic resources of a shallow-transfer rule-based machine translation system (Apertium). A system built with this toolkit was not outperformed by any other participant in the shared translation task of the Sixth Workshop on Statistical Machine Translation (WMT 11) for the Spanish–English language pair.</abstract>
      <bibkey>sanchez-cartagena-etal-2012-open</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="6">
      <title>A rule-based machine translation system from <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>erbo-<fixed-case>C</fixed-case>roatian to <fixed-case>M</fixed-case>acedonian</title>
      <author><first>Hrvoje</first><last>Peradin</last></author>
      <author><first>Francis</first><last>Tyers</last></author>
      <pages>55-64</pages>
      <url hash="87cd4059">2012.freeopmt-1.6</url>
      <abstract>This paper describes the development of a one-way machine translation system from SerboCroatian to Macedonian on the Apertium platform. Details of resources and development methods are given, as well as an evaluation, and general directives for future work.</abstract>
      <bibkey>peradin-tyers-2012-rule</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="7">
      <title>Deep evaluation of hybrid architectures: use of different metrics in <fixed-case>MERT</fixed-case> weight optimization</title>
      <author><first>Cristina</first><last>España-Bonet</last></author>
      <author><first>Gorka</first><last>Labaka</last></author>
      <author><first>Arantza</first><last>Díaz de Ilarranza</last></author>
      <author><first>Lluís</first><last>Màrquez</last></author>
      <author><first>Kepa</first><last>Sarasola</last></author>
      <pages>65-76</pages>
      <url hash="6f32e987">2012.freeopmt-1.7</url>
      <bibkey>espana-bonet-etal-2012-deep</bibkey>
    </paper>
  </volume>
</collection>
