<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<collection id="2020.loresmt">
  <volume id="1" ingest-date="2020-12-02" type="proceedings">
    <meta>
      <booktitle>Proceedings of the 3rd Workshop on Technologies for MT of Low Resource Languages</booktitle>
      <editor><first>Alina</first><last>Karakanta</last></editor>
      <editor><first>Atul Kr.</first><last>Ojha</last></editor>
      <editor><first>Chao-Hong</first><last>Liu</last></editor>
      <editor><first>Jade</first><last>Abbott</last></editor>
      <editor><first>John</first><last>Ortega</last></editor>
      <editor><first>Jonathan</first><last>Washington</last></editor>
      <editor><first>Nathaniel</first><last>Oco</last></editor>
      <editor><first>Surafel Melaku</first><last>Lakew</last></editor>
      <editor><first>Tommi A</first><last>Pirinen</last></editor>
      <editor><first>Valentin</first><last>Malykh</last></editor>
      <editor><first>Varvara</first><last>Logacheva</last></editor>
      <editor><first>Xiaobing</first><last>Zhao</last></editor>
      <publisher>Association for Computational Linguistics</publisher>
      <address>Suzhou, China</address>
      <month>December</month>
      <year>2020</year>
      <venue>loresmt</venue>
    </meta>
    <frontmatter>
      <url hash="c7b02162">2020.loresmt-1.0</url>
      <bibkey>loresmt-2020-technologies</bibkey>
    </frontmatter>
    <paper id="1">
      <title>Overcoming Resistance: The Normalization of an <fixed-case>A</fixed-case>mazonian Tribal Language</title>
      <author><first>John E</first><last>Ortega</last></author>
      <author><first>Richard Alexander</first><last>Castro-Mamani</last></author>
      <author><first>Jaime Rafael</first><last>Montoya Samame</last></author>
      <pages>1–13</pages>
      <abstract>Languages can be considered endangered for many reasons. One of the principal reasons for endangerment is the disappearance of its speakers. Another, more identifiable reason, is the lack of written resources. We present an automated sub-segmentation system called AshMorph that deals with the morphology of an Amazonian tribal language called Ashaninka which is at risk of being endangered due to the lack of availability (or resistance) of native speakers and the absence of written resources. We show that by the use of a cross-lingual lexicon and finite state transducers we can increase accuracy by more than 30% when compared to other modern sub-segmentation tools. Our results, made freely available on-line, are verified by an Ashaninka speaker and perform well in two distinct domains, everyday literary articles and the bible. This research serves as a first step in helping to preserve Ashaninka by offering a sub-segmentation process that can be used to normalize any Ashaninka text which will serve as input to a machine translation system for translation into other high-resource languages spoken by higher populated locations like Spanish and Portuguese in the case of Peru and Brazil where Ashaninka is mostly spoken.</abstract>
      <url hash="8a641aee">2020.loresmt-1.1</url>
      <bibkey>ortega-etal-2020-overcoming</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="2">
      <title>Bridging <fixed-case>P</fixed-case>hilippine Languages With Multilingual Neural Machine Translation</title>
      <author><first>Renz Iver</first><last>Baliber</last></author>
      <author><first>Charibeth</first><last>Cheng</last></author>
      <author><first>Kristine Mae</first><last>Adlaon</last></author>
      <author><first>Virgion</first><last>Mamonong</last></author>
      <pages>14–22</pages>
      <abstract>The Philippines is home to more than 150 languages that is considered to be low-resourced even on its major languages. This results into a lack of pursuit in developing a translation system for the underrepresented languages. To simplify the process of developing translation system for multiple languages, and to aid in improving the translation quality of zero to low-resource languages, multilingual NMT became an active area of research. However, existing works in multilingual NMT disregards the analysis of a multilingual model on a closely related and low-resource language group in the context of pivot-based translation and zero-shot translation. In this paper, we benchmarked translation for several Philippine Languages, provided an analysis of a multilingual NMT system for morphologically rich and low-resource languages in terms of its effectiveness in translating zero-resource languages with zero-shot translations. To further evaluate the capability of the multilingual NMT model in translating unseen language pairs in training, we tested the model to translate between Tagalog and Cebuano and compared its performance with a simple NMT model that is directly trained on a parallel Tagalog and Cebuano data in which we showed that zero-shot translation outperforms a directly trained model in some instances, while utilizing English as a pivot language in translating outperform both approaches.</abstract>
      <url hash="947402a7">2020.loresmt-1.2</url>
      <bibkey>baliber-etal-2020-bridging</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="3">
      <title>Neural Machine Translation for Extremely Low-Resource <fixed-case>A</fixed-case>frican Languages: A Case Study on <fixed-case>B</fixed-case>ambara</title>
      <author><first>Allahsera Auguste</first><last>Tapo</last></author>
      <author><first>Bakary</first><last>Coulibaly</last></author>
      <author><first>Sébastien</first><last>Diarra</last></author>
      <author><first>Christopher</first><last>Homan</last></author>
      <author><first>Julia</first><last>Kreutzer</last></author>
      <author><first>Sarah</first><last>Luger</last></author>
      <author><first>Arthur</first><last>Nagashima</last></author>
      <author><first>Marcos</first><last>Zampieri</last></author>
      <author><first>Michael</first><last>Leventhal</last></author>
      <pages>23–32</pages>
      <abstract>Low-resource languages present unique challenges to (neural) machine translation. We discuss the case of Bambara, a Mande language for which training data is scarce and requires significant amounts of pre-processing. More than the linguistic situation of Bambara itself, the socio-cultural context within which Bambara speakers live poses challenges for automated processing of this language. In this paper, we present the first parallel data set for machine translation of Bambara into and from English and French and the first benchmark results on machine translation to and from Bambara. We discuss challenges in working with low-resource languages and propose strategies to cope with data scarcity in low-resource machine translation (MT).</abstract>
      <url hash="d6d19c2d">2020.loresmt-1.3</url>
      <bibkey>tapo-etal-2020-neural</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="4">
      <title>Findings of the <fixed-case>L</fixed-case>o<fixed-case>R</fixed-case>es<fixed-case>MT</fixed-case> 2020 Shared Task on Zero-Shot for Low-Resource languages</title>
      <author><first>Atul Kr.</first><last>Ojha</last></author>
      <author><first>Valentin</first><last>Malykh</last></author>
      <author><first>Alina</first><last>Karakanta</last></author>
      <author><first>Chao-Hong</first><last>Liu</last></author>
      <pages>33–37</pages>
      <abstract>This paper presents the findings of the LoResMT 2020 Shared Task on zero-shot translation for low resource languages. This task was organised as part of the 3rd Workshop on Technologies for MT of Low Resource Languages (LoResMT) at AACL-IJCNLP 2020. The focus was on the zero-shot approach as a notable development in Neural Machine Translation to build MT systems for language pairs where parallel corpora are small or even non-existent. The shared task experience suggests that back-translation and domain adaptation methods result in better accuracy for small-size datasets. We further noted that, although translation between similar languages is no cakewalk, linguistically distinct languages require more data to give better results.</abstract>
      <url hash="4c23d3af">2020.loresmt-1.4</url>
      <bibkey>ojha-etal-2020-findings</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="5">
      <title>Zero-Shot Neural Machine Translation: <fixed-case>R</fixed-case>ussian-<fixed-case>H</fixed-case>indi @<fixed-case>L</fixed-case>o<fixed-case>R</fixed-case>es<fixed-case>MT</fixed-case> 2020</title>
      <author><first>Sahinur Rahman</first><last>Laskar</last></author>
      <author><first>Abdullah Faiz Ur Rahman</first><last>Khilji</last></author>
      <author><first>Partha</first><last>Pakray</last></author>
      <author><first>Sivaji</first><last>Bandyopadhyay</last></author>
      <pages>38–42</pages>
      <abstract>Neural machine translation (NMT) is a widely accepted approach in the machine translation (MT) community, translating from one natural language to another natural language. Although, NMT shows remarkable performance in both high and low resource languages, it needs sufficient training corpus. The availability of a parallel corpus in low resource language pairs is one of the challenging tasks in MT. To mitigate this issue, NMT attempts to utilize a monolingual corpus to get better at translation for low resource language pairs. Workshop on Technologies for MT of Low Resource Languages (LoResMT 2020) organized shared tasks of low resource language pair translation using zero-shot NMT. Here, the parallel corpus is not used and only monolingual corpora is allowed. We have participated in the same shared task with our team name CNLP-NITS for the Russian-Hindi language pair. We have used masked sequence to sequence pre-training for language generation (MASS) with only monolingual corpus following the unsupervised NMT architecture. The evaluated results are declared at the LoResMT 2020 shared task, which reports that our system achieves the bilingual evaluation understudy (BLEU) score of 0.59, precision score of 3.43, recall score of 5.48, F-measure score of 4.22, and rank-based intuitive bilingual evaluation score (RIBES) of 0.180147 in Russian to Hindi translation. And for Hindi to Russian translation, we have achieved BLEU, precision, recall, F-measure, and RIBES score of 1.11, 4.72, 4.41, 4.56, and 0.026842 respectively.</abstract>
      <url hash="b77fd717">2020.loresmt-1.5</url>
      <bibkey>laskar-etal-2020-zero</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="6">
      <title>Unsupervised Approach for Zero-Shot Experiments: <fixed-case>B</fixed-case>hojpuri–<fixed-case>H</fixed-case>indi and <fixed-case>M</fixed-case>agahi–<fixed-case>H</fixed-case>indi@<fixed-case>L</fixed-case>o<fixed-case>R</fixed-case>es<fixed-case>MT</fixed-case> 2020</title>
      <author><first>Amit</first><last>Kumar</last></author>
      <author><first>Rajesh Kumar</first><last>Mundotiya</last></author>
      <author><first>Anil Kumar</first><last>Singh</last></author>
      <pages>43–46</pages>
      <abstract>This paper reports a Machine Translation (MT) system submitted by the NLPRL team for the Bhojpuri–Hindi and Magahi–Hindi language pairs at LoResMT 2020 shared task. We used an unsupervised domain adaptation approach that gives promising results for zero or extremely low resource languages. Task organizers provide the development and the test sets for evaluation and the monolingual data for training. Our approach is a hybrid approach of domain adaptation and back-translation. Metrics used to evaluate the trained model are BLEU, RIBES, Precision, Recall and F-measure. Our approach gives relatively promising results, with a wide range, of 19.5, 13.71, 2.54, and 3.16 BLEU points for Bhojpuri to Hindi, Magahi to Hindi, Hindi to Bhojpuri and Hindi to Magahi language pairs, respectively.</abstract>
      <url hash="63ed8bbc">2020.loresmt-1.6</url>
      <bibkey>kumar-etal-2020-unsupervised</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="7">
      <title>Zero-shot translation among <fixed-case>I</fixed-case>ndian languages</title>
      <author><first>Rudali</first><last>Huidrom</last></author>
      <author><first>Yves</first><last>Lepage</last></author>
      <pages>47–54</pages>
      <abstract>Standard neural machine translation (NMT) allows a model to perform translation between a pair of languages. Multilingual neural machine translation (NMT), on the other hand, allows a model to perform translation between several language pairs, even between language pairs for which no sentences pair has been seen during training (zero-shot translation). This paper presents experiments with zero-shot translation on low resource Indian languages with a very small amount of data for each language pair. We first report results on balanced data over all considered language pairs. We then expand our experiments for additional three rounds by increasing the training data with 2,000 sentence pairs in each round for some of the language pairs. We obtain an increase in translation accuracy with its balanced data settings score multiplied by 7 for Manipuri to Hindi during Round-III of zero-shot translation.</abstract>
      <url hash="d1bd8f70">2020.loresmt-1.7</url>
      <bibkey>huidrom-lepage-2020-zero</bibkey>
      <pwcdataset url="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/pmindia">PMIndia</pwcdataset>
    </paper>
    <paper id="8">
      <title>Improving Multilingual Neural Machine Translation For Low-Resource Languages: <fixed-case>F</fixed-case>rench, <fixed-case>E</fixed-case>nglish - <fixed-case>V</fixed-case>ietnamese</title>
      <author><first>Thi-Vinh</first><last>Ngo</last></author>
      <author><first>Phuong-Thai</first><last>Nguyen</last></author>
      <author><first>Thanh-Le</first><last>Ha</last></author>
      <author><first>Khac-Quy</first><last>Dinh</last></author>
      <author><first>Le-Minh</first><last>Nguyen</last></author>
      <pages>55–61</pages>
      <abstract>Prior works have demonstrated that a low-resource language pair can benefit from multilingual machine translation (MT) systems, which rely on many language pairs’ joint training. This paper proposes two simple strategies to address the rare word issue in multilingual MT systems for two low-resource language pairs: French-Vietnamese and English-Vietnamese. The first strategy is about dynamical learning word similarity of tokens in the shared space among source languages while another one attempts to augment the translation ability of rare words through updating their embeddings during the training. Besides, we leverage monolingual data for multilingual MT systems to increase the amount of synthetic parallel corpora while dealing with the data sparsity problem. We have shown significant improvements of up to +1.62 and +2.54 BLEU points over the bilingual baseline systems for both language pairs and released our datasets for the research community.</abstract>
      <url hash="9743bbb3">2020.loresmt-1.8</url>
      <bibkey>ngo-etal-2020-improving</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="9">
      <title><fixed-case>E</fixed-case>n<fixed-case>A</fixed-case>s<fixed-case>C</fixed-case>orp1.0: <fixed-case>E</fixed-case>nglish-<fixed-case>A</fixed-case>ssamese Corpus</title>
      <author><first>Sahinur Rahman</first><last>Laskar</last></author>
      <author><first>Abdullah Faiz Ur Rahman</first><last>Khilji</last></author>
      <author><first>Partha</first><last>Pakray</last></author>
      <author><first>Sivaji</first><last>Bandyopadhyay</last></author>
      <pages>62–68</pages>
      <abstract>The corpus preparation is one of the important challenging task for the domain of machine translation especially in low resource language scenarios. Country like India where multiple languages exists, machine translation attempts to minimize the communication gap among people with different linguistic backgrounds. Although Google Translation covers automatic translation of various languages all over the world but it lags in some languages including Assamese. In this paper, we have developed EnAsCorp1.0, corpus of English-Assamese low resource pair where parallel and monolingual data are collected from various online sources. We have also implemented baseline systems with statistical machine translation and neural machine translation approaches for the same corpus.</abstract>
      <url hash="cfd86f51">2020.loresmt-1.9</url>
      <bibkey>laskar-etal-2020-enascorp1</bibkey>
      <pwcdataset url="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/pmindia">PMIndia</pwcdataset>
    </paper>
    <paper id="10">
      <title>Unsupervised Neural Machine Translation for <fixed-case>E</fixed-case>nglish and <fixed-case>M</fixed-case>anipuri</title>
      <author><first>Salam Michael</first><last>Singh</last></author>
      <author><first>Thoudam Doren</first><last>Singh</last></author>
      <pages>69–78</pages>
      <abstract>Availability of bitext dataset has been a key challenge in the conventional machine translation system which requires surplus amount of parallel data. In this work, we devise an unsupervised neural machine translation (UNMT) system consisting of a transformer based shared encoder and language specific decoders using denoising autoencoder and backtranslation with an additional Manipuri side multiple test reference. We report our work on low resource setting for English (en) - Manipuri (mni) language pair and attain a BLEU score of 3.1 for en-mni and 2.7 for mni-en respectively. Subjective evaluation on translated output gives encouraging findings.</abstract>
      <url hash="83c21583">2020.loresmt-1.10</url>
      <bibkey>singh-singh-2020-unsupervised</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="11">
      <title>Effective Architectures for Low Resource Multilingual Named Entity Transliteration</title>
      <author><first>Molly</first><last>Moran</last></author>
      <author><first>Constantine</first><last>Lignos</last></author>
      <pages>79–86</pages>
      <abstract>In this paper, we evaluate LSTM, biLSTM, GRU, and Transformer architectures for the task of name transliteration in a many-to-one multilingual paradigm, transliterating from 590 languages to English. We experiment with different encoder-decoder combinations and evaluate them using accuracy, character error rate, and an F-measure based on longest continuous subsequences. We find that using a Transformer for the encoder and decoder performs best, improving accuracy by over 4 points compared to previous work. We explore whether manipulating the source text by adding macrolanguage flag tokens or pre-romanizing source strings can improve performance and find that neither manipulation has a positive effect. Finally, we analyze performance differences between the LSTM and Transformer encoders when using a Transformer decoder and find that the Transformer encoder is better able to handle insertions and substitutions when transliterating.</abstract>
      <url hash="235d11d6">2020.loresmt-1.11</url>
      <bibkey>moran-lignos-2020-effective</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="12">
      <title>Towards Machine Translation for the <fixed-case>K</fixed-case>urdish Language</title>
      <author><first>Sina</first><last>Ahmadi</last></author>
      <author><first>Maraim</first><last>Masoud</last></author>
      <pages>87–98</pages>
      <abstract>Machine translation is the task of translating texts from one language to another using computers. It has been one of the major tasks in natural language processing and computational linguistics and has been motivating to facilitate human communication. Kurdish, an Indo-European language, has received little attention in this realm due to the language being less-resourced. Therefore, in this paper, we are addressing the main issues in creating a machine translation system for the Kurdish language, with a focus on the Sorani dialect. We describe the available scarce parallel data suitable for training a neural machine translation model for Sorani Kurdish-English translation. We also discuss some of the major challenges in Kurdish language translation and demonstrate how fundamental text processing tasks, such as tokenization, can improve translation performance.</abstract>
      <url hash="a37f9948">2020.loresmt-1.12</url>
      <bibkey>ahmadi-masoud-2020-towards</bibkey>
      <pwccode url="https://github.com/sinaahmadi/KurdishMT" additional="false">sinaahmadi/KurdishMT</pwccode>
    </paper>
    <paper id="13">
      <title><fixed-case>A</fixed-case>n Ensemble Method for Producing Word Representations focusing on the <fixed-case>G</fixed-case>reek Language</title>
      <author><first>Michalis</first><last>Lioudakis</last></author>
      <author><first>Stamatis</first><last>Outsios</last></author>
      <author><first>Michalis</first><last>Vazirgiannis</last></author>
      <pages>99–107</pages>
      <abstract>In this paper we present a new ensemble method, Continuous Bag-of-Skip-grams (CBOS), that produces high-quality word representations putting emphasis on the Greek language. The CBOS method combines the pioneering approaches for learning word representations: Continuous Bag-of-Words (CBOW) and Continuous Skip-gram. These methods are compared through intrinsic and extrinsic evaluation tasks on three different sources of data: the English Wikipedia corpus, the Greek Wikipedia corpus, and the Greek Web Content corpus. By comparing these methods across different tasks and datasets, it is evident that the CBOS method achieves state-of-the-art performance.</abstract>
      <url hash="d9fb6e2a">2020.loresmt-1.13</url>
      <bibkey>lioudakis-etal-2020-ensemble</bibkey>
      <pwccode url="https://github.com/mikeliou/greek_word_embeddings" additional="false">mikeliou/greek_word_embeddings</pwccode>
    </paper>
    <paper id="14">
      <title>Using Multiple Subwords to Improve <fixed-case>E</fixed-case>nglish-<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>speranto Automated Literary Translation Quality</title>
      <author><first>Alberto</first><last>Poncelas</last></author>
      <author><first>Jan</first><last>Buts</last></author>
      <author><first>James</first><last>Hadley</last></author>
      <author><first>Andy</first><last>Way</last></author>
      <pages>108–117</pages>
      <abstract>Building Machine Translation (MT) systems for low-resource languages remains challenging. For many language pairs, parallel data are not widely available, and in such cases MT models do not achieve results comparable to those seen with high-resource languages. When data are scarce, it is of paramount importance to make optimal use of the limited material available. To that end, in this paper we propose employing the same parallel sentences multiple times, only changing the way the words are split each time. For this purpose we use several Byte Pair Encoding models, with various merge operations used in their configuration. In our experiments, we use this technique to expand the available data and improve an MT system involving a low-resource language pair, namely English-Esperanto. As an additional contribution, we made available a set of English-Esperanto parallel data in the literary domain.</abstract>
      <url hash="b7083b66">2020.loresmt-1.14</url>
      <bibkey>poncelas-etal-2020-using</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="15">
      <title>Investigating Low-resource Machine Translation for <fixed-case>E</fixed-case>nglish-to-<fixed-case>T</fixed-case>amil</title>
      <author><first>Akshai</first><last>Ramesh</last></author>
      <author><first>Venkatesh</first><last>Balavadhani parthasa</last></author>
      <author><first>Rejwanul</first><last>Haque</last></author>
      <author><first>Andy</first><last>Way</last></author>
      <pages>118–125</pages>
      <abstract>Statistical machine translation (SMT) which was the dominant paradigm in machine translation (MT) research for nearly three decades has recently been superseded by the end-to-end deep learning approaches to MT. Although deep neural models produce state-of-the-art results in many translation tasks, they are found to under-perform on resource-poor scenarios. Despite some success, none of the present-day benchmarks that have tried to overcome this problem can be regarded as a universal solution to the problem of translation of many low-resource languages. In this work, we investigate the performance of phrase-based SMT (PB-SMT) and neural MT (NMT) on a rarely-tested low-resource language-pair, English-to-Tamil, taking a specialised data domain (software localisation) into consideration. In particular, we produce rankings of our MT systems via a social media platform-based human evaluation scheme, and demonstrate our findings in the low-resource domain-specific text translation task.</abstract>
      <url hash="89533ef3">2020.loresmt-1.15</url>
      <bibkey>ramesh-etal-2020-investigating</bibkey>
    </paper>
  </volume>
</collection>
