<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<collection id="2020.dnd">
  <volume id="11" type="journal" ingest-date="2026-04-20">
    <meta>
      <booktitle>Dialogue Discourse Volume 11</booktitle>
      <editor><first>Massimo</first><last>Poesio</last></editor>
      <editor><first>Manfred</first><last>Stede</last></editor>
      <editor><first>Amanda</first><last>Stent</last></editor>
      <editor><first>Jonathan</first><last>Ginzburg</last></editor>
      <editor><first>Vera</first><last>Demberg</last></editor>
      <editor><first>Amir</first><last>Zeldes</last></editor>
      <publisher>University of Illinois Chicago</publisher>
      <address>Chicago, Illinois, USA</address>
      <year>2020</year>
      <venue>dnd</venue>
      <journal-volume>11</journal-volume>
    </meta>
    <paper id="1">
      <title>Please, Please, Just Tell Me: The Linguistic Features of Humorous Deception</title>
      <author><first>Stephen</first><last>Skalicky</last></author>
      <author><first>Nicholas</first><last>Duran</last></author>
      <author><first>Scott A</first><last>Crossley</last></author>
      <pages>128-149</pages>
      <abstract>Prior research undertaken for the purpose of identifying deceptive language has focused on deception as it is used for nefarious ends, such as purposeful lying. However, despite the intent to mislead, not all examples of deception are carried out for malevolent ends. In this study, we describe the linguistic features of humorous deception. Specifically, we analyzed the linguistic features of 753 news stories, 1/3 of which were truthful and 2/3 of which we categorized as examples of humorous deception. The news stories we analyzed occurred naturally as part of a segment named Bluff the Listener on the popular American radio quiz show Wait, Wait...Don’t Tell Me!. Using a combination of supervised learning and predictive modeling, we identified 11 linguistic features accounting for approximately 18% of the variance between humorous deception and truthful news stories. These linguistic features suggested the deceptive news stories were more confident and descriptive but also less cohesive when compared to the truthful new stories. We suggest these findings reflect the dual communicative goal of this unique type of discourse to simultaneously deceive and be humorous.</abstract>
      <url hash="54a73d2c">2020.dnd-11.1</url>
      <doi>10.5210/dad.2020.205</doi>
      <bibkey>skalicky-etal-2020-please</bibkey>
      <month>December</month>
    </paper>
    <paper id="2">
      <title>Demonstrative Pronouns as Anti-Logophoric Pronouns: An Experimental Investigation</title>
      <author><first>Stefan</first><last>Hinterwimmer</last></author>
      <author><first>Andreas</first><last>Brocher</last></author>
      <author><first>Umesh</first><last>Patil</last></author>
      <pages>110-127</pages>
      <abstract>In this paper we report the results of two experimental studies in which we tested the claim of Hinterwimmer and Bosch (2017) that German demonstrative pronouns are anti-logophoric pronouns: They avoid discourse referents as antecedents that function as perspectival centers. In both experiments we tested the interpretative options of demonstrative pronouns in text segments which were either perspectivally neutral or in which the narrator’s or a topical protagonist’s perspective was foregrounded. Taken together, the experimental results are most compatible with a slightly modified version of the analysis argued for in Hinterwimmer and Bosch (2017) according to which topical discourse referents in neutral narration automatically become perspectival centers.</abstract>
      <url hash="7f507302">2020.dnd-11.2</url>
      <doi>10.5087/dad.2020.204</doi>
      <bibkey>hinterwimmer-etal-2020-demonstrative</bibkey>
      <month>October</month>
    </paper>
    <paper id="3">
      <title>Lexical and contextual cue effects in discourse expectations: Experimenting with <fixed-case>G</fixed-case>erman ’zwar...aber’ and <fixed-case>E</fixed-case>nglish ’true/sure...but’</title>
      <author><first>Juliane</first><last>Schwab</last></author>
      <author><first>Mingya</first><last>Liu</last></author>
      <pages>74-109</pages>
      <abstract>Existing literature shows that readers and listeners rapidly adjust their expectations about likely discourse continuations through discourse markers, as well as through other linguistic and extra-linguistic cues. However, it is unclear whether (i) the facilitative effects of various (extra-)linguistic cues differ in quality and (ii) whether the effects interact with one another in any principled manner. We conducted two self-paced reading experiments on concessive constructions in German and English wherein optional lexical and/or contextual cues appeared ahead of the concessive discourse marker. The results demonstrate that readers can use both types of cues to anticipate the upcoming discourse relation. Our study thus provides novel evidence for expectation-driven accounts of discourse processing and elucidates the functions of discourse signals. Furthermore, the results also show that the role that a type of cues plays is subject to cross-linguistic variation.</abstract>
      <url hash="27d94b33">2020.dnd-11.3</url>
      <doi>10.5087/dad.2020.203</doi>
      <bibkey>schwab-liu-2020-lexical</bibkey>
      <month>August</month>
    </paper>
    <paper id="4">
      <title>From Discursive Practice to Logic? Remarks on Logical Expressivism</title>
      <author><first>Rodger</first><last>Kibble</last></author>
      <pages>34-73</pages>
      <abstract>This paper proposes a novel account of the conditional locution as grounded in practices of goal- directed cooperative dialogue. It is argued that a conditional semantics can be obtained within a language fragment that lacks this locution, but supports assertive, inferential and directive prac- tices. We take Brandom’s logical expressivist programme as a point of departure, but argue that this programme is empirically flawed as it underestimates the pervasive context-dependence of linguistic items including logical vocabulary. We further take issue with his claim that a discursive practice involving only assertion and inference is sufficient for the conservative introduction and deployment of conditional vocabulary. A more promising route is provided by the introduction of directives, as in so-called “pseudo-imperatives” such as Get individuals to invest their time and the funding will follow: this has a conditional sense that if individuals invest their time, then funding will follow. We propose a semantic analysis for these forms which builds on Kukla and Lance’s account of prescriptives, and argue that our analysis more faithfully captures the “irrealis” nature of conditionals. The analysis is presented in terms of an information-state based dialogue model, with the information state comprising a partitioned commitment store. It is argued that our “dialogical” analysis of conditional reasoning is faithful to Brandom’s Sellarsian intuition of linguistic practice as a game of giving and asking for reasons. We conclude by contextualising and situating Brandom’s programme against the larger field of practice theory, by means of a comparison with the works of sociologist, anthropologist and philosopher Pierre Bourdieu, and suggest that this com- parison reveals further challenges to the expressivist programme. We also take note of Narasimhan et al’s recent proposals for agent-based modelling of social practice theory as a possible basis for future development.</abstract>
      <url hash="3a35e8c5">2020.dnd-11.4</url>
      <doi>10.5087/dad.2020.202</doi>
      <bibkey>kibble-2020-discursive</bibkey>
      <month>August</month>
    </paper>
    <paper id="5">
      <title>A Neural Approach to Discourse Relation Signal Detection</title>
      <author><first>Amir</first><last>Zeldes</last></author>
      <author><first>Yang</first><last>Liu</last></author>
      <pages>1-33</pages>
      <abstract>Previous data-driven work investigating the types and distributions of discourse relation signals, including discourse markers such as ’however’ or phrases such as ’as a result’ has focused on the relative frequencies of signal words within and outside text from each discourse relation. Such approaches do not allow us to quantify the signaling strength of individual instances of a signal on a scale (e.g. more or less discourse-relevant instances of ’and’), to assess the distribution of ambiguity for signals, or to identify words that hinder discourse relation identification in context (’anti-signals’ or ’distractors’). In this paper we present a data-driven approach to signal detection using a distantly supervised neural network and develop a metric, Δs (or ’delta-softmax’), to quantify signaling strength. Ranging between -1 and 1 and relying on recent advances in contextualized words embeddings, the metric represents each word’s positive or negative contribution to the identifiability of a relation in specific instances in context. Based on an English corpus annotated for discourse relations using Rhetorical Structure Theory and signal type annotations anchored to specific tokens, our analysis examines the reliability of the metric, the places where it overlaps with and differs from human judgments, and the implications for identifying features that neural models may need in order to perform better on automatic discourse relation classification.</abstract>
      <url hash="ffb06b02">2020.dnd-11.5</url>
      <doi>10.5087/dad.2020.201</doi>
      <bibkey>zeldes-liu-2020-neural</bibkey>
      <month>July</month>
    </paper>
    <paper id="6">
      <title>Modelling Structures for Situated Discourse</title>
      <author><first>Nicholas</first><last>Asher</last></author>
      <author><first>Julie</first><last>Hunter</last></author>
      <author><first>Kate</first><last>Thompson</last></author>
      <pages>89-121</pages>
      <abstract>This paper describes a corpus of situated multiparty chats developed for the STAC project (Strategic Conversation, ERC grant n. 269427). and annotated for discourse structure in the style of Segmented Discourse Representation Theory (SDRT; Asher &amp; Lascarides,2003). The STAC corpus is not only a rich source of data on strategic conversation, but also the first corpus that we are aware of that provides discourse structures for multiparty dialogues situated within a virtual environment. The corpus was annotated in two stages: we initially annotated the chat moves only, but later decided to annotate interactions between the chat moves and non-linguistic events from the virtual environment. This two-step procedure has allowed us quantify various ways in which adding information from the nonlinguistic context affects dialogue structure. In this paper, we look at how annotations based only on linguistic information were preserved once the nonlinguistic context was factored in. We explain that while the preservation of relation instances is relatively high when we move from one corpus to the other, there is little preservation of higher order structures that capture "the main point" of a dialogue and distinguish it from peripheral information.</abstract>
      <url hash="2f258fae">2020.dnd-11.6</url>
      <doi>10.5087/dad.2020.104</doi>
      <bibkey>asher-etal-2020-modelling</bibkey>
      <month>March</month>
    </paper>
    <paper id="7">
      <title>The Use of Perspective Markers and Connectives in Expressing Subjectivity: Evidence from Collocational Analyses</title>
      <author><first>Yipu</first><last>Wei</last></author>
      <author><first>Jacqueline</first><last>Evers-Vermeul</last></author>
      <author><first>Ted J.M.</first><last>Sanders</last></author>
      <pages>62-88</pages>
      <abstract>This study explores how subjectivity is expressed in coherence relations, by means of a distinctive collocational analysis on two Chinese causal connectives: the specific subjective kejian ‘so’, used in subjective argument-claim relations, and the underspecified suoyi ‘so’, which can be used in both subjective argument-claim and objective cause-consequence relations. On the basis of both Horn’s pragmatic Relation and Quality principles and the Uniform Information Density Theory, we hypothesized that the presence of other linguistic elements expressing subjectivity in a discourse segment should be related the degree of subjectivity encoded by the connective. In line with this hypothesis, the association scores showed that suoyi is more frequently combined with perspective markers expressing epistemic stance: cognition verbs and modal verbs. Kejian, which already expresses epistemic stance, co-occurred more often with perspective markers related to attitudinal stance, such as markers of expectedness and importance. The paper also pays attention to similarities and differences in collocation patterns across contexts and genres.</abstract>
      <url hash="06ddd128">2020.dnd-11.7</url>
      <doi>10.5087/dad.2020.103</doi>
      <bibkey>wei-etal-2020-use</bibkey>
      <month>March</month>
    </paper>
    <paper id="8">
      <title>Signaling of Causal Relations in <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>panish: Variety, Functionality, and Specificity</title>
      <author><first>Romualdo</first><last>Ibáñez</last></author>
      <author><first>Fernando</first><last>Moncada</last></author>
      <author><first>Benjamín</first><last>Cárcamo</last></author>
      <author><first>Valentina</first><last>Marín</last></author>
      <pages>40-61</pages>
      <abstract>While some recent studies on Spanish have shown that some causal discourse markers specialize in expressing certain types of causal relations, others have revealed that causal relations may be signaled by a variety of linguistic devices. Given that we were interested not only in specificity and variety, but also in the (poly) functionality of signals, our objective in the present study was threefold. First, to identify the variety of markers used to signal causal relations in Spanish. Second, to describe the (poly) functionality of those causal markers. Third, to determine whether there exists a relationship of specificity between markers and particular types of causal relations. We analyzed a corpus of 2,514 causal coherence relations previously annotated. 40 different linguistic devices used to signal causal relations were identified. These devices were grouped into two main classes: Discourse Markers and Cue Phrases. Regarding the (poly) functionality of the markers, we found that 8 of the most frequent markers were used to signal different relations. Regarding specificity, it was observed that various conjunctions and conjunctive adverbs specialize in signaling specific relations.</abstract>
      <url hash="ac1c3ae6">2020.dnd-11.8</url>
      <doi>10.5087/dad.2020.102</doi>
      <bibkey>ibanez-etal-2020-signaling</bibkey>
      <month>March</month>
    </paper>
    <paper id="9">
      <title>The timing of prominence information during the resolution of <fixed-case>G</fixed-case>erman personal and demonstrative pronouns</title>
      <author><first>Clare</first><last>Patterson</last></author>
      <author><first>Petra</first><last>Schumacher</last></author>
      <pages>1-39</pages>
      <abstract>German personal and demonstrative pronouns have distinct preferences in their interpretation; personal pronouns are more flexible in their interpretation but tend to resolve to a prominent antecedent, while demonstratives have a strong preference for a non-prominent antecedent. However, less is known about how prominence information is used during the process of resolution, particularly in the light of two- stage processing models which assume that reference will normally be to the most accessible candidate. We conducted three experiments investigating how prominence information is used during the resolution of gender-disambiguated personal and demonstrative pronouns in German. While the demonstrative pronoun required additional processing compared to the personal pronoun, prominence information did not affect resolution in shallow conditions. It did, however, affect resolution under deep processing conditions. We conclude that prominence information is not ruled out by the presence of stronger resolution cues such as gender. However, the deployment of prominence information in the evaluation of candidate antecedents is under strategic control.</abstract>
      <url hash="946b45e2">2020.dnd-11.9</url>
      <doi>10.5087/dad.2020.101</doi>
      <bibkey>patterson-schumacher-2020-timing</bibkey>
      <month>March</month>
    </paper>
  </volume>
</collection>
