<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<collection id="2020.wac">
  <volume id="1">
    <meta>
      <booktitle>Proceedings of the 12th Web as Corpus Workshop</booktitle>
      <editor><first>Adrien</first><last>Barbaresi</last></editor>
      <editor><first>Felix</first><last>Bildhauer</last></editor>
      <editor><first>Roland</first><last>Schäfer</last></editor>
      <editor><first>Egon</first><last>Stemle</last></editor>
      <publisher>European Language Resources Association</publisher>
      <address>Marseille, France</address>
      <month>May</month>
      <year>2020</year>
      <isbn>979-10-95546-68-9</isbn>
    </meta>
    <frontmatter>
      <url hash="62332e65">2020.wac-1.0</url>
    </frontmatter>
    <paper id="1">
      <title>Current Challenges in Web Corpus Building</title>
      <author><first>Miloš</first><last>Jakubíček</last></author>
      <author><first>Vojtěch</first><last>Kovář</last></author>
      <author><first>Pavel</first><last>Rychlý</last></author>
      <author><first>Vit</first><last>Suchomel</last></author>
      <pages>1–4</pages>
      <abstract>In this paper we discuss some of the current challenges in web corpus building that we faced in the recent years when expanding the corpora in Sketch Engine. The purpose of the paper is to provide an overview and raise discussion on possible solutions, rather than bringing ready solutions to the readers. For every issue we try to assess its severity and briefly discuss possible mitigation options.</abstract>
      <url hash="41af0837">2020.wac-1.1</url>
      <language>eng</language>
    </paper>
    <paper id="2">
      <title>Out-of-the-Box and into the Ditch? Multilingual Evaluation of Generic Text Extraction Tools</title>
      <author><first>Adrien</first><last>Barbaresi</last></author>
      <author><first>Gaël</first><last>Lejeune</last></author>
      <pages>5–13</pages>
      <abstract>This article examines extraction methods designed to retain the main text content of web pages and discusses how the extraction could be oriented and evaluated: can and should it be as generic as possible to ensure opportunistic corpus construction? The evaluation grounds on a comparative benchmark of open-source tools used on pages in five different languages (Chinese, English, Greek, Polish and Russian), it features several metrics to obtain more fine-grained differentiations. Our experiments highlight the diversity of web page layouts across languages or publishing countries. These discrepancies are reflected by diverging performances so that the right tool has to be chosen accordingly.</abstract>
      <url hash="577e1e37">2020.wac-1.2</url>
      <language>eng</language>
    </paper>
    <paper id="3">
      <title>From Web Crawl to Clean Register-Annotated Corpora</title>
      <author><first>Veronika</first><last>Laippala</last></author>
      <author><first>Samuel</first><last>Rönnqvist</last></author>
      <author><first>Saara</first><last>Hellström</last></author>
      <author><first>Juhani</first><last>Luotolahti</last></author>
      <author><first>Liina</first><last>Repo</last></author>
      <author><first>Anna</first><last>Salmela</last></author>
      <author><first>Valtteri</first><last>Skantsi</last></author>
      <author><first>Sampo</first><last>Pyysalo</last></author>
      <pages>14–22</pages>
      <abstract>The web presents unprecedented opportunities for large-scale collection of text in many languages. However, two critical steps in the development of web corpora remain challenging: the identification of clean text from source HTML and the assignment of genre or register information to the documents. In this paper, we evaluate a multilingual approach to this end. Our starting points are the Swedish and French Common Crawl datasets gathered for the 2017 CoNLL shared task, particularly the URLs. We 1) fetch HTML pages based on the URLs and run boilerplate removal, 2) train a classifier to further clean out undesired text fragments, and 3) annotate text registers. We compare boilerplate removal against the CoNLL texts, and find an improvement. For the further cleaning of undesired material, the best results are achieved using Multilingual BERT with monolingual fine-tuning. However, our results are promising also in a cross-lingual setting, without fine-tuning on the target language. Finally, the register annotations show that most of the documents belong to a relatively small set of registers, which are relatively similar in the two languages. A number of additional flags in the annotation are, however, necessary to reflect the wide range of linguistic variation associated with the documents.</abstract>
      <url hash="842e99fb">2020.wac-1.3</url>
      <language>eng</language>
    </paper>
    <paper id="4">
      <title>Building Web Corpora for Minority Languages</title>
      <author><first>Heidi</first><last>Jauhiainen</last></author>
      <author><first>Tommi</first><last>Jauhiainen</last></author>
      <author><first>Krister</first><last>Lindén</last></author>
      <pages>23–32</pages>
      <abstract>Web corpora creation for minority languages that do not have their own top-level Internet domain is no trivial matter. Web pages in such minority languages often contain text and links to pages in the dominant language of the country. When building corpora in specific languages, one has to decide how and at which stage to make sure the texts gathered are in the desired language. In the “Finno-Ugric Languages and the Internet” (Suki) project, we created web corpora for Uralic minority languages using web crawling combined with a language identification system in order to identify the language while crawling. In addition, we used language set identification and crowdsourcing before making sentence corpora out of the downloaded texts. In this article, we describe a strategy for collecting textual material from the Internet for minority languages. The strategy is based on the experiences we gained during the Suki project.</abstract>
      <url hash="1cb67619">2020.wac-1.4</url>
      <language>eng</language>
    </paper>
    <paper id="5">
      <title>The <fixed-case>ELTE</fixed-case>.<fixed-case>DH</fixed-case> Pilot Corpus – Creating a Handcrafted <fixed-case>G</fixed-case>igaword Web Corpus with Metadata</title>
      <author><first>Balázs</first><last>Indig</last></author>
      <author><first>Árpád</first><last>Knap</last></author>
      <author><first>Zsófia</first><last>Sárközi-Lindner</last></author>
      <author><first>Mária</first><last>Timári</last></author>
      <author><first>Gábor</first><last>Palkó</last></author>
      <pages>33–41</pages>
      <abstract>In this article, we present the method we used to create a middle-sized corpus using targeted web crawling. Our corpus contains news portal articles along with their metadata, that can be useful for diverse audiences, ranging from digital humanists to NLP users. The method presented in this paper applies rule-based components that allow the curation of the text and the metadata content. The curated data can thereon serve as a reference for various tasks and measurements. We designed our workflow to encourage modification and customisation. Our concept can also be applied to other genres of portals by using the discovered patterns in the architecture of the portals. We found that for a systematic creation or extension of a similar corpus, our method provides superior accuracy and ease of use compared to The Wayback Machine, while requiring minimal manpower and computational resources. Reproducing the corpus is possible if changes are introduced to the text-extraction process. The standard TEI format and Schema.org encoded metadata is used for the output format, but we stress that placing the corpus in a digital repository system is recommended in order to be able to define semantic relations between the segments and to add rich annotation.</abstract>
      <url hash="1ac0dd2e">2020.wac-1.5</url>
      <language>eng</language>
    </paper>
    <paper id="6">
      <title>Hypernym-<fixed-case>LIB</fixed-case>re: A Free Web-based Corpus for Hypernym Detection</title>
      <author><first>Shaurya</first><last>Rawat</last></author>
      <author><first>Mariano</first><last>Rico</last></author>
      <author><first>Oscar</first><last>Corcho</last></author>
      <pages>42–49</pages>
      <abstract>In this paper, we describe a new web-based corpus for hypernym detection. It consists of 32 GB of high quality english paragraphs along with their part-of-speech tagged and dependency parsed versions. For hypernym detection, the current state-of-the-art uses a corpus which is not available freely. We evaluate the state-of-the-art methods on our corpus and achieve similar results. The advantage of this corpora is that it is available under an open license. Our main contribution is the corpus with POS-tags and dependency tags and the code to extract and simulate the results we have achieved using our corpus.</abstract>
      <url hash="4456b730">2020.wac-1.6</url>
      <language>eng</language>
    </paper>
    <paper id="7">
      <title>A Cross-Genre Ensemble Approach to Robust <fixed-case>R</fixed-case>eddit Part of Speech Tagging</title>
      <author><first>Shabnam</first><last>Behzad</last></author>
      <author><first>Amir</first><last>Zeldes</last></author>
      <pages>50–56</pages>
      <abstract>Part of speech tagging is a fundamental NLP task often regarded as solved for high-resource languages such as English. Current state-of-the-art models have achieved high accuracy, especially on the news domain. However, when these models are applied to other corpora with different genres, and especially user-generated data from the Web, we see substantial drops in performance. In this work, we study how a state-of-the-art tagging model trained on different genres performs on Web content from unfiltered Reddit forum discussions. We report the results when training on different splits of the data, tested on Reddit. Our results show that even small amounts of in-domain data can outperform the contribution of data an order of magnitude larger coming from other Web domains. To make progress on out-of-domain tagging, we also evaluate an ensemble approach using multiple single-genre taggers as input features to a meta-classifier. We present state of the art performance on tagging Reddit data, as well as error analysis of the results of these models, and offer a typology of the most common error types among them, broken down by training corpus.</abstract>
      <url hash="a8579e54">2020.wac-1.7</url>
      <language>eng</language>
    </paper>
    <paper id="8">
      <title>Streaming Language-Specific <fixed-case>T</fixed-case>witter Data with Optimal Keywords</title>
      <author><first>Tim</first><last>Kreutz</last></author>
      <author><first>Walter</first><last>Daelemans</last></author>
      <pages>57–64</pages>
      <abstract>The Twitter Streaming API has been used to create language-specific corpora with varying degrees of success. Selecting a filter of frequent yet distinct keywords for German resulted in a near-complete collection of German tweets. This method is promising as it keeps within Twitter endpoint limitations and could be applied to other languages besides German. But so far no research has compared methods for selecting optimal keywords for this task. This paper proposes a method for finding optimal key phrases based on a greedy solution to the maximum coverage problem. We generate candidate key phrases for the 50 most frequent languages on Twitter. Candidates are then iteratively selected based on a variety of scoring functions applied to their coverage of target tweets. Selecting candidates based on the scoring function that exponentiates the precision of a key phrase and weighs it by recall achieved the best results overall. Some target languages yield lower results than what could be expected from their prevalence on Twitter. Upon analyzing the errors, we find that these are languages that are very close to more prevalent languages. In these cases, key phrases that limit finding the competitive language are selected, and overall recall on the target language also decreases. We publish the resulting optimized lists for each language as a resource. The code to generate lists for other research objectives is also supplied.</abstract>
      <url hash="261c1309">2020.wac-1.8</url>
      <language>eng</language>
    </paper>
  </volume>
</collection>
