<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<collection id="2020.nlp4if">
  <volume id="1" ingest-date="2020-11-29">
    <meta>
      <booktitle>Proceedings of the 3rd NLP4IF Workshop on NLP for Internet Freedom: Censorship, Disinformation, and Propaganda</booktitle>
      <editor><first>Giovanni</first><last>Da San Martino</last></editor>
      <editor><first>Chris</first><last>Brew</last></editor>
      <editor><first>Giovanni Luca</first><last>Ciampaglia</last></editor>
      <editor><first>Anna</first><last>Feldman</last></editor>
      <editor><first>Chris</first><last>Leberknight</last></editor>
      <editor><first>Preslav</first><last>Nakov</last></editor>
      <publisher>International Committee on Computational Linguistics (ICCL)</publisher>
      <address>Barcelona, Spain (Online)</address>
      <month>December</month>
      <year>2020</year>
    </meta>
    <frontmatter>
      <url hash="6daf5611">2020.nlp4if-1.0</url>
    </frontmatter>
    <paper id="1">
      <title>Two Stage Transformer Model for <fixed-case>COVID</fixed-case>-19 Fake News Detection and Fact Checking</title>
      <author><first>Rutvik</first><last>Vijjali</last></author>
      <author><first>Prathyush</first><last>Potluri</last></author>
      <author><first>Siddharth</first><last>Kumar</last></author>
      <author><first>Sundeep</first><last>Teki</last></author>
      <pages>1–10</pages>
      <abstract>The rapid advancement of technology in online communication via social media platforms has led to a prolific rise in the spread of misinformation and fake news. Fake news is especially rampant in the current COVID-19 pandemic, leading to people believing in false and potentially harmful claims and stories. Detecting fake news quickly can alleviate the spread of panic, chaos and potential health hazards. We developed a two stage automated pipeline for COVID-19 fake news detection using state of the art machine learning models for natural language processing. The first model leverages a novel fact checking algorithm that retrieves the most relevant facts concerning user queries about particular COVID-19 claims. The second model verifies the level of “truth” in the queried claim by computing the textual entailment between the claim and the true facts retrieved from a manually curated COVID-19 dataset. The dataset is based on a publicly available knowledge source consisting of more than 5000 COVID-19 false claims and verified explanations, a subset of which was internally annotated and cross-validated to train and evaluate our models. We evaluate a series of models based on classical text-based features to more contextual Transformer based models and observe that a model pipeline based on BERT and ALBERT for the two stages respectively yields the best results.</abstract>
      <url hash="6a49755e">2020.nlp4if-1.1</url>
    </paper>
    <paper id="2">
      <title>Measuring Alignment to Authoritarian State Media as Framing Bias</title>
      <author><first>Timothy</first><last>Niven</last></author>
      <author><first>Hung-Yu</first><last>Kao</last></author>
      <pages>11–21</pages>
      <abstract>We introduce what is to the best of our knowledge a new task in natural language processing: measuring alignment to authoritarian state media. We operationalize alignment in terms of sociological definitions of media bias. We take as a case study the alignment of four Taiwanese media outlets to the Chinese Communist Party state media. We present the results of an initial investigation using the frequency of words in psychologically meaningful categories. Our findings suggest that the chosen word categories correlate with framing choices. We develop a calculation method that yields reasonable results for measuring alignment, agreeing well with the known labels. We confirm that our method does capture event selection bias, but whether it captures framing bias requires further investigation.</abstract>
      <url hash="08146601">2020.nlp4if-1.2</url>
    </paper>
    <paper id="3">
      <title>Incorporating Count-Based Features into Pre-Trained Models for Improved Stance Detection</title>
      <author><first>Anushka</first><last>Prakash</last></author>
      <author><first>Harish</first><last>Tayyar Madabushi</last></author>
      <pages>22–32</pages>
      <abstract>The explosive growth and popularity of Social Media has revolutionised the way we communicate and collaborate. Unfortunately, this same ease of accessing and sharing information has led to an explosion of misinformation and propaganda. Given that stance detection can significantly aid in veracity prediction, this work focuses on boosting automated stance detection, a task on which pre-trained models have been extremely successful on, as on several other tasks. This work shows that the task of stance detection can benefit from feature based information, especially on certain under performing classes, however, integrating such features into pre-trained models using ensembling is challenging. We propose a novel architecture for integrating features with pre-trained models that address these challenges and test our method on the RumourEval 2019 dataset. This method achieves state-of-the-art results with an F1-score of 63.94 on the test set.</abstract>
      <url hash="0a96de5a">2020.nlp4if-1.3</url>
    </paper>
    <paper id="4">
      <title>A Multi-Modal Method for Satire Detection using Textual and Visual Cues</title>
      <author><first>Lily</first><last>Li</last></author>
      <author><first>Or</first><last>Levi</last></author>
      <author><first>Pedram</first><last>Hosseini</last></author>
      <author><first>David</first><last>Broniatowski</last></author>
      <pages>33–38</pages>
      <abstract>Satire is a form of humorous critique, but it is sometimes misinterpreted by readers as legitimate news, which can lead to harmful consequences. We observe that the images used in satirical news articles often contain absurd or ridiculous content and that image manipulation is used to create fictional scenarios. While previous work have studied text-based methods, in this work we propose a multi-modal approach based on state-of-the-art visiolinguistic model ViLBERT. To this end, we create a new dataset consisting of images and headlines of regular and satirical news for the task of satire detection. We fine-tune ViLBERT on the dataset and train a convolutional neural network that uses an image forensics technique. Evaluation on the dataset shows that our proposed multi-modal approach outperforms image-only, text-only, and simple fusion baselines.</abstract>
      <url hash="ee82001c">2020.nlp4if-1.4</url>
    </paper>
    <paper id="5">
      <title>A Risk Communication Event Detection Model via Contrastive Learning</title>
      <author><first>Mingi</first><last>Shin</last></author>
      <author><first>Sungwon</first><last>Han</last></author>
      <author><first>Sungkyu</first><last>Park</last></author>
      <author><first>Meeyoung</first><last>Cha</last></author>
      <pages>39–43</pages>
      <abstract>This paper presents a time-topic cohesive model describing the communication patterns on the coronavirus pandemic from three Asian countries. The strength of our model is two-fold. First, it detects contextualized events based on topical and temporal information via contrastive learning. Second, it can be applied to multiple languages, enabling a comparison of risk communication across cultures. We present a case study and discuss future implications of the proposed model.</abstract>
      <url hash="13733921">2020.nlp4if-1.5</url>
    </paper>
  </volume>
</collection>
