<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<collection id="2021.dnd">
  <volume id="12" type="journal" ingest-date="2026-04-20">
    <meta>
      <booktitle>Dialogue &amp; Discourse Volume 12</booktitle>
      <editor><first>Patrick</first><last>Healey</last></editor>
      <editor><first>Barbara Di</first><last>Eugenio</last></editor>
      <editor><first>Vera</first><last>Demberg</last></editor>
      <editor><first>Jonathan</first><last>Ginzburg</last></editor>
      <editor><first>Kallirroi</first><last>Georgila</last></editor>
      <editor><first>Amir</first><last>Zeldes</last></editor>
      <editor><first>Massimo</first><last>Poesio</last></editor>
      <publisher>University of Illinois Chicago</publisher>
      <address>Chicago, Illinois, USA</address>
      <year>2021</year>
      <venue>dnd</venue>
      <journal-volume>12</journal-volume>
    </meta>
    <paper id="1">
      <title>Event and Entity Coreference Across Five Languages: Effects of Context and Referring Expression</title>
      <author><first>Luca</first><last>Bevacqua</last></author>
      <author><first>Sharid</first><last>Loáiciga</last></author>
      <author><first>Hannah</first><last>Rohde</last></author>
      <author><first>Christian</first><last>Hardmeier</last></author>
      <pages>192-226</pages>
      <abstract>Current work on coreference focuses primarily on entities, often leaving unanalysed the use of anaphors to corefer with antecedents such as events and textual segments. Moreover, the anaphoric forms that speakers use for entity and non-entity coreference are not mutually exclusive. This ambiguity has been the subject of recent work in English, with evidence of a split between comprehenders’ preferential interpretation of personal versus demonstrative pronouns. In addition, comprehenders are shown to be sensitive to antecedent complexity and aspectual status, two verb-driven cues that signal how an event is being portrayed. Here we extend this work via a comparison across five languages (English, French, German, Italian, and Spanish). With a story-continuation experiment, we test how different referring expressions corefer with entity and event antecedents and whether verbal features such as argument structure and aspect influence this choice. Our results show widely consistent, not categorical biases across languages: entity coreference is favoured for personal pronouns and event coreference for demonstratives. Antecedent complexity increases the rate at which anaphors are taken to corefer with an event antecedent, but portraying an event as completed does not reach statistical significance (though showing quite uniform patterns). Lastly, we report a comparison of the same referring expressions to refer to entity and event antecedents in a trilingual parallel corpus annotated with coreference.Together, the results provide a first crosslingual picture of coreference preferences beyond the restricted entity-only patterns targeted by most existing work on coreference. The five languages are all shown to allow gradable use of pronouns for entity and event coreference, with biases that align with existing generalizations about the link between prominence and the use of reduced referring expressions. The studies also show the feasibility of manipulating targeted verb-driven cues across multiple languages to support crosslingual comparisons.</abstract>
      <url hash="0d4c03ec">2021.dnd-12.1</url>
      <doi>10.5210/dad.2021.207</doi>
      <bibkey>bevacqua-etal-2021-event</bibkey>
      <month>December</month>
    </paper>
    <paper id="2">
      <title>An Analysis of <fixed-case>J</fixed-case>apanese Sentence-final Particle Yone: Compare Yone and Ne in Response</title>
      <author><first>Jun</first><last>Xu</last></author>
      <pages>174-191</pages>
      <abstract>Yone, a Japanese sentence-final particle (SFP), is frequently used in conversation, and some functions overlap with ne, another SFP. However, not much discussion has taken place about their differences. This study argues that the two Japanese sentence-final particles, yone and ne, express a distinction about the speaker’s state of mind: yone indicates that an idea has been on the speaker’s mind, while ne suggests a thought just emerged into the speaker’s awareness. Naturally occurring conversation data provides evidence for this claim. The results show that the particles reflect the speaker’s choice of presenting his/her state of awareness.</abstract>
      <url hash="d4ab0355">2021.dnd-12.2</url>
      <doi>10.5210/dad.2021.206</doi>
      <bibkey>xu-2021-analysis</bibkey>
      <month>December</month>
    </paper>
    <paper id="3">
      <title>Lexical Alignment to Non-native Speakers</title>
      <author><first>Iva</first><last>Ivanova</last></author>
      <author><first>Holly</first><last>Branigan</last></author>
      <author><first>Janet</first><last>McLean</last></author>
      <author><first>Albert</first><last>Costa</last></author>
      <author><first>Martin</first><last>Pickering</last></author>
      <pages>145-173</pages>
      <abstract>Two picture-matching-game experiments investigated if lexical-referential alignment to non-native speakers is enhanced by a desire to aid communicative success (by saying something the conversation partner can certainly understand), a form of audience design. In Experiment 1, a group of native speakers of British English that was not given evidence of their conversation partners’ picture-matching performance showed more alignment to non-native than to native speakers, while another group that was given such evidence aligned equivalently to the two types of speaker. Experiment 2, conducted with speakers of Castilian Spanish, replicated the greater alignment to non-native than native speakers without feedback. However, Experiment 2 also showed that production of grammatical errors by the confederate produced no additional increase of alignment even though making errors suggests lower communicative competence. We suggest that this pattern is consistent with another collaborative strategy, the desire to model correct usage. Together, these results support a role for audience design in alignment to non-native speakers in structured task-based dialogue, but one that is strategically deployed only when deemed necessary.</abstract>
      <url hash="a418edc4">2021.dnd-12.3</url>
      <doi>10.5210/dad.2021.205</doi>
      <bibkey>ivanova-etal-2021-lexical</bibkey>
      <month>October</month>
    </paper>
    <paper id="4">
      <title>Narrative Elements in Expository Texts</title>
      <author><first>Nina L.</first><last>Sangers</last></author>
      <author><first>Jacqueline</first><last>Evers-Vermeul</last></author>
      <author><first>Ted J.M.</first><last>Sanders</last></author>
      <author><first>Hans</first><last>Hoeken</last></author>
      <pages>115-144</pages>
      <abstract>While the use of narrative elements in educational texts seems to be an adequate means to enhance students’ engagement and comprehension, we know little about how and to what extent these elements are used in the present-day educational practice. In this quantitative corpus-based analysis, we chart how and when narrative elements are used in current Dutch educational texts (N=999). While educational texts have traditionally been considered prime exemplars of expository texts, we show that the distinction between the expository and narrative genre is not that strict in the educational domain: prototypical narrative elements – particularized events, experiencing characters, and landscapes of consciousness – occur in 45% of the corpus’ texts. Their distribution varies between school subjects: while specific events, specific people, and their experiences are often at the heart of the to-be-learned information in history texts, narrativity is less present in the educational content of biology and geography texts. Instead publishers employ narrative-like strategies to make these texts more concrete and imaginable, such as the addition of fictitious characters and representative entities.</abstract>
      <url hash="37cea676">2021.dnd-12.4</url>
      <doi>10.5210/dad.2021.204</doi>
      <bibkey>sangers-etal-2021-narrative</bibkey>
      <month>October</month>
    </paper>
    <paper id="5">
      <title>User Satisfaction Reward Estimation Across Domains: Domain-independent Dialogue Policy Learning</title>
      <author><first>Stefan</first><last>Ultes</last></author>
      <author><first>Wolfgang</first><last>Maier</last></author>
      <pages>81-114</pages>
      <abstract>Learning suitable and well-performing dialogue behaviour in statistical spoken dialogue systems has been in the focus of research for many years. While most work that is based on reinforcement learning employs an objective measure like task success for modelling the reward signal, we propose to use a reward signal based on user satisfaction. We propose a novel estimator and show that it outperforms all previous estimators while learning temporal dependencies implicitly. We show in simulated experiments that a live user satisfaction estimation model may be applied resulting in higher estimated satisfaction whilst achieving similar success rates. Moreover, we show that a satisfaction estimation model trained on one domain may be applied in many other domains that cover a similar task. We verify our findings by employing the model to one of the domains for learning a policy from real users and compare its performance to policies using user satisfaction and task success acquired directly from the users as reward.</abstract>
      <url hash="d05d05f1">2021.dnd-12.5</url>
      <doi>10.5210/dad.2021.203</doi>
      <bibkey>ultes-maier-2021-user</bibkey>
      <month>September</month>
    </paper>
    <paper id="6">
      <title>Processing of discourse anaphors by <fixed-case>L</fixed-case>2 speakers of <fixed-case>E</fixed-case>nglish</title>
      <author><first>Derya</first><last>Cokal</last></author>
      <author><first>Patrick</first><last>Sturt</last></author>
      <author><first>Fernanda</first><last>Ferreira</last></author>
      <pages>38-80</pages>
      <abstract>This study examines the cognitive information processes that Turkish advanced non-native speakers of English employ in assigning the referents of this and that in reading and production. We predicted that these speakers would assign referents in relation to the linear distance between discourse-linked anaphors and their referents in the discourse (i.e., based on spatial-temporal features of this and that), which means they would prefer this for a referent mentioned in the proximal chunk of text and that for a referent mentioned in the distal chunk. We also predicted that readers would not assign referents based on the focusing features of this and that. We tested our predictions in two eye- tracking reading experiments and one sentence-completion experiment. Turkish L2 learners’ on- line reference resolution in reading experiments was different from that of English native speakers that were tested in a previous study. In the eye-tracking experiments, Turkish L2 learners did not show evidence of using a recency strategy to resolve referential ambiguity and did not use spatial- temporal or focusing features of this and that to assign referents. On the other hand, in the sentence- completion experiment, the effect of prominence of discourse structure in the use of this and that was qualitatively similar to that of English native speakers, but their indexing of the degree of focus of this and that was different. Our results suggest that the difference between Turkish L2 learners and English native speakers is due to L1 interference.</abstract>
      <url hash="a74802ff">2021.dnd-12.6</url>
      <doi>10.5210/dad.2021.202</doi>
      <bibkey>cokal-etal-2021-processing</bibkey>
      <month>August</month>
    </paper>
    <paper id="7">
      <title>Discourse Relations and Connectives in Higher Text Structure</title>
      <author><first>Lucie</first><last>Polakova</last></author>
      <author><first>Jiří</first><last>Mírovský</last></author>
      <author><first>Šárka</first><last>Zikánová</last></author>
      <author><first>Eva</first><last>Hajičová</last></author>
      <pages>1-37</pages>
      <abstract>The present article investigates possibilities and limits of local (shallow) analysis of discourse coherence with respect to the phenomena of global coherence and higher composition of texts. We study corpora annotated with local discourse relations in Czech and partly in English to try and find clues in the local annotation indicating a higher discourse structure. First, we classify patterns of subsequent or overlapping pairs of local relations, and hierarchies formed by nested local relations. Special attention is then given to relations crossing paragraph boundaries and their semantic types, and to paragraph-initial discourse connectives. In the third part, we examine situations in which annotators incline to marking a large argument (larger than one sentence) of a discourse relation even with a minimality principle annotation rule in place. Our analyses bring (i) new linguistic insights regarding coherence signals in local and higher contexts, e.g. detection and description of hierarchies of local discourse relations up to 5 levels in Czech and English, description of distribution differences in semantic types in cross-paragraph and other settings, identification of Czech connectives only typical for higher structures, or the detection of prevalence of large left-sided arguments in locally annotated data; (ii) as another type of contribution, some new reflections on methodologies of the approaches under scrutiny.</abstract>
      <url hash="02787db3">2021.dnd-12.7</url>
      <doi>10.5210/dad.2021.201</doi>
      <bibkey>polakova-etal-2021-discourse</bibkey>
      <month>July</month>
    </paper>
    <paper id="8">
      <title>Referential Communication Between <fixed-case>F</fixed-case>riends and Strangers in the Wild</title>
      <author><first>Kris</first><last>Liu</last></author>
      <author><first>J. Trevor</first><last>D'Arcey</last></author>
      <author><first>Marilyn</first><last>Walker</last></author>
      <author><first>Jean Fox</first><last>Tree</last></author>
      <pages>45-72</pages>
      <abstract>The Map Task (Anderson et al., 1991) and Tangram Task (Clark &amp; Wilkes-Gibbs, 1986) are traditional referential communication tasks that are used in psycholinguistics research to demonstrate how conversational partners mutually agree on descriptions (or referring expressions) for landmarks or unusual target objects. These highly-controlled, laboratory-based tasks take place under conditions that are relatively unusual for naturally-occurring conversations (Speed, Wnuk, &amp; Majid, 2016). In this study, we used the Artwalk Task (Liu, Fox Tree, &amp; Walker, 2016) – a real world-situated blend of the Map Task and Tangram Task – to demonstrate that the process of negotiating referring expressions ‘in the wild’ is similar to the process that takes place in a laboratory. In Artwalk, participant pairs communicated via a Skype-to-mobile phone connection. One participant guided the other through a small downtown area with the goal of identifying public art objects, finding objects twice during two rounds. In addition to replicating laboratory results, we also found that acquaintanceship and extraversion influenced the number of unique descriptors used by dyads in this task. In Round 1, introverts in stranger dyads used fewer descriptors but introverts in friend dyads were indistinguishable from extraverts. The influence of extraversion declined by Round 2. This study suggests that referent negotiation observed in labs is generalizable but that naturalistic communication is subject to social and personality factors that may not be as influential in laboratory conditions.</abstract>
      <url hash="8f6835b0">2021.dnd-12.8</url>
      <doi>10.5210/dad.2021.103</doi>
      <bibkey>liu-etal-2021-referential</bibkey>
      <month>April</month>
    </paper>
    <paper id="9">
      <title>Cognitive and social delays in the initiation of conversational repair</title>
      <author><first>Julia Beret</first><last>Mertens</last></author>
      <author><first>Jan Peter De</first><last>Ruiter</last></author>
      <pages>21-44</pages>
      <abstract>The exact timing of a conversational turn conveys important information to a listener. Most turns are initiated within 250ms after the previous turn. However, interlocutors take longer to initiate certain types of turns: those that either require more cognitive processing or are socially dispreferred. Many dispreferred turns are also cognitively demanding, so it is difficult to attribute specific conversational delays to social or cognitive mechanisms. In this paper, we evaluate the relative contribution of cognitive and social variables to the timing of utterances in conversation. We focus on a type of turn that is socially dispreferred, cognitively demanding, and generally delayed: other-initiations of repair (OIRs). OIRs occur when a listener notices and decides to signal a comprehension problem (e.g., "What?"). We analyzed the Floor Transfer Offsets of 456 OIRs, and found that interlocutors initiated OIRs later when trouble sources had weaker discourse context or were shorter, and when the OIR was more face-threatening. Our results suggest that both cognitive and social variables contribute to the timing of delayed utterances in conversation. We discuss how attention, prediction, planning, and social preference manifest in the timing of turns.</abstract>
      <url hash="36c9b3bb">2021.dnd-12.9</url>
      <doi>10.5210/dad.2021.102</doi>
      <bibkey>mertens-ruiter-2021-cognitive</bibkey>
      <month>March</month>
    </paper>
    <paper id="10">
      <title>How People Structure Representations of Discourse</title>
      <author><first>Alan</first><last>Garnham</last></author>
      <pages>1-20</pages>
      <abstract>Mental models or situation models include representations of people, but much of the literature about such models focuses on the representation of eventualities (events, states, and processes) or (small-scale) situations. In the well-known event-indexing model of Zwaan, Langston, and Graesser (1995), for example, protagonists are just one of five dimensions on which situation models are indexed. They are not given any additional special status. Consideration of longer narratives, and the ways in which readers or listeners relate to them, suggest that people have a more central status in the way we think about texts, and hence in discourse representations, Indeed, such considerations suggest that discourse representations are organised around (the representations of) central characters. The paper develops the idea of the centrality of main characters in representations of longer texts, by considering, among other things, the way information is presented in novels, with L’Éducation Sentimentale by Gustav Flaubert as a case study. Conclusions are also drawn about the role of representations of people in the representation of other types of text.</abstract>
      <url hash="3de4fa7f">2021.dnd-12.10</url>
      <doi>10.5210/dad.2021.101</doi>
      <bibkey>garnham-2021-people</bibkey>
      <month>February</month>
    </paper>
  </volume>
</collection>
