<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<collection id="2021.semeval">
  <volume id="1" ingest-date="2021-07-25" type="proceedings">
    <meta>
      <booktitle>Proceedings of the 15th International Workshop on Semantic Evaluation (SemEval-2021)</booktitle>
      <editor><first>Alexis</first><last>Palmer</last></editor>
      <editor><first>Nathan</first><last>Schneider</last></editor>
      <editor><first>Natalie</first><last>Schluter</last></editor>
      <editor><first>Guy</first><last>Emerson</last></editor>
      <editor><first>Aurelie</first><last>Herbelot</last></editor>
      <editor><first>Xiaodan</first><last>Zhu</last></editor>
      <publisher>Association for Computational Linguistics</publisher>
      <address>Online</address>
      <month>August</month>
      <year>2021</year>
      <url hash="01d5d604">2021.semeval-1</url>
      <venue>semeval</venue>
    </meta>
    <frontmatter>
      <url hash="404ba67b">2021.semeval-1.0</url>
      <bibkey>semeval-2021-international</bibkey>
    </frontmatter>
    <paper id="1">
      <title><fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 1: Lexical Complexity Prediction</title>
      <author><first>Matthew</first><last>Shardlow</last></author>
      <author><first>Richard</first><last>Evans</last></author>
      <author><first>Gustavo Henrique</first><last>Paetzold</last></author>
      <author><first>Marcos</first><last>Zampieri</last></author>
      <pages>1–16</pages>
      <abstract>This paper presents the results and main findings of SemEval-2021 Task 1 - Lexical Complexity Prediction. We provided participants with an augmented version of the CompLex Corpus (Shardlow et al. 2020). CompLex is an English multi-domain corpus in which words and multi-word expressions (MWEs) were annotated with respect to their complexity using a five point Likert scale. SemEval-2021 Task 1 featured two Sub-tasks: Sub-task 1 focused on single words and Sub-task 2 focused on MWEs. The competition attracted 198 teams in total, of which 54 teams submitted official runs on the test data to Sub-task 1 and 37 to Sub-task 2.</abstract>
      <url hash="026e0c42">2021.semeval-1.1</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.1</doi>
      <bibkey>shardlow-etal-2021-semeval</bibkey>
      <video href="2021.semeval-1.1.mp4"/>
    </paper>
    <paper id="2">
      <title><fixed-case>OCHADAI</fixed-case>-<fixed-case>KYOTO</fixed-case> at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 1: Enhancing Model Generalization and Robustness for Lexical Complexity Prediction</title>
      <author><first>Yuki</first><last>Taya</last></author>
      <author><first>Lis</first><last>Kanashiro Pereira</last></author>
      <author><first>Fei</first><last>Cheng</last></author>
      <author><first>Ichiro</first><last>Kobayashi</last></author>
      <pages>17–23</pages>
      <abstract>We propose an ensemble model for predicting the lexical complexity of words and multiword expressions (MWEs). The model receives as input a sentence with a target word or MWE and outputs its complexity score. Given that a key challenge with this task is the limited size of annotated data, our model relies on pretrained contextual representations from different state-of-the-art transformer-based language models (i.e., BERT and RoBERTa), and on a variety of training methods for further enhancing model generalization and robustness: multi-step fine-tuning and multi-task learning, and adversarial training. Additionally, we propose to enrich contextual representations by adding hand-crafted features during training. Our model achieved competitive results and ranked among the top-10 systems in both sub-tasks.</abstract>
      <url hash="772da07b">2021.semeval-1.2</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.2</doi>
      <bibkey>taya-etal-2021-ochadai</bibkey>
      <video href="2021.semeval-1.2.mp4"/>
    </paper>
    <paper id="3">
      <title><fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 2: Multilingual and Cross-lingual Word-in-Context Disambiguation (<fixed-case>MCL</fixed-case>-<fixed-case>W</fixed-case>i<fixed-case>C</fixed-case>)</title>
      <author><first>Federico</first><last>Martelli</last></author>
      <author><first>Najla</first><last>Kalach</last></author>
      <author><first>Gabriele</first><last>Tola</last></author>
      <author><first>Roberto</first><last>Navigli</last></author>
      <pages>24–36</pages>
      <abstract>In this paper, we introduce the first SemEval task on Multilingual and Cross-Lingual Word-in-Context disambiguation (MCL-WiC). This task allows the largely under-investigated inherent ability of systems to discriminate between word senses within and across languages to be evaluated, dropping the requirement of a fixed sense inventory. Framed as a binary classification, our task is divided into two parts. In the multilingual sub-task, participating systems are required to determine whether two target words, each occurring in a different context within the same language, express the same meaning or not. Instead, in the cross-lingual part, systems are asked to perform the task in a cross-lingual scenario, in which the two target words and their corresponding contexts are provided in two different languages. We illustrate our task, as well as the construction of our manually-created dataset including five languages, namely Arabic, Chinese, English, French and Russian, and the results of the participating systems. Datasets and results are available at: <url>https://github.com/SapienzaNLP/mcl-wic</url>.</abstract>
      <url hash="b096ff36">2021.semeval-1.3</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.3</doi>
      <bibkey>martelli-etal-2021-semeval</bibkey>
      <video href="2021.semeval-1.3.mp4"/>
      <pwccode url="https://github.com/SapienzaNLP/mcl-wic" additional="false">SapienzaNLP/mcl-wic</pwccode>
      <pwcdataset url="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/wic">WiC</pwcdataset>
    </paper>
    <paper id="4">
      <title><fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 4: Reading Comprehension of Abstract Meaning</title>
      <author><first>Boyuan</first><last>Zheng</last></author>
      <author><first>Xiaoyu</first><last>Yang</last></author>
      <author><first>Yu-Ping</first><last>Ruan</last></author>
      <author><first>Zhenhua</first><last>Ling</last></author>
      <author><first>Quan</first><last>Liu</last></author>
      <author><first>Si</first><last>Wei</last></author>
      <author><first>Xiaodan</first><last>Zhu</last></author>
      <pages>37–50</pages>
      <abstract>This paper introduces the SemEval-2021 shared task 4: Reading Comprehension of Abstract Meaning (ReCAM). This shared task is designed to help evaluate the ability of machines in representing and understanding abstract concepts. Given a passage and the corresponding question, a participating system is expected to choose the correct answer from five candidates of abstract concepts in cloze-style machine reading comprehension tasks. Based on two typical definitions of abstractness, i.e., the imperceptibility and nonspecificity, our task provides three subtasks to evaluate models’ ability in comprehending the two types of abstract meaning and the models’ generalizability. Specifically, Subtask 1 aims to evaluate how well a participating system models concepts that cannot be directly perceived in the physical world. Subtask 2 focuses on models’ ability in comprehending nonspecific concepts located high in a hypernym hierarchy given the context of a passage. Subtask 3 aims to provide some insights into models’ generalizability over the two types of abstractness. During the SemEval-2021 official evaluation period, we received 23 submissions to Subtask 1 and 28 to Subtask 2. The participating teams additionally made 29 submissions to Subtask 3. The leaderboard and competition website can be found at <url>https://competitions.codalab.org/competitions/26153</url>. The data and baseline code are available at <url>https://github.com/boyuanzheng010/SemEval2021-Reading-Comprehension-of-Abstract-Meaning</url>.</abstract>
      <url hash="946edccf">2021.semeval-1.4</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.4</doi>
      <bibkey>zheng-etal-2021-semeval</bibkey>
      <pwccode url="https://github.com/boyuanzheng010/SemEval2021-Reading-Comprehension-of-Abstract-Meaning" additional="false">boyuanzheng010/SemEval2021-Reading-Comprehension-of-Abstract-Meaning</pwccode>
      <pwcdataset url="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/recam">ReCAM</pwcdataset>
    </paper>
    <paper id="5">
      <title><fixed-case>TA</fixed-case>-<fixed-case>MAMC</fixed-case> at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 4: Task-adaptive Pretraining and Multi-head Attention for Abstract Meaning Reading Comprehension</title>
      <author><first>Jing</first><last>Zhang</last></author>
      <author><first>Yimeng</first><last>Zhuang</last></author>
      <author><first>Yinpei</first><last>Su</last></author>
      <pages>51–58</pages>
      <abstract>This paper describes our system used in the SemEval-2021 Task4 Reading Comprehension of Abstract Meaning, achieving 1st for subtask 1 and 2nd for subtask 2 on the leaderboard. We propose an ensemble of ELECTRA-based models with task-adaptive pretraining and a multi-head attention multiple-choice classifier on top of the pre-trained model. The main contributions of our system are 1) revealing the performance discrepancy of different transformer-based pretraining models on the downstream task, 2) presentation of an efficient method to generate large task-adaptive corpora for pretraining. We also investigated several pretraining strategies and contrastive learning objectives. Our system achieves a test accuracy of 95.11 and 94.89 on subtask 1 and subtask 2 respectively.</abstract>
      <url hash="d4d93efb">2021.semeval-1.5</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.5</doi>
      <bibkey>zhang-etal-2021-ta</bibkey>
      <pwcdataset url="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/glue">GLUE</pwcdataset>
      <pwcdataset url="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/multinli">MultiNLI</pwcdataset>
      <pwcdataset url="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/newsroom">NEWSROOM</pwcdataset>
      <pwcdataset url="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/recam">ReCAM</pwcdataset>
    </paper>
    <paper id="6">
      <title><fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 5: Toxic Spans Detection</title>
      <author><first>John</first><last>Pavlopoulos</last></author>
      <author><first>Jeffrey</first><last>Sorensen</last></author>
      <author><first>Léo</first><last>Laugier</last></author>
      <author><first>Ion</first><last>Androutsopoulos</last></author>
      <pages>59–69</pages>
      <abstract>The Toxic Spans Detection task of SemEval-2021 required participants to predict the spans of toxic posts that were responsible for the toxic label of the posts. The task could be addressed as supervised sequence labeling, using training data with gold toxic spans provided by the organisers. It could also be treated as rationale extraction, using classifiers trained on potentially larger external datasets of posts manually annotated as toxic or not, without toxic span annotations. For the supervised sequence labeling approach and evaluation purposes, posts previously labeled as toxic were crowd-annotated for toxic spans. Participants submitted their predicted spans for a held-out test set and were scored using character-based F1. This overview summarises the work of the 36 teams that provided system descriptions.</abstract>
      <url hash="ff71cc2e">2021.semeval-1.6</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.6</doi>
      <bibkey>pavlopoulos-etal-2021-semeval</bibkey>
      <video href="2021.semeval-1.6.mp4"/>
      <pwcdataset url="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/civil-comments">Civil Comments</pwcdataset>
    </paper>
    <paper id="7">
      <title><fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 6: Detection of Persuasion Techniques in Texts and Images</title>
      <author><first>Dimitar</first><last>Dimitrov</last></author>
      <author><first>Bishr</first><last>Bin Ali</last></author>
      <author><first>Shaden</first><last>Shaar</last></author>
      <author><first>Firoj</first><last>Alam</last></author>
      <author><first>Fabrizio</first><last>Silvestri</last></author>
      <author><first>Hamed</first><last>Firooz</last></author>
      <author><first>Preslav</first><last>Nakov</last></author>
      <author><first>Giovanni</first><last>Da San Martino</last></author>
      <pages>70–98</pages>
      <abstract>We describe SemEval-2021 task 6 on Detection of Persuasion Techniques in Texts and Images: the data, the annotation guidelines, the evaluation setup, the results, and the participating systems. The task focused on memes and had three subtasks: (i) detecting the techniques in the text, (ii) detecting the text spans where the techniques are used, and (iii) detecting techniques in the entire meme, i.e., both in the text and in the image. It was a popular task, attracting 71 registrations, and 22 teams that eventually made an official submission on the test set. The evaluation results for the third subtask confirmed the importance of both modalities, the text and the image. Moreover, some teams reported benefits when not just combining the two modalities, e.g., by using early or late fusion, but rather modeling the interaction between them in a joint model.</abstract>
      <url hash="7fb48942">2021.semeval-1.7</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.7</doi>
      <bibkey>dimitrov-etal-2021-semeval</bibkey>
      <video href="2021.semeval-1.7.mp4"/>
      <pwcdataset url="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/hateful-memes">Hateful Memes</pwcdataset>
    </paper>
    <paper id="8">
      <title>Alpha at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 6: Transformer Based Propaganda Classification</title>
      <author><first>Zhida</first><last>Feng</last></author>
      <author><first>Jiji</first><last>Tang</last></author>
      <author><first>Jiaxiang</first><last>Liu</last></author>
      <author><first>Weichong</first><last>Yin</last></author>
      <author><first>Shikun</first><last>Feng</last></author>
      <author><first>Yu</first><last>Sun</last></author>
      <author><first>Li</first><last>Chen</last></author>
      <pages>99–104</pages>
      <abstract>This paper describes our system participated in Task 6 of SemEval-2021: the task focuses on multimodal propaganda technique classification and it aims to classify given image and text into 22 classes. In this paper, we propose to use transformer based architecture to fuse the clues from both image and text. We explore two branches of techniques including fine-tuning the text pretrained transformer with extended visual features, and fine-tuning the multimodal pretrained transformers. For the visual features, we have tested both grid features based on ResNet and salient region features from pretrained object detector. Among the pretrained multimodal transformers, we choose ERNIE-ViL, a two-steam cross-attended transformers pretrained on large scale image-caption aligned data. Fine-tuing ERNIE-ViL for our task produce a better performance due to general joint multimodal representation for text and image learned by ERNIE-ViL. Besides, as the distribution of the classification labels is very unbalanced, we also make a further attempt on the loss function and the experiment result shows that focal loss would perform better than cross entropy loss. Last we have won first for subtask C in the final competition.</abstract>
      <url hash="a6f72adf">2021.semeval-1.8</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.8</doi>
      <bibkey>feng-etal-2021-alpha</bibkey>
      <video href="2021.semeval-1.8.mp4"/>
    </paper>
    <paper id="9">
      <title><fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val 2021 Task 7: <fixed-case>H</fixed-case>a<fixed-case>H</fixed-case>ackathon, Detecting and Rating Humor and Offense</title>
      <author><first>J. A.</first><last>Meaney</last></author>
      <author><first>Steven</first><last>Wilson</last></author>
      <author><first>Luis</first><last>Chiruzzo</last></author>
      <author><first>Adam</first><last>Lopez</last></author>
      <author><first>Walid</first><last>Magdy</last></author>
      <pages>105–119</pages>
      <abstract>SemEval 2021 Task 7, HaHackathon, was the first shared task to combine the previously separate domains of humor detection and offense detection. We collected 10,000 texts from Twitter and the Kaggle Short Jokes dataset, and had each annotated for humor and offense by 20 annotators aged 18-70. Our subtasks were binary humor detection, prediction of humor and offense ratings, and a novel controversy task: to predict if the variance in the humor ratings was higher than a specific threshold. The subtasks attracted 36-58 submissions, with most of the participants choosing to use pre-trained language models. Many of the highest performing teams also implemented additional optimization techniques, including task-adaptive training and adversarial training. The results suggest that the participating systems are well suited to humor detection, but that humor controversy is a more challenging task. We discuss which models excel in this task, which auxiliary techniques boost their performance, and analyze the errors which were not captured by the best systems.</abstract>
      <url hash="4c2e27ab">2021.semeval-1.9</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.9</doi>
      <bibkey>meaney-etal-2021-semeval</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="10">
      <title><fixed-case>L</fixed-case>ang<fixed-case>R</fixed-case>esearch<fixed-case>L</fixed-case>ab <fixed-case>NC</fixed-case> at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 1: Linguistic Feature Based Modelling for Lexical Complexity</title>
      <author><first>Raksha</first><last>Agarwal</last></author>
      <author><first>Niladri</first><last>Chatterjee</last></author>
      <pages>120–125</pages>
      <abstract>The present work aims at assigning a complexity score between 0 and 1 to a target word or phrase in a given sentence. For each Single Word Target, a Random Forest Regressor is trained on a feature set consisting of lexical, semantic, and syntactic information about the target. For each Multiword Target, a set of individual word features is taken along with single word complexities in the feature space. The system yielded the Pearson correlation of 0.7402 and 0.8244 on the test set for the Single and Multiword Targets, respectively.</abstract>
      <url hash="2fbd0b16">2021.semeval-1.10</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.10</doi>
      <bibkey>agarwal-chatterjee-2021-langresearchlab-nc</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="11">
      <title>Complex words identification using word-level features for <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2020 Task 1</title>
      <author><first>Jenny A.</first><last>Ortiz-Zambrano</last></author>
      <author><first>Arturo</first><last>Montejo-Ráez</last></author>
      <pages>126–129</pages>
      <abstract>This article describes a system to predict the complexity of words for the Lexical Complexity Prediction (LCP) shared task hosted at SemEval 2021 (Task 1) with a new annotated English dataset with a Likert scale. Located in the Lexical Semantics track, the task consisted of predicting the complexity value of the words in context. A machine learning approach was carried out based on the frequency of the words and several characteristics added at word level. Over these features, a supervised random forest regression algorithm was trained. Several runs were performed with different values to observe the performance of the algorithm. For the evaluation, our best results reported a M.A.E score of 0.07347, M.S.E. of 0.00938, and R.M.S.E. of 0.096871. Our experiments showed that, with a greater number of characteristics, the precision of the classification increases.</abstract>
      <url hash="d0b886d4">2021.semeval-1.11</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.11</doi>
      <bibkey>ortiz-zambrano-montejo-raez-2021-complex</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="12">
      <title><fixed-case>TUDA</fixed-case>-<fixed-case>CCL</fixed-case> at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 1: Using Gradient-boosted Regression Tree Ensembles Trained on a Heterogeneous Feature Set for Predicting Lexical Complexity</title>
      <author><first>Sebastian</first><last>Gombert</last></author>
      <author><first>Sabine</first><last>Bartsch</last></author>
      <pages>130–137</pages>
      <abstract>In this paper, we present our systems submitted to SemEval-2021 Task 1 on lexical complexity prediction. The aim of this shared task was to create systems able to predict the lexical complexity of word tokens and bigram multiword expressions within a given sentence context, a continuous value indicating the difficulty in understanding a respective utterance. Our approach relies on gradient boosted regression tree ensembles fitted using a heterogeneous feature set combining linguistic features, static and contextualized word embeddings, psycholinguistic norm lexica, WordNet, word- and character bigram frequencies and inclusion in wordlists to create a model able to assign a word or multiword expression a context-dependent complexity score. We can show that especially contextualised string embeddings can help with predicting lexical complexity.</abstract>
      <url hash="4c533bc7">2021.semeval-1.12</url>
      <attachment type="OptionalSupplementaryMaterial" hash="459f6d1a">2021.semeval-1.12.OptionalSupplementaryMaterial.zip</attachment>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.12</doi>
      <bibkey>gombert-bartsch-2021-tuda</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="13">
      <title><fixed-case>JCT</fixed-case> at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 1: Context-aware Representation for Lexical Complexity Prediction</title>
      <author><first>Chaya</first><last>Liebeskind</last></author>
      <author><first>Otniel</first><last>Elkayam</last></author>
      <author><first>Shmuel</first><last>Liebeskind</last></author>
      <pages>138–143</pages>
      <abstract>In this paper, we present our contribution in SemEval-2021 Task 1: Lexical Complexity Prediction, where we integrate linguistic, statistical, and semantic properties of the target word and its context as features within a Machine Learning (ML) framework for predicting lexical complexity. In particular, we use BERT contextualized word embeddings to represent the semantic meaning of the target word and its context. We participated in the sub-task of predicting the complexity score of single words</abstract>
      <url hash="65c56c10">2021.semeval-1.13</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.13</doi>
      <bibkey>liebeskind-etal-2021-jct</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="14">
      <title><fixed-case>IAPUCP</fixed-case> at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 1: Stacking Fine-Tuned Transformers is Almost All You Need for Lexical Complexity Prediction</title>
      <author><first>Kervy</first><last>Rivas Rojas</last></author>
      <author><first>Fernando</first><last>Alva-Manchego</last></author>
      <pages>144–149</pages>
      <abstract>This paper describes our submission to SemEval-2021 Task 1: predicting the complexity score for single words. Our model leverages standard morphosyntactic and frequency-based features that proved helpful for Complex Word Identification (a related task), and combines them with predictions made by Transformer-based pre-trained models that were fine-tuned on the Shared Task data. Our submission system stacks all previous models with a LightGBM at the top. One novelty of our approach is the use of multi-task learning for fine-tuning a pre-trained model for both Lexical Complexity Prediction and Word Sense Disambiguation. Our analysis shows that all independent models achieve a good performance in the task, but that stacking them obtains a Pearson correlation of 0.7704, merely 0.018 points behind the winning submission.</abstract>
      <url hash="153efc4a">2021.semeval-1.14</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.14</doi>
      <bibkey>rivas-rojas-alva-manchego-2021-iapucp</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="15">
      <title><fixed-case>U</fixed-case>ppsala <fixed-case>NLP</fixed-case> at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 2: Multilingual Language Models for Fine-tuning and Feature Extraction in Word-in-Context Disambiguation</title>
      <author><first>Huiling</first><last>You</last></author>
      <author><first>Xingran</first><last>Zhu</last></author>
      <author><first>Sara</first><last>Stymne</last></author>
      <pages>150–156</pages>
      <abstract>We describe the Uppsala NLP submission to SemEval-2021 Task 2 on multilingual and cross-lingual word-in-context disambiguation. We explore the usefulness of three pre-trained multilingual language models, XLM-RoBERTa (XLMR), Multilingual BERT (mBERT) and multilingual distilled BERT (mDistilBERT). We compare these three models in two setups, fine-tuning and as feature extractors. In the second case we also experiment with using dependency-based information. We find that fine-tuning is better than feature extraction. XLMR performs better than mBERT in the cross-lingual setting both with fine-tuning and feature extraction, whereas these two models give a similar performance in the multilingual setting. mDistilBERT performs poorly with fine-tuning but gives similar results to the other models when used as a feature extractor. We submitted our two best systems, fine-tuned with XLMR and mBERT.</abstract>
      <url hash="b663aee7">2021.semeval-1.15</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.15</doi>
      <bibkey>you-etal-2021-uppsala</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="16">
      <title><fixed-case>S</fixed-case>koltech<fixed-case>NLP</fixed-case> at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 2: Generating Cross-Lingual Training Data for the Word-in-Context Task</title>
      <author><first>Anton</first><last>Razzhigaev</last></author>
      <author><first>Nikolay</first><last>Arefyev</last></author>
      <author><first>Alexander</first><last>Panchenko</last></author>
      <pages>157–162</pages>
      <abstract>In this paper, we present a system for the solution of the cross-lingual and multilingual word-in-context disambiguation task. Task organizers provided monolingual data in several languages, but no cross-lingual training data were available. To address the lack of the officially provided cross-lingual training data, we decided to generate such data ourselves. We describe a simple yet effective approach based on machine translation and back translation of the lexical units to the original language used in the context of this shared task. In our experiments, we used a neural system based on the XLM-R, a pre-trained transformer-based masked language model, as a baseline. We show the effectiveness of the proposed approach as it allows to substantially improve the performance of this strong neural baseline model. In addition, in this study, we present multiple types of the XLM-R based classifier, experimenting with various ways of mixing information from the first and second occurrences of the target word in two samples.</abstract>
      <url hash="3345619c">2021.semeval-1.16</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.16</doi>
      <bibkey>razzhigaev-etal-2021-skoltechnlp</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="17">
      <title>Zhestyatsky at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 2: <fixed-case>R</fixed-case>e<fixed-case>LU</fixed-case> over Cosine Similarity for <fixed-case>BERT</fixed-case> Fine-tuning</title>
      <author><first>Boris</first><last>Zhestiankin</last></author>
      <author><first>Maria</first><last>Ponomareva</last></author>
      <pages>163–168</pages>
      <abstract>This paper presents our contribution to SemEval-2021 Task 2: Multilingual and Cross-lingual Word-in-Context Disambiguation (MCL-WiC). Our experiments cover English (EN-EN) sub-track from the multilingual setting of the task. We experiment with several pre-trained language models and investigate an impact of different top-layers on fine-tuning. We find the combination of Cosine Similarity and ReLU activation leading to the most effective fine-tuning procedure. Our best model results in accuracy 92.7%, which is the fourth-best score in EN-EN sub-track.</abstract>
      <url hash="855da59b">2021.semeval-1.17</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.17</doi>
      <bibkey>zhestiankin-ponomareva-2021-zhestyatsky</bibkey>
      <pwccode url="https://github.com/zhestyatsky/MCL-WiC" additional="false">zhestyatsky/MCL-WiC</pwccode>
      <pwcdataset url="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/superglue">SuperGLUE</pwcdataset>
      <pwcdataset url="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/wic">WiC</pwcdataset>
    </paper>
    <paper id="18">
      <title><fixed-case>S</fixed-case>zeged<fixed-case>AI</fixed-case> at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 2: Zero-shot Approach for Multilingual and Cross-lingual Word-in-Context Disambiguation</title>
      <author><first>Gábor</first><last>Berend</last></author>
      <pages>169–174</pages>
      <abstract>In this paper, we introduce our system that we participated with at the multilingual and cross-lingual word-in-context disambiguation SemEval 2021 shared task. In our experiments, we investigated the possibility of using an all-words fine-grained word sense disambiguation system trained purely on sense-annotated data in English and draw predictions on the semantic equivalence of words in context based on the similarity of the ranked lists of the (English) WordNet synsets returned for the target words decisions had to be made for. We overcame the multi,-and cross-lingual aspects of the shared task by applying a multilingual transformer for encoding the texts written in either Arabic, English, French, Russian and Chinese. While our results lag behind top scoring submissions, it has the benefit that it not only provides a binary flag whether two words in their context have the same meaning, but also provides a more tangible output in the form of a ranked list of (English) WordNet synsets irrespective of the language of the input texts. As our framework is designed to be as generic as possible, it can be applied as a baseline for basically any language (supported by the multilingual transformed architecture employed) even in the absence of any additional form of language specific training data.</abstract>
      <url hash="b7e1ca58">2021.semeval-1.18</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.18</doi>
      <bibkey>berend-2021-szegedai</bibkey>
      <pwcdataset url="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/wic">WiC</pwcdataset>
      <pwcdataset url="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/word-sense-disambiguation-a-unified">Word Sense Disambiguation: a Unified Evaluation Framework and Empirical Comparison</pwcdataset>
    </paper>
    <paper id="19">
      <title><fixed-case>R</fixed-case>e<fixed-case>CAM</fixed-case>@<fixed-case>IITK</fixed-case> at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 4: <fixed-case>BERT</fixed-case> and <fixed-case>ALBERT</fixed-case> based Ensemble for Abstract Word Prediction</title>
      <author><first>Abhishek</first><last>Mittal</last></author>
      <author><first>Ashutosh</first><last>Modi</last></author>
      <pages>175–182</pages>
      <abstract>This paper describes our system for Task 4 of SemEval-2021: Reading Comprehension of Abstract Meaning (ReCAM). We participated in all subtasks where the main goal was to predict an abstract word missing from a statement. We fine-tuned the pre-trained masked language models namely BERT and ALBERT and used an Ensemble of these as our submitted system on Subtask 1 (ReCAM-Imperceptibility) and Subtask 2 (ReCAM-Nonspecificity). For Subtask 3 (ReCAM-Intersection), we submitted the ALBERT model as it gives the best results. We tried multiple approaches and found that Masked Language Modeling(MLM) based approach works the best.</abstract>
      <url hash="2d5eadc2">2021.semeval-1.19</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.19</doi>
      <bibkey>mittal-modi-2021-recam</bibkey>
      <pwccode url="https://github.com/amittal151/SemEval-2021-Task4_models" additional="false">amittal151/SemEval-2021-Task4_models</pwccode>
      <pwcdataset url="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/recam">ReCAM</pwcdataset>
    </paper>
    <paper id="20">
      <title><fixed-case>ECNU</fixed-case>_<fixed-case>ICA</fixed-case>_1 <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 4: Leveraging Knowledge-enhanced Graph Attention Networks for Reading Comprehension of Abstract Meaning</title>
      <author><first>Pingsheng</first><last>Liu</last></author>
      <author><first>Linlin</first><last>Wang</last></author>
      <author><first>Qian</first><last>Zhao</last></author>
      <author><first>Hao</first><last>Chen</last></author>
      <author><first>Yuxi</first><last>Feng</last></author>
      <author><first>Xin</first><last>Lin</last></author>
      <author><first>Liang</first><last>He</last></author>
      <pages>183–188</pages>
      <abstract>This paper describes our system for SemEval-2021 Task 4: Reading Comprehension of Abstract Meaning. To accomplish this task, we utilize the Knowledge-Enhanced Graph Attention Network (KEGAT) architecture with a novel semantic space transformation strategy. It leverages heterogeneous knowledge to learn adequate evidences, and seeks for an effective semantic space of abstract concepts to better improve the ability of a machine in understanding the abstract meaning of natural language. Experimental results show that our system achieves strong performance on this task in terms of both imperceptibility and nonspecificity.</abstract>
      <url hash="f5eeda12">2021.semeval-1.20</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.20</doi>
      <bibkey>liu-etal-2021-ecnu</bibkey>
      <pwcdataset url="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/conceptnet">ConceptNet</pwcdataset>
    </paper>
    <paper id="21">
      <title><fixed-case>LRG</fixed-case> at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 4: Improving Reading Comprehension with Abstract Words using Augmentation, Linguistic Features and Voting</title>
      <author><first>Abheesht</first><last>Sharma</last></author>
      <author><first>Harshit</first><last>Pandey</last></author>
      <author><first>Gunjan</first><last>Chhablani</last></author>
      <author><first>Yash</first><last>Bhartia</last></author>
      <author><first>Tirtharaj</first><last>Dash</last></author>
      <pages>189–198</pages>
      <abstract>We present our approaches and methods for SemEval-2021 Task-4 Reading Comprehension of Abstract Meaning. Given a question with a fill-in-the-blank, and a corresponding context, the task is to predict the most suitable word from a list of 5 options. There are three subtasks: Imperceptibility, Non-Specificity and Intersection. We use encoders of transformers-based models pretrained on the MLM task to build our Fill-in-the-blank (FitB) models. Moreover, to model imperceptibility, we define certain linguistic features, and to model non-specificity, we leverage information from hypernyms and hyponyms provided by a lexical database. Specifically, for non-specificity, we try out augmentation techniques, and other statistical techniques. We also propose variants, namely Chunk Voting and Max Context, to take care of input length restrictions for BERT, etc. Additionally, we perform a thorough ablation study, and use Integrated Gradients to explain our predictions on a few samples. Our models achieve accuracies of 75.31% and 77.84%, on the test sets for subtask-I and subtask-II, respectively. For subtask-III, we achieve accuracies of 65.64% and 64.27%.</abstract>
      <url hash="57a8c4f6">2021.semeval-1.21</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.21</doi>
      <bibkey>sharma-etal-2021-lrg</bibkey>
      <pwccode url="https://github.com/gchhablani/ReCAM" additional="false">gchhablani/ReCAM</pwccode>
    </paper>
    <paper id="22">
      <title><fixed-case>IIE</fixed-case>-<fixed-case>NLP</fixed-case>-Eyas at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 4: Enhancing <fixed-case>PLM</fixed-case> for <fixed-case>R</fixed-case>e<fixed-case>CAM</fixed-case> with Special Tokens, Re-Ranking, <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>iamese Encoders and Back Translation</title>
      <author><first>Yuqiang</first><last>Xie</last></author>
      <author><first>Luxi</first><last>Xing</last></author>
      <author><first>Wei</first><last>Peng</last></author>
      <author><first>Yue</first><last>Hu</last></author>
      <pages>199–204</pages>
      <abstract>This paper introduces our systems for all three subtasks of SemEval-2021 Task 4: Reading Comprehension of Abstract Meaning. To help our model better represent and understand abstract concepts in natural language, we well-design many simple and effective approaches adapted to the backbone model (RoBERTa). Specifically, we formalize the subtasks into the multiple-choice question answering format and add special tokens to abstract concepts, then, the final prediction of QA is considered as the result of subtasks. Additionally, we employ many finetuning tricks to improve the performance. Experimental results show that our approach gains significant performance compared with the baseline systems. Our system achieves eighth rank (87.51%) and tenth rank (89.64%) on the official blind test set of subtask 1 and subtask 2 respectively.</abstract>
      <url hash="99c08385">2021.semeval-1.22</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.22</doi>
      <bibkey>xie-etal-2021-iie</bibkey>
      <pwcdataset url="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/recam">ReCAM</pwcdataset>
    </paper>
    <paper id="23">
      <title><fixed-case>NLP</fixed-case>-<fixed-case>IIS</fixed-case>@<fixed-case>UT</fixed-case> at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 4: Machine Reading Comprehension using the Long Document Transformer</title>
      <author><first>Hossein</first><last>Basafa</last></author>
      <author><first>Sajad</first><last>Movahedi</last></author>
      <author><first>Ali</first><last>Ebrahimi</last></author>
      <author><first>Azadeh</first><last>Shakery</last></author>
      <author><first>Heshaam</first><last>Faili</last></author>
      <pages>205–210</pages>
      <abstract>This paper presents a technical report of our submission to the 4th task of SemEval-2021, titled: Reading Comprehension of Abstract Meaning. In this task, we want to predict the correct answer based on a question given a context. Usually, contexts are very lengthy and require a large receptive field from the model. Thus, common contextualized language models like BERT miss fine representation and performance due to the limited capacity of the input tokens. To tackle this problem, we used the longformer model to better process the sequences. Furthermore, we utilized the method proposed in the longformer benchmark on wikihop dataset which improved the accuracy on our task data from (23.01% and 22.95%) achieved by the baselines for subtask 1 and 2, respectively, to (70.30% and 64.38%).</abstract>
      <url hash="cba6750a">2021.semeval-1.23</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.23</doi>
      <bibkey>basafa-etal-2021-nlp</bibkey>
      <pwcdataset url="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/wikihop">WikiHop</pwcdataset>
    </paper>
    <paper id="24">
      <title><fixed-case>IITK</fixed-case>@Detox at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 5: Semi-Supervised Learning and Dice Loss for Toxic Spans Detection</title>
      <author><first>Archit</first><last>Bansal</last></author>
      <author><first>Abhay</first><last>Kaushik</last></author>
      <author><first>Ashutosh</first><last>Modi</last></author>
      <pages>211–219</pages>
      <abstract>In this work, we present our approach and findings for SemEval-2021 Task 5 - Toxic Spans Detection. The task’s main aim was to identify spans to which a given text’s toxicity could be attributed. The task is challenging mainly due to two constraints: the small training dataset and imbalanced class distribution. Our paper investigates two techniques, semi-supervised learning and learning with Self-Adjusting Dice Loss, for tackling these challenges. Our submitted system (ranked ninth on the leader board) consisted of an ensemble of various pre-trained Transformer Language Models trained using either of the above-proposed techniques.</abstract>
      <url hash="8a4b1d7a">2021.semeval-1.24</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.24</doi>
      <bibkey>bansal-etal-2021-iitk</bibkey>
      <pwccode url="https://github.com/architb1703/Toxic_Span" additional="false">architb1703/Toxic_Span</pwccode>
      <pwcdataset url="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/civil-comments">Civil Comments</pwcdataset>
    </paper>
    <paper id="25">
      <title><fixed-case>U</fixed-case>ni<fixed-case>P</fixed-case>arma at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 5: Toxic Spans Detection Using <fixed-case>C</fixed-case>haracter<fixed-case>BERT</fixed-case> and Bag-of-Words Model</title>
      <author><first>Akbar</first><last>Karimi</last></author>
      <author><first>Leonardo</first><last>Rossi</last></author>
      <author><first>Andrea</first><last>Prati</last></author>
      <pages>220–224</pages>
      <abstract>With the ever-increasing availability of digital information, toxic content is also on the rise. Therefore, the detection of this type of language is of paramount importance. We tackle this problem utilizing a combination of a state-of-the-art pre-trained language model (CharacterBERT) and a traditional bag-of-words technique. Since the content is full of toxic words that have not been written according to their dictionary spelling, attendance to individual characters is crucial. Therefore, we use CharacterBERT to extract features based on the word characters. It consists of a CharacterCNN module that learns character embeddings from the context. These are, then, fed into the well-known BERT architecture. The bag-of-words method, on the other hand, further improves upon that by making sure that some frequently used toxic words get labeled accordingly. With a ∼4 percent difference from the first team, our system ranked 36 th in the competition. The code is available for further research and reproduction of the results.</abstract>
      <url hash="04a9a034">2021.semeval-1.25</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.25</doi>
      <bibkey>karimi-etal-2021-uniparma</bibkey>
      <pwccode url="https://github.com/IMPLabUniPr/UniParma-at-semeval-2021-task-5" additional="false">IMPLabUniPr/UniParma-at-semeval-2021-task-5</pwccode>
    </paper>
    <paper id="26">
      <title><fixed-case>UPB</fixed-case> at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 5: Virtual Adversarial Training for Toxic Spans Detection</title>
      <author><first>Andrei</first><last>Paraschiv</last></author>
      <author><first>Dumitru-Clementin</first><last>Cercel</last></author>
      <author><first>Mihai</first><last>Dascalu</last></author>
      <pages>225–232</pages>
      <abstract>The real-world impact of polarization and toxicity in the online sphere marked the end of 2020 and the beginning of this year in a negative way. Semeval-2021, Task 5 - Toxic Spans Detection is based on a novel annotation of a subset of the Jigsaw Unintended Bias dataset and is the first language toxicity detection task dedicated to identifying the toxicity-level spans. For this task, participants had to automatically detect character spans in short comments that render the message as toxic. Our model considers applying Virtual Adversarial Training in a semi-supervised setting during the fine-tuning process of several Transformer-based models (i.e., BERT and RoBERTa), in combination with Conditional Random Fields. Our approach leads to performance improvements and more robust models, enabling us to achieve an F1-score of 65.73% in the official submission and an F1-score of 66.13% after further tuning during post-evaluation.</abstract>
      <url hash="0bb742a9">2021.semeval-1.26</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.26</doi>
      <bibkey>paraschiv-etal-2021-upb</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="27">
      <title><fixed-case>NLRG</fixed-case> at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 5: Toxic Spans Detection Leveraging <fixed-case>BERT</fixed-case>-based Token Classification and Span Prediction Techniques</title>
      <author><first>Gunjan</first><last>Chhablani</last></author>
      <author><first>Abheesht</first><last>Sharma</last></author>
      <author><first>Harshit</first><last>Pandey</last></author>
      <author><first>Yash</first><last>Bhartia</last></author>
      <author><first>Shan</first><last>Suthaharan</last></author>
      <pages>233–242</pages>
      <abstract>Toxicity detection of text has been a popular NLP task in the recent years. In SemEval-2021 Task-5 Toxic Spans Detection, the focus is on detecting toxic spans within English passages. Most state-of-the-art span detection approaches employ various techniques, each of which can be broadly classified into Token Classification or Span Prediction approaches. In our paper, we explore simple versions of both of these approaches and their performance on the task. Specifically, we use BERT-based models - BERT, RoBERTa, and SpanBERT for both approaches. We also combine these approaches and modify them to bring improvements for Toxic Spans prediction. To this end, we investigate results on four hybrid approaches - Multi-Span, Span+Token, LSTM-CRF, and a combination of predicted offsets using union/intersection. Additionally, we perform a thorough ablative analysis and analyze our observed results. Our best submission - a combination of SpanBERT Span Predictor and RoBERTa Token Classifier predictions - achieves an F1 score of 0.6753 on the test set. Our best post-eval F1 score is 0.6895 on intersection of predicted offsets from top-3 RoBERTa Token Classification checkpoints. These approaches improve the performance by 3% on average than those of the shared baseline models - RNNSL and SpaCy NER.</abstract>
      <url hash="4a0f6b63">2021.semeval-1.27</url>
      <attachment type="OptionalSupplementaryMaterial" hash="94f1075b">2021.semeval-1.27.OptionalSupplementaryMaterial.zip</attachment>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.27</doi>
      <bibkey>chhablani-etal-2021-nlrg</bibkey>
      <pwccode url="https://github.com/gchhablani/toxic-spans-detection" additional="false">gchhablani/toxic-spans-detection</pwccode>
      <pwcdataset url="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/civil-comments">Civil Comments</pwcdataset>
      <pwcdataset url="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/squad">SQuAD</pwcdataset>
    </paper>
    <paper id="28">
      <title><fixed-case>U</fixed-case>o<fixed-case>B</fixed-case> at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 5: Extending Pre-Trained Language Models to Include Task and Domain-Specific Information for Toxic Span Prediction</title>
      <author><first>Erik</first><last>Yan</last></author>
      <author><first>Harish</first><last>Tayyar Madabushi</last></author>
      <pages>243–248</pages>
      <abstract>Toxicity is pervasive in social media and poses a major threat to the health of online communities. The recent introduction of pre-trained language models, which have achieved state-of-the-art results in many NLP tasks, has transformed the way in which we approach natural language processing. However, the inherent nature of pre-training means that they are unlikely to capture task-specific statistical information or learn domain-specific knowledge. Additionally, most implementations of these models typically do not employ conditional random fields, a method for simultaneous token classification. We show that these modifications can improve model performance on the Toxic Spans Detection task at SemEval-2021 to achieve a score within 4 percentage points of the top performing team.</abstract>
      <url hash="c667fc32">2021.semeval-1.28</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.28</doi>
      <bibkey>yan-tayyar-madabushi-2021-uob</bibkey>
      <pwccode url="https://github.com/erikdyan/toxic_span_detection" additional="false">erikdyan/toxic_span_detection</pwccode>
    </paper>
    <paper id="29">
      <title>Cisco at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 5: What’s Toxic?: Leveraging Transformers for Multiple Toxic Span Extraction from Online Comments</title>
      <author><first>Sreyan</first><last>Ghosh</last></author>
      <author><first>Sonal</first><last>Kumar</last></author>
      <pages>249–257</pages>
      <abstract>Social network platforms are generally used to share positive, constructive, and insightful content. However, in recent times, people often get exposed to objectionable content like threat, identity attacks, hate speech, insults, obscene texts, offensive remarks or bullying. Existing work on toxic speech detection focuses on binary classification or on differentiating toxic speech among a small set of categories. This paper describes the system proposed by team Cisco for SemEval-2021 Task 5: Toxic Spans Detection, the first shared task focusing on detecting the spans in the text that attribute to its toxicity, in English language. We approach this problem primarily in two ways: a sequence tagging approach and a dependency parsing approach. In our sequence tagging approach we tag each token in a sentence under a particular tagging scheme. Our best performing architecture in this approach also proved to be our best performing architecture overall with an F1 score of 0.6922, thereby placing us 7th on the final evaluation phase leaderboard. We also explore a dependency parsing approach where we extract spans from the input sentence under the supervision of target span boundaries and rank our spans using a biaffine model. Finally, we also provide a detailed analysis of our results and model performance in our paper.</abstract>
      <url hash="9835d2f6">2021.semeval-1.29</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.29</doi>
      <bibkey>ghosh-kumar-2021-cisco</bibkey>
      <pwccode url="https://github.com/Sreyan88/SemEval-2021-Toxic-Spans-Detection" additional="false">Sreyan88/SemEval-2021-Toxic-Spans-Detection</pwccode>
    </paper>
    <paper id="30">
      <title><fixed-case>M</fixed-case>ed<fixed-case>AI</fixed-case> at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 5: Start-to-end Tagging Framework for Toxic Spans Detection</title>
      <author><first>Zhen</first><last>Wang</last></author>
      <author><first>Hongjie</first><last>Fan</last></author>
      <author><first>Junfei</first><last>Liu</last></author>
      <pages>258–262</pages>
      <abstract>This paper describes the system submitted to SemEval 2021 Task 5: Toxic Spans Detection. The task concerns evaluating systems that detect the spans that make a text toxic when detecting such spans are possible. To address the possibly multi-span detection problem, we develop a start-to-end tagging framework on top of RoBERTa based language model. Besides, we design a custom loss function that takes distance into account. In comparison to other participating teams, our system has achieved 69.03% F1 score, which is slightly lower (-1.8 and -1.73) than the top 1(70.83%) and top 2 (70.77%), respectively.</abstract>
      <url hash="2eb21c32">2021.semeval-1.30</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.30</doi>
      <bibkey>wang-etal-2021-medai</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="31">
      <title><fixed-case>H</fixed-case>amilton<fixed-case>D</fixed-case>inggg at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 5: Investigating Toxic Span Detection using <fixed-case>R</fixed-case>o<fixed-case>BERT</fixed-case>a Pre-training</title>
      <author><first>Huiyang</first><last>Ding</last></author>
      <author><first>David</first><last>Jurgens</last></author>
      <pages>263–269</pages>
      <abstract>This paper presents our system submission to task 5: Toxic Spans Detection of the SemEval-2021 competition. The competition aims at detecting the spans that make a toxic span toxic. In this paper, we demonstrate our system for detecting toxic spans, which includes expanding the toxic training set with Local Interpretable Model-Agnostic Explanations (LIME), fine-tuning RoBERTa model for detection, and error analysis. We found that feeding the model with an expanded training set using Reddit comments of polarized-toxicity and labeling with LIME on top of logistic regression classification could help RoBERTa more accurately learn to recognize toxic spans. We achieved a span-level F1 score of 0.6715 on the testing phase. Our quantitative and qualitative results show that the predictions from our system could be a good supplement to the gold training set’s annotations.</abstract>
      <url hash="cea17923">2021.semeval-1.31</url>
      <attachment type="OptionalSupplementaryMaterial" hash="38840fbc">2021.semeval-1.31.OptionalSupplementaryMaterial.zip</attachment>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.31</doi>
      <bibkey>ding-jurgens-2021-hamiltondinggg</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="32">
      <title><fixed-case>WVOQ</fixed-case> at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 6: <fixed-case>BART</fixed-case> for Span Detection and Classification</title>
      <author><first>Cees</first><last>Roele</last></author>
      <pages>270–274</pages>
      <abstract>Simultaneous span detection and classification is a task not currently addressed in standard NLP frameworks. The present paper describes why and how an EncoderDecoder model was used to combine span detection and classification to address subtask 2 of SemEval-2021 Task 6.</abstract>
      <url hash="c1c2908b">2021.semeval-1.32</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.32</doi>
      <bibkey>roele-2021-wvoq</bibkey>
      <pwccode url="https://github.com/ceesroele/SemEval-2021-Task-6" additional="false">ceesroele/SemEval-2021-Task-6</pwccode>
    </paper>
    <paper id="33">
      <title><fixed-case>H</fixed-case>umor<fixed-case>H</fixed-case>unter at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 7: Humor and Offense Recognition with Disentangled Attention</title>
      <author><first>Yubo</first><last>Xie</last></author>
      <author><first>Junze</first><last>Li</last></author>
      <author><first>Pearl</first><last>Pu</last></author>
      <pages>275–280</pages>
      <abstract>In this paper, we describe our system submitted to SemEval 2021 Task 7: HaHackathon: Detecting and Rating Humor and Offense. The task aims at predicting whether the given text is humorous, the average humor rating given by the annotators, and whether the humor rating is controversial. In addition, the task also involves predicting how offensive the text is. Our approach adopts the DeBERTa architecture with disentangled attention mechanism, where the attention scores between words are calculated based on their content vectors and relative position vectors. We also took advantage of the pre-trained language models and fine-tuned the DeBERTa model on all the four subtasks. We experimented with several BERT-like structures and found that the large DeBERTa model generally performs better. During the evaluation phase, our system achieved an F-score of 0.9480 on subtask 1a, an RMSE of 0.5510 on subtask 1b, an F-score of 0.4764 on subtask 1c, and an RMSE of 0.4230 on subtask 2a (rank 3 on the leaderboard).</abstract>
      <url hash="8eed6474">2021.semeval-1.33</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.33</doi>
      <bibkey>xie-etal-2021-humorhunter</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="34">
      <title>Grenzlinie at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 7: Detecting and Rating Humor and Offense</title>
      <author><first>Renyuan</first><last>Liu</last></author>
      <author><first>Xiaobing</first><last>Zhou</last></author>
      <pages>281–285</pages>
      <abstract>This paper introduces the result of Team Grenzlinie’s experiment in SemEval-2021 task 7: HaHackathon: Detecting and Rating Humor and Offense. This task has two subtasks. Subtask1 includes the humor detection task, the humor rating prediction task, and the humor controversy detection task. Subtask2 is an offensive rating prediction task. Detection task is a binary classification task, and the rating prediction task is a regression task between 0 to 5. 0 means the task is not humorous or not offensive, 5 means the task is very humorous or very offensive. For all the tasks, this paper chooses RoBERTa as the pre-trained model. In classification tasks, Bi-LSTM and adversarial training are adopted. In the regression task, the Bi-LSTM is also adopted. And then we propose a new approach named compare method. Finally, our system achieves an F1-score of 95.05% in the humor detection task, F1-score of 61.74% in the humor controversy detection task, 0.6143 RMSE in humor rating task, 0.4761 RMSE in the offensive rating task on the test datasets.</abstract>
      <url hash="7ea7f0d2">2021.semeval-1.34</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.34</doi>
      <bibkey>liu-zhou-2021-grenzlinie</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="35">
      <title>abcbpc at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 7: <fixed-case>ERNIE</fixed-case>-based Multi-task Model for Detecting and Rating Humor and Offense</title>
      <author><first>Chao</first><last>Pang</last></author>
      <author><first>Xiaoran</first><last>Fan</last></author>
      <author><first>Weiyue</first><last>Su</last></author>
      <author><first>Xuyi</first><last>Chen</last></author>
      <author><first>Shuohuan</first><last>Wang</last></author>
      <author><first>Jiaxiang</first><last>Liu</last></author>
      <author><first>Xuan</first><last>Ouyang</last></author>
      <author><first>Shikun</first><last>Feng</last></author>
      <author><first>Yu</first><last>Sun</last></author>
      <pages>286–289</pages>
      <abstract>This paper describes our system participated in Task 7 of SemEval-2021: Detecting and Rating Humor and Offense. The task is designed to detect and score humor and offense which are influenced by subjective factors. In order to obtain semantic information from a large amount of unlabeled data, we applied unsupervised pre-trained language models. By conducting research and experiments, we found that the ERNIE 2.0 and DeBERTa pre-trained models achieved impressive performance in various subtasks. Therefore, we applied the above pre-trained models to fine-tune the downstream neural network. In the process of fine-tuning the model, we adopted multi-task training strategy and ensemble learning method. Based on the above strategy and method, we achieved RMSE of 0.4959 for subtask 1b, and finally won the first place.</abstract>
      <url hash="ff50db16">2021.semeval-1.35</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.35</doi>
      <bibkey>pang-etal-2021-abcbpc</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="36">
      <title>Humor@<fixed-case>IITK</fixed-case> at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 7: Large Language Models for Quantifying Humor and Offensiveness</title>
      <author><first>Aishwarya</first><last>Gupta</last></author>
      <author><first>Avik</first><last>Pal</last></author>
      <author><first>Bholeshwar</first><last>Khurana</last></author>
      <author><first>Lakshay</first><last>Tyagi</last></author>
      <author><first>Ashutosh</first><last>Modi</last></author>
      <pages>290–296</pages>
      <abstract>Humor and Offense are highly subjective due to multiple word senses, cultural knowledge, and pragmatic competence. Hence, accurately detecting humorous and offensive texts has several compelling use cases in Recommendation Systems and Personalized Content Moderation. However, due to the lack of an extensive labeled dataset, most prior works in this domain haven’t explored large neural models for subjective humor understanding. This paper explores whether large neural models and their ensembles can capture the intricacies associated with humor/offense detection and rating. Our experiments on the SemEval-2021 Task 7: HaHackathon show that we can develop reasonable humor and offense detection systems with such models. Our models are ranked 3rd in subtask 1b and consistently ranked around the top 33% of the leaderboard for the remaining subtasks.</abstract>
      <url hash="3e4a4e46">2021.semeval-1.36</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.36</doi>
      <bibkey>gupta-etal-2021-humor</bibkey>
      <pwccode url="https://github.com/aishgupta/Quantifying-Humor-Offensiveness" additional="false">aishgupta/Quantifying-Humor-Offensiveness</pwccode>
    </paper>
    <paper id="37">
      <title><fixed-case>R</fixed-case>o<fixed-case>M</fixed-case>a at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 7: A Transformer-based Approach for Detecting and Rating Humor and Offense</title>
      <author><first>Roberto</first><last>Labadie</last></author>
      <author><first>Mariano Jason</first><last>Rodriguez</last></author>
      <author><first>Reynier</first><last>Ortega</last></author>
      <author><first>Paolo</first><last>Rosso</last></author>
      <pages>297–305</pages>
      <abstract>In this paper we describe the systems used by the RoMa team in the shared task on Detecting and Rating Humor and Offense (HaHackathon) at SemEval 2021. Our systems rely on data representations learned through fine-tuned neural language models. Particularly, we explore two distinct architectures. The first one is based on a Siamese Neural Network (SNN) combined with a graph-based clustering method. The SNN model is used for learning a latent space where instances of humor and non-humor can be distinguished. The clustering method is applied to build prototypes of both classes which are used for training and classifying new messages. The second one combines neural language model representations with a linear regression model which makes the final ratings. Our systems achieved the best results for humor classification using model one, whereas for offensive and humor rating the second model obtained better performance. In the case of the controversial humor prediction, the most significant improvement was achieved by a fine-tuning of the neural language model. In general, the results achieved are encouraging and give us a starting point for further improvements.</abstract>
      <url hash="0edd40af">2021.semeval-1.37</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.37</doi>
      <bibkey>labadie-etal-2021-roma</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="38">
      <title><fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 8: <fixed-case>M</fixed-case>eas<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val – Extracting Counts and Measurements and their Related Contexts</title>
      <author><first>Corey</first><last>Harper</last></author>
      <author><first>Jessica</first><last>Cox</last></author>
      <author><first>Curt</first><last>Kohler</last></author>
      <author><first>Antony</first><last>Scerri</last></author>
      <author><first>Ron</first><last>Daniel Jr.</last></author>
      <author><first>Paul</first><last>Groth</last></author>
      <pages>306–316</pages>
      <abstract>We describe MeasEval, a SemEval task of extracting counts, measurements, and related context from scientific documents, which is of significant importance to the creation of Knowledge Graphs that distill information from the scientific literature. This is a new task in 2021, for which over 75 submissions from 25 participants were received. We expect the data developed for this task and the findings reported to be valuable to the scientific knowledge extraction, metrology, and automated knowledge base construction communities.</abstract>
      <url hash="9bf9d9b6">2021.semeval-1.38</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.38</doi>
      <bibkey>harper-etal-2021-semeval</bibkey>
      <video href="2021.semeval-1.38.mp4"/>
    </paper>
    <paper id="39">
      <title><fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 9: Fact Verification and Evidence Finding for Tabular Data in Scientific Documents (<fixed-case>SEM</fixed-case>-<fixed-case>TAB</fixed-case>-<fixed-case>FACTS</fixed-case>)</title>
      <author><first>Nancy X. R.</first><last>Wang</last></author>
      <author><first>Diwakar</first><last>Mahajan</last></author>
      <author><first>Marina</first><last>Danilevsky</last></author>
      <author><first>Sara</first><last>Rosenthal</last></author>
      <pages>317–326</pages>
      <abstract>Understanding tables is an important and relevant task that involves understanding table structure as well as being able to compare and contrast information within cells. In this paper, we address this challenge by presenting a new dataset and tasks that addresses this goal in a shared task in SemEval 2020 Task 9: Fact Verification and Evidence Finding for Tabular Data in Scientific Documents (SEM-TAB-FACTS). Our dataset contains 981 manually-generated tables and an auto-generated dataset of 1980 tables providing over 180K statement and over 16M evidence annotations. SEM-TAB-FACTS featured two sub-tasks. In sub-task A, the goal was to determine if a statement is supported, refuted or unknown in relation to a table. In sub-task B, the focus was on identifying the specific cells of a table that provide evidence for the statement. 69 teams signed up to participate in the task with 19 successful submissions to subtask A and 12 successful submissions to subtask B. We present our results and main findings from the competition.</abstract>
      <url hash="1129ce70">2021.semeval-1.39</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.39</doi>
      <bibkey>wang-etal-2021-semeval</bibkey>
      <video href="2021.semeval-1.39.mp4"/>
      <pwcdataset url="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/infotabs">InfoTabS</pwcdataset>
      <pwcdataset url="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/tabfact">TabFact</pwcdataset>
    </paper>
    <paper id="40">
      <title><fixed-case>B</fixed-case>reaking<fixed-case>BERT</fixed-case>@<fixed-case>IITK</fixed-case> at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 9: Statement Verification and Evidence Finding with Tables</title>
      <author><first>Aditya</first><last>Jindal</last></author>
      <author><first>Ankur</first><last>Gupta</last></author>
      <author><first>Jaya</first><last>Srivastava</last></author>
      <author><first>Preeti</first><last>Menghwani</last></author>
      <author><first>Vijit</first><last>Malik</last></author>
      <author><first>Vishesh</first><last>Kaushik</last></author>
      <author><first>Ashutosh</first><last>Modi</last></author>
      <pages>327–337</pages>
      <abstract>Recently, there has been an interest in the research on factual verification and prediction over structured data like tables and graphs. To circumvent any false news incident, it is necessary to not only model and predict over structured data efficiently but also to explain those predictions. In this paper, as the part of the SemEval-2021 Task 9, we tackle the problem of fact verification and evidence finding over tabular data. There are two subtasks, in which given a table and a statement/fact, the subtask A is to determine whether the statement is inferred from the tabular data and the subtask B is to determine which cells in the table provide evidence for the former subtask. We make a comparison of the baselines and state of the art approaches over the given SemTabFact dataset. We also propose a novel approach CellBERT to solve the task of evidence finding, as a form of Natural Language Inference task. We obtain a 3-way F1 score of 0.69 on subtask A and an F1 score of 0.65 on subtask B.</abstract>
      <url hash="ec5c7ed2">2021.semeval-1.40</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.40</doi>
      <bibkey>jindal-etal-2021-breakingbert</bibkey>
      <video href="2021.semeval-1.40.mp4"/>
      <pwcdataset url="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/tabfact">TabFact</pwcdataset>
    </paper>
    <paper id="41">
      <title><fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 12: Learning with Disagreements</title>
      <author><first>Alexandra</first><last>Uma</last></author>
      <author><first>Tommaso</first><last>Fornaciari</last></author>
      <author><first>Anca</first><last>Dumitrache</last></author>
      <author><first>Tristan</first><last>Miller</last></author>
      <author><first>Jon</first><last>Chamberlain</last></author>
      <author><first>Barbara</first><last>Plank</last></author>
      <author><first>Edwin</first><last>Simpson</last></author>
      <author><first>Massimo</first><last>Poesio</last></author>
      <pages>338–347</pages>
      <abstract>Disagreement between coders is ubiquitous in virtually all datasets annotated with human judgements in both natural language processing and computer vision. However, most supervised machine learning methods assume that a single preferred interpretation exists for each item, which is at best an idealization. The aim of the SemEval-2021 shared task on learning with disagreements (Le-Wi-Di) was to provide a unified testing framework for methods for learning from data containing multiple and possibly contradictory annotations covering the best-known datasets containing information about disagreements for interpreting language and classifying images. In this paper we describe the shared task and its results.</abstract>
      <url hash="b602aa5e">2021.semeval-1.41</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.41</doi>
      <bibkey>uma-etal-2021-semeval</bibkey>
      <video href="2021.semeval-1.41.mp4"/>
      <pwcdataset url="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/cifar-10">CIFAR-10</pwcdataset>
      <pwcdataset url="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/cifar-10h">CIFAR-10H</pwcdataset>
      <pwcdataset url="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/labelme">LabelMe</pwcdataset>
    </paper>
    <paper id="42">
      <title><fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 10: Source-Free Domain Adaptation for Semantic Processing</title>
      <author><first>Egoitz</first><last>Laparra</last></author>
      <author><first>Xin</first><last>Su</last></author>
      <author><first>Yiyun</first><last>Zhao</last></author>
      <author><first>Özlem</first><last>Uzuner</last></author>
      <author><first>Timothy</first><last>Miller</last></author>
      <author><first>Steven</first><last>Bethard</last></author>
      <pages>348–356</pages>
      <abstract>This paper presents the Source-Free Domain Adaptation shared task held within SemEval-2021. The aim of the task was to explore adaptation of machine-learning models in the face of data sharing constraints. Specifically, we consider the scenario where annotations exist for a domain but cannot be shared. Instead, participants are provided with models trained on that (source) data. Participants also receive some labeled data from a new (development) domain on which to explore domain adaptation algorithms. Participants are then tested on data representing a new (target) domain. We explored this scenario with two different semantic tasks: negation detection (a text classification task) and time expression recognition (a sequence tagging task).</abstract>
      <url hash="a36fe8ab">2021.semeval-1.42</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.42</doi>
      <bibkey>laparra-etal-2021-semeval</bibkey>
      <pwccode url="https://github.com/machine-learning-for-medical-language/source-free-domain-adaptation" additional="false">machine-learning-for-medical-language/source-free-domain-adaptation</pwccode>
    </paper>
    <paper id="43">
      <title><fixed-case>BLCUFIGHT</fixed-case> at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 10: Novel Unsupervised Frameworks For Source-Free Domain Adaptation</title>
      <author><first>Weikang</first><last>Wang</last></author>
      <author><first>Yi</first><last>Wu</last></author>
      <author><first>Yixiang</first><last>Liu</last></author>
      <author><first>Pengyuan</first><last>Liu</last></author>
      <pages>357–363</pages>
      <abstract>Domain adaptation assumes that samples from source and target domains are freely accessible during a training phase. However, such assumption is rarely plausible in the real-world and may causes data-privacy issues, especially when the label of the source domain can be a sensitive attribute as an identifier. SemEval-2021 task 10 focuses on these issues. We participate in the task and propose novel frameworks based on self-training method. In our systems, two different frameworks are designed to solve text classification and sequence labeling. These approaches are tested to be effective which ranks the third among all system in subtask A, and ranks the first among all system in subtask B.</abstract>
      <url hash="7ca9e8b8">2021.semeval-1.43</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.43</doi>
      <bibkey>wang-etal-2021-blcufight</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="44">
      <title><fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 11: <fixed-case>NLPC</fixed-case>ontribution<fixed-case>G</fixed-case>raph - Structuring Scholarly <fixed-case>NLP</fixed-case> Contributions for a Research Knowledge Graph</title>
      <author><first>Jennifer</first><last>D’Souza</last></author>
      <author><first>Sören</first><last>Auer</last></author>
      <author><first>Ted</first><last>Pedersen</last></author>
      <pages>364–376</pages>
      <abstract>There is currently a gap between the natural language expression of scholarly publications and their structured semantic content modeling to enable intelligent content search. With the volume of research growing exponentially every year, a search feature operating over semantically structured content is compelling. The SemEval-2021 Shared Task NLPContributionGraph (a.k.a. ‘the NCG task’) tasks participants to develop automated systems that structure contributions from NLP scholarly articles in the English language. Being the first-of-its-kind in the SemEval series, the task released structured data from NLP scholarly articles at three levels of information granularity, i.e. at sentence-level, phrase-level, and phrases organized as triples toward Knowledge Graph (KG) building. The sentence-level annotations comprised the few sentences about the article’s contribution. The phrase-level annotations were scientific term and predicate phrases from the contribution sentences. Finally, the triples constituted the research overview KG. For the Shared Task, participating systems were then expected to automatically classify contribution sentences, extract scientific terms and relations from the sentences, and organize them as KG triples. Overall, the task drew a strong participation demographic of seven teams and 27 participants. The best end-to-end task system classified contribution sentences at 57.27% F1, phrases at 46.41% F1, and triples at 22.28% F1. While the absolute performance to generate triples remains low, as conclusion to the article, the difficulty of producing such data and as a consequence of modeling it is highlighted.</abstract>
      <url hash="1ad8ac65">2021.semeval-1.44</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.44</doi>
      <bibkey>dsouza-etal-2021-semeval</bibkey>
      <video href="2021.semeval-1.44.mp4"/>
      <pwcdataset url="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/semeval-2021-task-11-nlpcontributiongraph">SemEval-2021 Task-11</pwcdataset>
    </paper>
    <paper id="45">
      <title><fixed-case>UIUC</fixed-case>_<fixed-case>B</fixed-case>io<fixed-case>NLP</fixed-case> at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 11: A Cascade of Neural Models for Structuring Scholarly <fixed-case>NLP</fixed-case> Contributions</title>
      <author><first>Haoyang</first><last>Liu</last></author>
      <author><first>M. Janina</first><last>Sarol</last></author>
      <author><first>Halil</first><last>Kilicoglu</last></author>
      <pages>377–386</pages>
      <abstract>We propose a cascade of neural models that performs sentence classification, phrase recognition, and triple extraction to automatically structure the scholarly contributions of NLP publications. To identify the most important contribution sentences in a paper, we used a BERT-based classifier with positional features (Subtask 1). A BERT-CRF model was used to recognize and characterize relevant phrases in contribution sentences (Subtask 2). We categorized the triples into several types based on whether and how their elements were expressed in text, and addressed each type using separate BERT-based classifiers as well as rules (Subtask 3). Our system was officially ranked second in Phase 1 evaluation and first in both parts of Phase 2 evaluation. After fixing a submission error in Pharse 1, our approach yields the best results overall. In this paper, in addition to a system description, we also provide further analysis of our results, highlighting its strengths and limitations. We make our code publicly available at <url>https://github.com/Liu-Hy/nlp-contrib-graph</url>.</abstract>
      <url hash="c36006da">2021.semeval-1.45</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.45</doi>
      <bibkey>liu-etal-2021-uiuc</bibkey>
      <video href="2021.semeval-1.45.mp4"/>
      <pwccode url="https://github.com/Liu-Hy/nlp-contrib-graph" additional="false">Liu-Hy/nlp-contrib-graph</pwccode>
    </paper>
    <paper id="46">
      <title><fixed-case>KGP</fixed-case> at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 8: Leveraging Multi-Staged Language Models for Extracting Measurements, their Attributes and Relations</title>
      <author><first>Neel</first><last>Karia</last></author>
      <author><first>Ayush</first><last>Kaushal</last></author>
      <author><first>Faraaz</first><last>Mallick</last></author>
      <pages>387–396</pages>
      <abstract>SemEval-2021 Task 8: MeasEval aims at improving the machine understanding of measurements in scientific texts through a set of entity and semantic relation extraction sub-tasks on identifying quantity spans along with various attributes and relationships. This paper describes our system, consisting of a three-stage pipeline, that leverages pre-trained language models to extract the quantity spans in the text, followed by intelligent templates to identify units and modifiers. Finally, it identifies the quantity attributes and their relations using language models boosted with a feature re-using hierarchical architecture and multi-task learning. Our submission significantly outperforms the baseline, with the best model from the post-evaluation phase delivering more than 100% increase on F1 (Overall) from the baseline.</abstract>
      <url hash="32ef1afe">2021.semeval-1.46</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.46</doi>
      <bibkey>karia-etal-2021-kgp</bibkey>
      <pwccode url="https://github.com/Ayushk4/SE-T8" additional="false">Ayushk4/SE-T8</pwccode>
    </paper>
    <paper id="47">
      <title><fixed-case>DPR</fixed-case> at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 8: Dynamic Path Reasoning for Measurement Relation Extraction</title>
      <author><first>Amir</first><last>Pouran Ben Veyseh</last></author>
      <author><first>Franck</first><last>Dernoncourt</last></author>
      <author><first>Thien Huu</first><last>Nguyen</last></author>
      <pages>397–403</pages>
      <abstract>Scientific documents are replete with measurements mentioned in various formats and styles. As such, in a document with multiple quantities and measured entities, the task of associating each quantity to its corresponding measured entity is challenging. Thus, it is necessary to have a method to efficiently extract all measurements and attributes related to them. To this end, in this paper, we propose a novel model for the task of measurement relation extraction (MRE) whose goal is to recognize the relation between measured entities, quantities, and conditions mentioned in a document. Our model employs a deep translation-based architecture to dynamically induce the important words in the document to classify the relation between a pair of entities. Furthermore, we introduce a novel regularization technique based on Information Bottleneck (IB) to filter out the noisy information from the induced set of important words. Our experiments on the recent SemEval 2021 Task 8 datasets reveal the effectiveness of the proposed model.</abstract>
      <url hash="6967f8f4">2021.semeval-1.47</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.47</doi>
      <bibkey>pouran-ben-veyseh-etal-2021-dpr</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="48">
      <title><fixed-case>CL</fixed-case>a<fixed-case>C</fixed-case>-np at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 8: Dependency <fixed-case>DGCNN</fixed-case></title>
      <author><first>Nihatha</first><last>Lathiff</last></author>
      <author><first>Pavel PK</first><last>Khloponin</last></author>
      <author><first>Sabine</first><last>Bergler</last></author>
      <pages>404–409</pages>
      <abstract>MeasEval aims at identifying quantities along with the entities that are measured with additional properties within English scientific documents. The variety of styles used makes measurements, a most crucial aspect of scientific writing, challenging to extract. This paper presents ablation studies making the case for several preprocessing steps such as specialized tokenization rules. For linguistic structure, we encode dependency trees in a Deep Graph Convolution Network (DGCNN) for multi-task classification.</abstract>
      <url hash="dc088963">2021.semeval-1.48</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.48</doi>
      <bibkey>lathiff-etal-2021-clac</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="49">
      <title><fixed-case>CL</fixed-case>a<fixed-case>C</fixed-case>-<fixed-case>BP</fixed-case> at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 8: <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>ci<fixed-case>BERT</fixed-case> Plus Rules for <fixed-case>M</fixed-case>eas<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val</title>
      <author><first>Benjamin</first><last>Therien</last></author>
      <author><first>Parsa</first><last>Bagherzadeh</last></author>
      <author><first>Sabine</first><last>Bergler</last></author>
      <pages>410–415</pages>
      <abstract>This paper explains the design of a heterogeneous system that ranked eighth in competition in SemEval2021 Task 8. We analyze ablation experiments and demonstrate how the system components, namely tokenizer, unit identifier, modifier classifier, and language model, affect the overall score. We compare our results to similar experiments from the literature and introduce a grouping algorithm developed in the post-evaluation phase that increased our system’s overall score, hypothetically elevating our competition rank from eight to six.</abstract>
      <url hash="f57f8c47">2021.semeval-1.49</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.49</doi>
      <bibkey>therien-etal-2021-clac</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="50">
      <title><fixed-case>TH</fixed-case>i<fixed-case>F</fixed-case>ly_<fixed-case>Q</fixed-case>ueens at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 9: Two-stage Statement Verification with Adaptive Ensembling and Slot-based Operation</title>
      <author><first>Yuxuan</first><last>Zhou</last></author>
      <author><first>Kaiyin</first><last>Zhou</last></author>
      <author><first>Xien</first><last>Liu</last></author>
      <author><first>Ji</first><last>Wu</last></author>
      <author><first>Xiaodan</first><last>Zhu</last></author>
      <pages>416–422</pages>
      <abstract>This paper describes our system for verifying statements with tables at SemEval-2021 Task 9. We developed a two-stage verifying system based on the latest table-based pre-trained model GraPPa. Multiple networks are devised to verify different types of statements in the competition dataset and an adaptive model ensembling technique is applied to ensemble models in both stages. A statement-slot-based symbolic operation module is also used in our system to further improve the performance and stability of the system. Our model achieves second place in the 3-way classification and fourth place in the 2-way classification evaluation. Several ablation experiments show the effectiveness of different modules proposed in this paper.</abstract>
      <url hash="9fbc304d">2021.semeval-1.50</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.50</doi>
      <bibkey>zhou-etal-2021-thifly</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="51">
      <title><fixed-case>TAPAS</fixed-case> at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 9: Reasoning over tables with intermediate pre-training</title>
      <author><first>Thomas</first><last>Müller</last></author>
      <author><first>Julian</first><last>Eisenschlos</last></author>
      <author><first>Syrine</first><last>Krichene</last></author>
      <pages>423–430</pages>
      <abstract>We present the TAPAS contribution to the Shared Task on Statement Verification and Evidence Finding with Tables (SemEval 2021 Task 9, Wang et al. (2021)). SEM TAB FACT Task A is a classification task of recognizing if a statement is entailed, neutral or refuted by the content of a given table. We adopt the binary TAPAS model of Eisenschlos et al. (2020) to this task. We learn two binary classification models: A first model to predict if a statement is neutral or non-neutral and a second one to predict if it is entailed or refuted. As the shared task training set contains only entailed or refuted examples, we generate artificial neutral examples to train the first model. Both models are pre-trained using a MASKLM objective, intermediate counter-factual and synthetic data (Eisenschlos et al., 2020) and TABFACT (Chen et al., 2020), a large table entailment dataset. We find that the artificial neutral examples are somewhat effective at training the first model, achieving 68.03 test F1 versus the 60.47 of a majority baseline. For the second stage, we find that the pre-training on the intermediate data and TABFACT improves the results over MASKLM pre-training (68.03 vs 57.01).</abstract>
      <url hash="c2e85cd7">2021.semeval-1.51</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.51</doi>
      <bibkey>muller-etal-2021-tapas</bibkey>
      <pwcdataset url="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/sqa">SQA</pwcdataset>
      <pwcdataset url="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/tabfact">TabFact</pwcdataset>
    </paper>
    <paper id="52">
      <title><fixed-case>BOUN</fixed-case> at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 9: Text Augmentation Techniques for Fact Verification in Tabular Data</title>
      <author><first>Abdullatif</first><last>Köksal</last></author>
      <author><first>Yusuf</first><last>Yüksel</last></author>
      <author><first>Bekir</first><last>Yıldırım</last></author>
      <author><first>Arzucan</first><last>Özgür</last></author>
      <pages>431–437</pages>
      <abstract>In this paper, we present our text augmentation based approach for the Table Statement Support Subtask (Phase A) of SemEval-2021 Task 9. We experiment with different text augmentation techniques such as back translation and synonym swapping using Word2Vec and WordNet. We show that text augmentation techniques lead to 2.5% improvement in F1 on the test set. Further, we investigate the impact of domain adaptation and joint learning on fact verification in tabular data by utilizing the SemTabFacts and TabFact datasets. We observe that joint learning improves the F1 scores on the SemTabFacts and TabFact test sets by 3.31% and 0.77%, respectively.</abstract>
      <url hash="a1b607d1">2021.semeval-1.52</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.52</doi>
      <bibkey>koksal-etal-2021-boun</bibkey>
      <pwcdataset url="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/glue">GLUE</pwcdataset>
      <pwcdataset url="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/tabfact">TabFact</pwcdataset>
    </paper>
    <paper id="53">
      <title><fixed-case>IITK</fixed-case> at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 10: Source-Free Unsupervised Domain Adaptation using Class Prototypes</title>
      <author id="harshit-kumar-iit"><first>Harshit</first><last>Kumar</last></author>
      <author><first>Jinang</first><last>Shah</last></author>
      <author><first>Nidhi</first><last>Hegde</last></author>
      <author><first>Priyanshu</first><last>Gupta</last></author>
      <author><first>Vaibhav</first><last>Jindal</last></author>
      <author><first>Ashutosh</first><last>Modi</last></author>
      <pages>438–444</pages>
      <abstract>Recent progress in deep learning has primarily been fueled by the availability of large amounts of annotated data that is obtained from highly expensive manual annotating pro-cesses. To tackle this issue of availability of annotated data, a lot of research has been done on unsupervised domain adaptation that tries to generate systems for an unlabelled target domain data, given labeled source domain data. However, the availability of annotated or labelled source domain dataset can’t always be guaranteed because of data-privacy issues. This is especially the case with medical data, as it may contain sensitive information of the patients. Source-free domain adaptation (SFDA) aims to resolve this issue by us-ing models trained on the source data instead of using the original annotated source data. In this work, we try to build SFDA systems for semantic processing by specifically focusing on the negation detection subtask of the SemEval2021 Task 10. We propose two approaches -ProtoAUGandAdapt-ProtoAUGthat use the idea of self-entropy to choose reliable and high confidence samples, which are then used for data augmentation and subsequent training of the models. Our methods report an improvement of up to 7% in F1 score over the baseline for the Negation Detection subtask.</abstract>
      <url hash="55a7d74a">2021.semeval-1.53</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.53</doi>
      <bibkey>kumar-etal-2021-iitk</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="54">
      <title><fixed-case>PTST</fixed-case>-<fixed-case>U</fixed-case>o<fixed-case>M</fixed-case> at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 10: Parsimonious Transfer for Sequence Tagging</title>
      <author><first>Kemal</first><last>Kurniawan</last></author>
      <author><first>Lea</first><last>Frermann</last></author>
      <author><first>Philip</first><last>Schulz</last></author>
      <author><first>Trevor</first><last>Cohn</last></author>
      <pages>445–451</pages>
      <abstract>This paper describes PTST, a source-free unsupervised domain adaptation technique for sequence tagging, and its application to the SemEval-2021 Task 10 on time expression recognition. PTST is an extension of the cross-lingual parsimonious parser transfer framework, which uses high-probability predictions of the source model as a supervision signal in self-training. We extend the framework to a sequence prediction setting, and demonstrate its applicability to unsupervised domain adaptation. PTST achieves F1 score of 79.6% on the official test set, with the precision of 90.1%, the highest out of 14 submissions.</abstract>
      <url hash="915e1901">2021.semeval-1.54</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.54</doi>
      <bibkey>kurniawan-etal-2021-ptst</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="55">
      <title>Self-Adapter at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 10: Entropy-based Pseudo-Labeler for Source-free Domain Adaptation</title>
      <author><first>Sangwon</first><last>Yoon</last></author>
      <author><first>Yanghoon</first><last>Kim</last></author>
      <author><first>Kyomin</first><last>Jung</last></author>
      <pages>452–457</pages>
      <abstract>Source-free domain adaptation is an emerging line of work in deep learning research since it is closely related to the real-world environment. We study the domain adaption in the sequence labeling problem where the model trained on the source domain data is given. We propose two methods: Self-Adapter and Selective Classifier Training. Self-Adapter is a training method that uses sentence-level pseudo-labels filtered by the self-entropy threshold to provide supervision to the whole model. Selective Classifier Training uses token-level pseudo-labels and supervises only the classification layer of the model. The proposed methods are evaluated on data provided by SemEval-2021 task 10 and Self-Adapter achieves 2nd rank performance.</abstract>
      <url hash="88ffffc2">2021.semeval-1.55</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.55</doi>
      <bibkey>yoon-etal-2021-self</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="56">
      <title>The <fixed-case>U</fixed-case>niversity of <fixed-case>A</fixed-case>rizona at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 10: Applying Self-training, Active Learning and Data Augmentation to Source-free Domain Adaptation</title>
      <author><first>Xin</first><last>Su</last></author>
      <author><first>Yiyun</first><last>Zhao</last></author>
      <author><first>Steven</first><last>Bethard</last></author>
      <pages>458–466</pages>
      <abstract>This paper describes our systems for negation detection and time expression recognition in SemEval 2021 Task 10, Source-Free Domain Adaptation for Semantic Processing. We show that self-training, active learning and data augmentation techniques can improve the generalization ability of the model on the unlabeled target domain data without accessing source domain data. We also perform detailed ablation studies and error analyses for our time expression recognition systems to identify the source of the performance improvement and give constructive feedback on the temporal normalization annotation guidelines.</abstract>
      <url hash="9f8b87dd">2021.semeval-1.56</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.56</doi>
      <bibkey>su-etal-2021-university</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="57">
      <title><fixed-case>K</fixed-case>now<fixed-case>G</fixed-case>raph@<fixed-case>IITK</fixed-case> at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 11: Building Knowledge Graph for <fixed-case>NLP</fixed-case> Research</title>
      <author><first>Shashank</first><last>Shailabh</last></author>
      <author><first>Sajal</first><last>Chaurasia</last></author>
      <author><first>Ashutosh</first><last>Modi</last></author>
      <pages>467–477</pages>
      <abstract>Research in Natural Language Processing is making rapid advances, resulting in the publication of a large number of research papers. Finding relevant research papers and their contribution to the domain is a challenging problem. In this paper, we address this challenge via the SemEval 2021 Task 11: NLPContributionGraph, by developing a system for a research paper contributions-focused knowledge graph over Natural Language Processing literature. The task is divided into three sub-tasks: extracting contribution sentences that show important contributions in the research article, extracting phrases from the contribution sentences, and predicting the information units in the research article together with triplet formation from the phrases. The proposed system is agnostic to the subject domain and can be applied for building a knowledge graph for any area. We found that transformer-based language models can significantly improve existing techniques and utilized the SciBERT-based model. Our first sub-task uses Bidirectional LSTM (BiLSTM) stacked on top of SciBERT model layers, while the second sub-task uses Conditional Random Field (CRF) on top of SciBERT with BiLSTM. The third sub-task uses a combined SciBERT based neural approach with heuristics for information unit prediction and triplet formation from the phrases. Our system achieved F1 score of 0.38, 0.63 and 0.76 in end-to-end pipeline testing, phrase extraction testing and triplet extraction testing respectively.</abstract>
      <url hash="0ff0323b">2021.semeval-1.57</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.57</doi>
      <bibkey>shailabh-etal-2021-knowgraph</bibkey>
      <pwcdataset url="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/semeval-2021-task-11-nlpcontributiongraph">SemEval-2021 Task-11</pwcdataset>
    </paper>
    <paper id="58">
      <title><fixed-case>YNU</fixed-case>-<fixed-case>HPCC</fixed-case> at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 11: Using a <fixed-case>BERT</fixed-case> Model to Extract Contributions from <fixed-case>NLP</fixed-case> Scholarly Articles</title>
      <author><first>Xinge</first><last>Ma</last></author>
      <author><first>Jin</first><last>Wang</last></author>
      <author><first>Xuejie</first><last>Zhang</last></author>
      <pages>478–484</pages>
      <abstract>This paper describes the system we built as the YNU-HPCC team in the SemEval-2021 Task 11: NLPContributionGraph. This task involves first identifying sentences in the given natural language processing (NLP) scholarly articles that reflect research contributions through binary classification; then identifying the core scientific terms and their relation phrases from these contribution sentences by sequence labeling; and finally, these scientific terms and relation phrases are categorized, identified, and organized into subject-predicate-object triples to form a knowledge graph with the help of multiclass classification and multi-label classification. We developed a system for this task using a pre-trained language representation model called BERT that stands for Bidirectional Encoder Representations from Transformers, and achieved good results. The average F1-score for Evaluation Phase 2, Part 1 was 0.4562 and ranked 7th, and the average F1-score for Evaluation Phase 2, Part 2 was 0.6541, and also ranked 7th.</abstract>
      <url hash="066f21ba">2021.semeval-1.58</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.58</doi>
      <bibkey>ma-etal-2021-ynu</bibkey>
      <pwcdataset url="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/semeval-2021-task-11-nlpcontributiongraph">SemEval-2021 Task-11</pwcdataset>
    </paper>
    <paper id="59">
      <title><fixed-case>ITNLP</fixed-case> at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 11: Boosting <fixed-case>BERT</fixed-case> with Sampling and Adversarial Training for Knowledge Extraction</title>
      <author><first>Genyu</first><last>Zhang</last></author>
      <author><first>Yu</first><last>Su</last></author>
      <author><first>Changhong</first><last>He</last></author>
      <author><first>Lei</first><last>Lin</last></author>
      <author><first>Chengjie</first><last>Sun</last></author>
      <author><first>Lili</first><last>Shan</last></author>
      <pages>485–489</pages>
      <abstract>This paper describes the winning system in the End-to-end Pipeline phase for the NLPContributionGraph task. The system is composed of three BERT-based models and the three models are used to extract sentences, entities and triples respectively. Experiments show that sampling and adversarial training can greatly boost the system. In End-to-end Pipeline phase, our system got an average F1 of 0.4703, significantly higher than the second-placed system which got an average F1 of 0.3828.</abstract>
      <url hash="c9400786">2021.semeval-1.59</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.59</doi>
      <bibkey>zhang-etal-2021-itnlp</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="60">
      <title><fixed-case>D</fixed-case>uluth at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 11: Applying <fixed-case>D</fixed-case>e<fixed-case>BERT</fixed-case>a to Contributing Sentence Selection and Dependency Parsing for Entity Extraction</title>
      <author><first>Anna</first><last>Martin</last></author>
      <author><first>Ted</first><last>Pedersen</last></author>
      <pages>490–501</pages>
      <abstract>This paper describes the Duluth system that participated in SemEval-2021 Task 11, NLP Contribution Graph. It details the extraction of contribution sentences and scientific entities and their relations from scholarly articles in the domain of Natural Language Processing. Our solution uses deBERTa for multi-class sentence classification to extract the contributing sentences and their type, and dependency parsing to outline each sentence and extract subject-predicate-object triples. Our system ranked fifth of seven for Phase 1: end-to-end pipeline, sixth of eight for Phase 2 Part 1: phrases and triples, and fifth of eight for Phase 2 Part 2: triples extraction.</abstract>
      <url hash="4963cbad">2021.semeval-1.60</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.60</doi>
      <bibkey>martin-pedersen-2021-duluth</bibkey>
      <pwcdataset url="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/semeval2017">SemEval-2017 Task-10</pwcdataset>
      <pwcdataset url="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/semeval-2021-task-11-nlpcontributiongraph">SemEval-2021 Task-11</pwcdataset>
    </paper>
    <paper id="61">
      <title><fixed-case>INNOVATORS</fixed-case> at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task-11: A Dependency Parsing and <fixed-case>BERT</fixed-case>-based model for Extracting Contribution Knowledge from Scientific Papers</title>
      <author><first>Hardik</first><last>Arora</last></author>
      <author><first>Tirthankar</first><last>Ghosal</last></author>
      <author><first>Sandeep</first><last>Kumar</last></author>
      <author><first>Suraj</first><last>Patwal</last></author>
      <author><first>Phil</first><last>Gooch</last></author>
      <pages>502–510</pages>
      <abstract>In this work, we describe our system submission to the SemEval 2021 Task 11: NLP Contribution Graph Challenge. We attempt all the three sub-tasks in the challenge and report our results. Subtask 1 aims to identify the contributing sentences in a given publication. Subtask 2 follows from Subtask 1 to extract the scientific term and predicate phrases from the identified contributing sentences. The final Subtask 3 entails extracting <i>triples</i> (subject, predicate, object) from the phrases and categorizing them under one or more defined information units. With the NLPContributionGraph Shared Task, the organizers formalized the building of a scholarly contributions-focused graph over NLP scholarly articles as an automated task. Our approaches include a BERT-based classification model for identifying the contributing sentences in a research publication, a rule-based dependency parsing for phrase extraction, followed by a CNN-based model for information units classification, and a set of rules for triples extraction. The quantitative results show that we obtain the 5th, 5th, and 7th rank respectively in three evaluation phases. We make our codes available at <url>https://github.com/HardikArora17/SemEval-2021-INNOVATORS</url>.</abstract>
      <url hash="7d66a138">2021.semeval-1.61</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.61</doi>
      <bibkey>arora-etal-2021-innovators</bibkey>
      <pwcdataset url="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/semeval-2021-task-11-nlpcontributiongraph">SemEval-2021 Task-11</pwcdataset>
    </paper>
    <paper id="62">
      <title><fixed-case>MCL</fixed-case>@<fixed-case>IITK</fixed-case> at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 2: Multilingual and Cross-lingual Word-in-Context Disambiguation using Augmented Data, Signals, and Transformers</title>
      <author><first>Rohan</first><last>Gupta</last></author>
      <author><first>Jay</first><last>Mundra</last></author>
      <author><first>Deepak</first><last>Mahajan</last></author>
      <author><first>Ashutosh</first><last>Modi</last></author>
      <pages>511–520</pages>
      <abstract>In this work, we present our approach for solving the SemEval 2021 Task 2: Multilingual and Cross-lingual Word-in-Context Disambiguation (MCL-WiC). The task is a sentence pair classification problem where the goal is to detect whether a given word common to both the sentences evokes the same meaning. We submit systems for both the settings - Multilingual (the pair’s sentences belong to the same language) and Cross-Lingual (the pair’s sentences belong to different languages). The training data is provided only in English. Consequently, we employ cross-lingual transfer techniques. Our approach employs fine-tuning pre-trained transformer-based language models, like ELECTRA and ALBERT, for the English task and XLM-R for all other tasks. To improve these systems’ performance, we propose adding a signal to the word to be disambiguated and augmenting our data by sentence pair reversal. We further augment the dataset provided to us with WiC, XL-WiC and SemCor 3.0. Using ensembles, we achieve strong performance in the Multilingual task, placing first in the EN-EN and FR-FR sub-tasks. For the Cross-Lingual setting, we employed translate-test methods and a zero-shot method, using our multilingual models, with the latter performing slightly better.</abstract>
      <url hash="8d73d9b7">2021.semeval-1.62</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.62</doi>
      <bibkey>gupta-etal-2021-mcl</bibkey>
      <pwcdataset url="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/wic">WiC</pwcdataset>
      <pwcdataset url="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/word-sense-disambiguation-a-unified">Word Sense Disambiguation: a Unified Evaluation Framework and Empirical Comparison</pwcdataset>
      <pwcdataset url="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/xl-wic">XL-WiC</pwcdataset>
    </paper>
    <paper id="63">
      <title><fixed-case>HITSZ</fixed-case>-<fixed-case>HLT</fixed-case> at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 5: Ensemble Sequence Labeling and Span Boundary Detection for Toxic Span Detection</title>
      <author><first>Qinglin</first><last>Zhu</last></author>
      <author><first>Zijie</first><last>Lin</last></author>
      <author><first>Yice</first><last>Zhang</last></author>
      <author><first>Jingyi</first><last>Sun</last></author>
      <author><first>Xiang</first><last>Li</last></author>
      <author><first>Qihui</first><last>Lin</last></author>
      <author><first>Yixue</first><last>Dang</last></author>
      <author><first>Ruifeng</first><last>Xu</last></author>
      <pages>521–526</pages>
      <abstract>This paper presents the winning system that participated in SemEval-2021 Task 5: Toxic Spans Detection. This task aims to locate those spans that attribute to the text’s toxicity within a text, which is crucial for semi-automated moderation in online discussions. We formalize this task as the Sequence Labeling (SL) problem and the Span Boundary Detection (SBD) problem separately and employ three state-of-the-art models. Next, we integrate predictions of these models to produce a more credible and complement result. Our system achieves a char-level score of 70.83%, ranking 1/91. In addition, we also explore the lexicon-based method, which is strongly interpretable and flexible in practice.</abstract>
      <url hash="55d83b70">2021.semeval-1.63</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.63</doi>
      <bibkey>zhu-etal-2021-hitsz</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="64">
      <title><fixed-case>S</fixed-case>arcasm<fixed-case>D</fixed-case>et at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 7: Detect Humor and Offensive based on Demographic Factors using <fixed-case>R</fixed-case>o<fixed-case>BERT</fixed-case>a Pre-trained Model</title>
      <author><first>Dalya</first><last>Faraj</last></author>
      <author><first>Malak</first><last>Abdullah</last></author>
      <pages>527–533</pages>
      <abstract>This paper presents one of the top winning solution systems for task 7 at SemEval2021, HaHackathon: Detecting and Rating Humor and Offense. This competition is divided into two tasks, task1 with three sub-tasks 1a,1b, and 1c, and task2. The goal for task1 is to predict if the text would be considered humorous or not, and if it is yes, then predict how humorous it is and whether the humor rating would be perceived as controversial. The goal of the task2 is to predict how the text is considered offensive for users in general. Our solution has been developed using RoBERTa pre-trained model with ensemble techniques. The paper describes the submitted solution system’s architecture with the experiments and the hyperparameter tuning that led to this robust system. Our model ranked third and fourth places out of 50 teams in tasks 1c and 1a with F1-Score of 0.6270 and 0.9675, respectively. At the same time, the model ranked one of the top 10 models in task 1b and task 2 with an RMSE scores of 0.5446 and 0.4469, respectively.</abstract>
      <url hash="dafb47fc">2021.semeval-1.64</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.64</doi>
      <bibkey>faraj-abdullah-2021-sarcasmdet</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="65">
      <title><fixed-case>UPB</fixed-case> at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 8: Extracting Semantic Information on Measurements as Multi-Turn Question Answering</title>
      <author><first>Andrei-Marius</first><last>Avram</last></author>
      <author><first>George-Eduard</first><last>Zaharia</last></author>
      <author><first>Dumitru-Clementin</first><last>Cercel</last></author>
      <author><first>Mihai</first><last>Dascalu</last></author>
      <pages>534–540</pages>
      <abstract>Extracting semantic information on measurements and counts is an important topic in terms of analyzing scientific discourses. The 8th task of SemEval-2021: Counts and Measurements (MeasEval) aimed to boost research in this direction by providing a new dataset on which participants train their models to extract meaningful information on measurements from scientific texts. The competition is composed of five subtasks that build on top of each other: (1) quantity span identification, (2) unit extraction from the identified quantities and their value modifier classification, (3) span identification for measured entities and measured properties, (4) qualifier span identification, and (5) relation extraction between the identified quantities, measured entities, measured properties, and qualifiers. We approached these challenges by first identifying the quantities, extracting their units of measurement, classifying them with corresponding modifiers, and afterwards using them to jointly solve the last three subtasks in a multi-turn question answering manner. Our best performing model obtained an overlapping F1-score of 36.91% on the test set.</abstract>
      <url hash="a4fc652d">2021.semeval-1.65</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.65</doi>
      <bibkey>avram-etal-2021-upb</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="66">
      <title><fixed-case>IITK</fixed-case>@<fixed-case>LCP</fixed-case> at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 1: Classification for Lexical Complexity Regression Task</title>
      <author><first>Neil</first><last>Shirude</last></author>
      <author><first>Sagnik</first><last>Mukherjee</last></author>
      <author><first>Tushar</first><last>Shandhilya</last></author>
      <author><first>Ananta</first><last>Mukherjee</last></author>
      <author><first>Ashutosh</first><last>Modi</last></author>
      <pages>541–547</pages>
      <abstract>This paper describes our contribution to SemEval 2021 Task 1 (Shardlow et al., 2021): Lexical Complexity Prediction. In our approach, we leverage the ELECTRA model and attempt to mirror the data annotation scheme. Although the task is a regression task, we show that we can treat it as an aggregation of several classification and regression models. This somewhat counter-intuitive approach achieved an MAE score of 0.0654 for Sub-Task 1 and MAE of 0.0811 on Sub-Task 2. Additionally, we used the concept of weak supervision signals from Gloss-BERT in our work, and it significantly improved the MAE score in Sub-Task 1.</abstract>
      <url hash="9b430f68">2021.semeval-1.66</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.66</doi>
      <bibkey>shirude-etal-2021-iitk</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="67">
      <title><fixed-case>LCP</fixed-case>-<fixed-case>RIT</fixed-case> at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 1: Exploring Linguistic Features for Lexical Complexity Prediction</title>
      <author><first>Abhinandan Tejalkumar</first><last>Desai</last></author>
      <author><first>Kai</first><last>North</last></author>
      <author><first>Marcos</first><last>Zampieri</last></author>
      <author><first>Christopher</first><last>Homan</last></author>
      <pages>548–553</pages>
      <abstract>This paper describes team LCP-RIT’s submission to the SemEval-2021 Task 1: Lexical Complexity Prediction (LCP). The task organizers provided participants with an augmented version of CompLex (Shardlow et al., 2020), an English multi-domain dataset in which words in context were annotated with respect to their complexity using a five point Likert scale. Our system uses logistic regression and a wide range of linguistic features (e.g. psycholinguistic features, n-grams, word frequency, POS tags) to predict the complexity of single words in this dataset. We analyze the impact of different linguistic features on the classification performance and we evaluate the results in terms of mean absolute error, mean squared error, Pearson correlation, and Spearman correlation.</abstract>
      <url hash="23186590">2021.semeval-1.67</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.67</doi>
      <bibkey>desai-etal-2021-lcp</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="68">
      <title>Alejandro Mosquera at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 1: Exploring Sentence and Word Features for Lexical Complexity Prediction</title>
      <author><first>Alejandro</first><last>Mosquera</last></author>
      <pages>554–559</pages>
      <abstract>This paper revisits feature engineering approaches for predicting the complexity level of English words in a particular context using regression techniques. Our best submission to the Lexical Complexity Prediction (LCP) shared task was ranked 3rd out of 48 systems for sub-task 1 and achieved Pearson correlation coefficients of 0.779 and 0.809 for single words and multi-word expressions respectively. The conclusion is that a combination of lexical, contextual and semantic features can still produce strong baselines when compared against human judgement.</abstract>
      <url hash="70c30c10">2021.semeval-1.68</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.68</doi>
      <bibkey>mosquera-2021-alejandro</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="69">
      <title><fixed-case>C</fixed-case>omp<fixed-case>NA</fixed-case> at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 1: Prediction of lexical complexity analyzing heterogeneous features</title>
      <author><first>Giuseppe</first><last>Vettigli</last></author>
      <author><first>Antonio</first><last>Sorgente</last></author>
      <pages>560–564</pages>
      <abstract>This paper describes the CompNa model that has been submitted to the Lexical Complexity Prediction (LCP) shared task hosted at SemEval 2021 (Task 1). The solution is based on combining features of different nature through an ensambling method based on Decision Trees and trained using Gradient Boosting. We discuss the results of the model and highlight the features with more predictive capabilities.</abstract>
      <url hash="17f6d7f7">2021.semeval-1.69</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.69</doi>
      <bibkey>vettigli-sorgente-2021-compna</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="70">
      <title><fixed-case>P</fixed-case>oly<fixed-case>U</fixed-case> <fixed-case>CBS</fixed-case>-Comp at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 1: Lexical Complexity Prediction (<fixed-case>LCP</fixed-case>)</title>
      <author><first>Rong</first><last>Xiang</last></author>
      <author><first>Jinghang</first><last>Gu</last></author>
      <author><first>Emmanuele</first><last>Chersoni</last></author>
      <author><first>Wenjie</first><last>Li</last></author>
      <author><first>Qin</first><last>Lu</last></author>
      <author><first>Chu-Ren</first><last>Huang</last></author>
      <pages>565–570</pages>
      <abstract>In this contribution, we describe the system presented by the PolyU CBS-Comp Team at the Task 1 of SemEval 2021, where the goal was the estimation of the complexity of words in a given sentence context. Our top system, based on a combination of lexical, syntactic, word embeddings and Transformers-derived features and on a Gradient Boosting Regressor, achieves a top correlation score of 0.754 on the subtask 1 for single words and 0.659 on the subtask 2 for multiword expressions.</abstract>
      <url hash="b185a0b5">2021.semeval-1.70</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.70</doi>
      <bibkey>xiang-etal-2021-polyu</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="71">
      <title><fixed-case>LAST</fixed-case> at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 1: Improving Multi-Word Complexity Prediction Using Bigram Association Measures</title>
      <author><first>Yves</first><last>Bestgen</last></author>
      <pages>571–577</pages>
      <abstract>This paper describes the system developed by the Laboratoire d’analyse statistique des textes (LAST) for the Lexical Complexity Prediction shared task at SemEval-2021. The proposed system is made up of a LightGBM model fed with features obtained from many word frequency lists, published lexical norms and psychometric data. For tackling the specificity of the multi-word task, it uses bigram association measures. Despite that the only contextual feature used was sentence length, the system achieved an honorable performance in the multi-word task, but poorer in the single word task. The bigram association measures were found useful, but to a limited extent.</abstract>
      <url hash="e5817044">2021.semeval-1.71</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.71</doi>
      <bibkey>bestgen-2021-last-semeval</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="72">
      <title><fixed-case>D</fixed-case>eep<fixed-case>B</fixed-case>lue<fixed-case>AI</fixed-case> at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 1: Lexical Complexity Prediction with A Deep Ensemble Approach</title>
      <author><first>Chunguang</first><last>Pan</last></author>
      <author><first>Bingyan</first><last>Song</last></author>
      <author><first>Shengguang</first><last>Wang</last></author>
      <author><first>Zhipeng</first><last>Luo</last></author>
      <pages>578–584</pages>
      <abstract>Lexical complexity plays an important role in reading comprehension. lexical complexity prediction (LCP) can not only be used as a part of Lexical Simplification systems, but also as a stand-alone application to help people better reading. This paper presents the winning system we submitted to the LCP Shared Task of SemEval 2021 that capable of dealing with both two subtasks. We first perform fine-tuning on numbers of pre-trained language models (PLMs) with various hyperparameters and different training strategies such as pseudo-labelling and data augmentation. Then an effective stacking mechanism is applied on top of the fine-tuned PLMs to obtain the final prediction. Experimental results on the Complex dataset show the validity of our method and we rank first and second for subtask 2 and 1.</abstract>
      <url hash="0abee90b">2021.semeval-1.72</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.72</doi>
      <bibkey>pan-etal-2021-deepblueai-semeval</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="73">
      <title><fixed-case>CS</fixed-case>-<fixed-case>UM</fixed-case>6<fixed-case>P</fixed-case> at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 1: A Deep Learning Model-based Pre-trained Transformer Encoder for Lexical Complexity</title>
      <author><first>Nabil</first><last>El Mamoun</last></author>
      <author><first>Abdelkader</first><last>El Mahdaouy</last></author>
      <author><first>Abdellah</first><last>El Mekki</last></author>
      <author><first>Kabil</first><last>Essefar</last></author>
      <author><first>Ismail</first><last>Berrada</last></author>
      <pages>585–589</pages>
      <abstract>Lexical Complexity Prediction (LCP) involves assigning a difficulty score to a particular word or expression, in a text intended for a target audience. In this paper, we introduce a new deep learning-based system for this challenging task. The proposed system consists of a deep learning model, based on pre-trained transformer encoder, for word and Multi-Word Expression (MWE) complexity prediction. First, on top of the encoder’s contextualized word embedding, our model employs an attention layer on the input context and the complex word or MWE. Then, the attention output is concatenated with the pooled output of the encoder and passed to a regression module. We investigate both single-task and joint training on both Sub-Tasks data using multiple pre-trained transformer-based encoders. The obtained results are very promising and show the effectiveness of fine-tuning pre-trained transformers for LCP task.</abstract>
      <url hash="a0998ad5">2021.semeval-1.73</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.73</doi>
      <bibkey>el-mamoun-etal-2021-cs</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="74">
      <title><fixed-case>C</fixed-case>ambridge at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 1: An Ensemble of Feature-Based and Neural Models for Lexical Complexity Prediction</title>
      <author><first>Zheng</first><last>Yuan</last></author>
      <author><first>Gladys</first><last>Tyen</last></author>
      <author><first>David</first><last>Strohmaier</last></author>
      <pages>590–597</pages>
      <abstract>This paper describes our submission to the SemEval-2021 shared task on Lexical Complexity Prediction. We approached it as a regression problem and present an ensemble combining four systems, one feature-based and three neural with fine-tuning, frequency pre-training and multi-task learning, achieving Pearson scores of 0.8264 and 0.7556 on the trial and test sets respectively (sub-task 1). We further present our analysis of the results and discuss our findings.</abstract>
      <url hash="cfbd2425">2021.semeval-1.74</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.74</doi>
      <bibkey>yuan-etal-2021-cambridge</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="75">
      <title>hub at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 1: Fusion of Sentence and Word Frequency to Predict Lexical Complexity</title>
      <author><first>Bo</first><last>Huang</last></author>
      <author><first>Yang</first><last>Bai</last></author>
      <author><first>Xiaobing</first><last>Zhou</last></author>
      <pages>598–602</pages>
      <abstract>In this paper, we propose a method of fusing sentence information and word frequency information for the SemEval 2021 Task 1-Lexical Complexity Prediction (LCP) shared task. In our system, the sentence information comes from the RoBERTa model, and the word frequency information comes from the Tf-Idf algorithm. Use Inception block as a shared layer to learn sentence and word frequency information We described the implementation of our best system and discussed our methods and experiments in the task. The shared task is divided into two sub-tasks. The goal of the two sub-tasks is to predict the complexity of a predetermined word. The shared task is divided into two subtasks. The goal of the two subtasks is to predict the complexity of a predetermined word. The evaluation index of the task is the Pearson correlation coefficient. Our best performance system has Pearson correlation coefficients of 0.7434 and 0.8000 in the single-token subtask test set and the multi-token subtask test set, respectively.</abstract>
      <url hash="bdad0cf2">2021.semeval-1.75</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.75</doi>
      <bibkey>huang-etal-2021-hub</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="76">
      <title><fixed-case>M</fixed-case>anchester Metropolitan at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 1: Convolutional Networks for Complex Word Identification</title>
      <author><first>Robert</first><last>Flynn</last></author>
      <author><first>Matthew</first><last>Shardlow</last></author>
      <pages>603–608</pages>
      <abstract>We present two convolutional neural networks for predicting the complexity of words and phrases in context on a continuous scale. Both models utilize word and character embeddings alongside lexical features as inputs. Our system displays reasonable results with a Pearson correlation of 0.7754 on the task as a whole. We highlight the limitations of this method in properly assessing the context of the target text, and explore the effectiveness of both systems across a range of genres. Both models were submitted as part of LCP 2021, which focuses on the identification of complex words and phrases as a context dependent, regression based task.</abstract>
      <url hash="6040f3f4">2021.semeval-1.76</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.76</doi>
      <bibkey>flynn-shardlow-2021-manchester</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="77">
      <title><fixed-case>UPB</fixed-case> at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 1: Combining Deep Learning and Hand-Crafted Features for Lexical Complexity Prediction</title>
      <author><first>George-Eduard</first><last>Zaharia</last></author>
      <author><first>Dumitru-Clementin</first><last>Cercel</last></author>
      <author><first>Mihai</first><last>Dascalu</last></author>
      <pages>609–616</pages>
      <abstract>Reading is a complex process which requires proper understanding of texts in order to create coherent mental representations. However, comprehension problems may arise due to hard-to-understand sections, which can prove troublesome for readers, while accounting for their specific language skills. As such, steps towards simplifying these sections can be performed, by accurately identifying and evaluating difficult structures. In this paper, we describe our approach for the SemEval-2021 Task 1: Lexical Complexity Prediction competition that consists of a mixture of advanced NLP techniques, namely Transformer-based language models, pre-trained word embeddings, Graph Convolutional Networks, Capsule Networks, as well as a series of hand-crafted textual complexity features. Our models are applicable on both subtasks and achieve good performance results, with a MAE below 0.07 and a Person correlation of .73 for single word identification, as well as a MAE below 0.08 and a Person correlation of .79 for multiple word targets. Our results are just 5.46% and 6.5% lower than the top scores obtained in the competition on the first and the second subtasks, respectively.</abstract>
      <url hash="f6d28b3b">2021.semeval-1.77</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.77</doi>
      <bibkey>zaharia-etal-2021-upb</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="78">
      <title><fixed-case>UTFPR</fixed-case> at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 1: Complexity Prediction by Combining <fixed-case>BERT</fixed-case> Vectors and Classic Features</title>
      <author><first>Gustavo Henrique</first><last>Paetzold</last></author>
      <pages>617–622</pages>
      <abstract>We describe the UTFPR systems submitted to the Lexical Complexity Prediction shared task of SemEval 2021. They perform complexity prediction by combining classic features, such as word frequency, n-gram frequency, word length, and number of senses, with BERT vectors. We test numerous feature combinations and machine learning models in our experiments and find that BERT vectors, even if not optimized for the task at hand, are a great complement to classic features. We also find that employing the principle of compositionality can potentially help in phrase complexity prediction. Our systems place 45th out of 55 for single words and 29th out of 38 for phrases.</abstract>
      <url hash="eb9f40a7">2021.semeval-1.78</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.78</doi>
      <bibkey>paetzold-2021-utfpr</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="79">
      <title><fixed-case>RG</fixed-case> <fixed-case>PA</fixed-case> at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 1: A Contextual Attention-based Model with <fixed-case>R</fixed-case>o<fixed-case>BERT</fixed-case>a for Lexical Complexity Prediction</title>
      <author><first>Gang</first><last>Rao</last></author>
      <author><first>Maochang</first><last>Li</last></author>
      <author><first>Xiaolong</first><last>Hou</last></author>
      <author><first>Lianxin</first><last>Jiang</last></author>
      <author><first>Yang</first><last>Mo</last></author>
      <author><first>Jianping</first><last>Shen</last></author>
      <pages>623–626</pages>
      <abstract>In this paper we propose a contextual attention based model with two-stage fine-tune training using RoBERTa. First, we perform the first-stage fine-tune on corpus with RoBERTa, so that the model can learn some prior domain knowledge. Then we get the contextual embedding of context words based on the token-level embedding with the fine-tuned model. And we use Kfold cross-validation to get K models and ensemble them to get the final result. Finally, we attain the 2nd place in the final evaluation phase of sub-task 2 with pearson correlation of 0.8575.</abstract>
      <url hash="4b389693">2021.semeval-1.79</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.79</doi>
      <bibkey>rao-etal-2021-rg</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="80">
      <title><fixed-case>CSECU</fixed-case>-<fixed-case>DSG</fixed-case> at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 1: Fusion of Transformer Models for Lexical Complexity Prediction</title>
      <author><first>Abdul</first><last>Aziz</last></author>
      <author><first>MD. Akram</first><last>Hossain</last></author>
      <author><first>Abu Nowshed</first><last>Chy</last></author>
      <pages>627–631</pages>
      <abstract>Lexical complexity prediction (LCP) conveys the anticipation of the complexity level of a token or a set of tokens in a sentence. It plays a vital role in the improvement of various NLP tasks including lexical simplification, translations, and text generation. However, multiple meaning of a word in multiple circumstances, grammatical complex structure, and the mutual dependency of words in a sentence make it difficult to estimate the lexical complexity. To address these challenges, SemEval-2021 Task 1 introduced a shared task focusing on LCP and this paper presents our participation in this task. We proposed a transformer-based approach with sentence pair regression. We employed two fine-tuned transformer models. Including BERT and RoBERTa to train our model and fuse their predicted score to the complexity estimation. Experimental results demonstrate that our proposed method achieved competitive performance compared to the participants’ systems.</abstract>
      <url hash="40e97d83">2021.semeval-1.80</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.80</doi>
      <bibkey>aziz-etal-2021-csecu</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="81">
      <title><fixed-case>CLULEX</fixed-case> at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 1: A Simple System Goes a Long Way</title>
      <author><first>Greta</first><last>Smolenska</last></author>
      <author><first>Peter</first><last>Kolb</last></author>
      <author><first>Sinan</first><last>Tang</last></author>
      <author><first>Mironas</first><last>Bitinis</last></author>
      <author><first>Héctor</first><last>Hernández</last></author>
      <author><first>Elin</first><last>Asklöv</last></author>
      <pages>632–639</pages>
      <abstract>This paper presents the system we submitted to the first Lexical Complexity Prediction (LCP) Shared Task 2021. The Shared Task provides participants with a new English dataset that includes context of the target word. We participate in the single-word complexity prediction sub-task and focus on feature engineering. Our best system is trained on linguistic features and word embeddings (Pearson’s score of 0.7942). We demonstrate, however, that a simpler feature set achieves comparable results and submit a model trained on 36 linguistic features (Pearson’s score of 0.7925).</abstract>
      <url hash="15a0b21e">2021.semeval-1.81</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.81</doi>
      <bibkey>smolenska-etal-2021-clulex</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="82">
      <title><fixed-case>RS</fixed-case>_<fixed-case>GV</fixed-case> at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 1: Sense Relative Lexical Complexity Prediction</title>
      <author><first>Regina</first><last>Stodden</last></author>
      <author><first>Gayatri</first><last>Venugopal</last></author>
      <pages>640–649</pages>
      <abstract>We present the technical report of the system called RS_GV at SemEval-2021 Task 1 on lexical complexity prediction of English words. RS_GV is a neural network using hand-crafted linguistic features in combination with character and word embeddings to predict target words’ complexity. For the generation of the hand-crafted features, we set the target words in relation to their senses. RS_GV predicts the complexity well of biomedical terms but it has problems with the complexity prediction of very complex and very simple target words.</abstract>
      <url hash="ae9fb5c7">2021.semeval-1.82</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.82</doi>
      <bibkey>stodden-venugopal-2021-rs</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="83">
      <title><fixed-case>UNBNLP</fixed-case> at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 1: Predicting lexical complexity with masked language models and character-level encoders</title>
      <author><first>Milton</first><last>King</last></author>
      <author><first>Ali</first><last>Hakimi Parizi</last></author>
      <author><first>Samin</first><last>Fakharian</last></author>
      <author><first>Paul</first><last>Cook</last></author>
      <pages>650–654</pages>
      <abstract>In this paper, we present three supervised systems for English lexical complexity prediction of single and multiword expressions for SemEval-2021 Task 1. We explore the use of statistical baseline features, masked language models, and character-level encoders to predict the complexity of a target token in context. Our best system combines information from these three sources. The results indicate that information from masked language models and character-level encoders can be combined to improve lexical complexity prediction.</abstract>
      <url hash="598f4b0c">2021.semeval-1.83</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.83</doi>
      <bibkey>king-etal-2021-unbnlp</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="84">
      <title><fixed-case>ANDI</fixed-case> at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 1: Predicting complexity in context using distributional models, behavioural norms, and lexical resources</title>
      <author><first>Armand</first><last>Rotaru</last></author>
      <pages>655–660</pages>
      <abstract>In this paper we describe our participation in the Lexical Complexity Prediction (LCP) shared task of SemEval 2021, which involved predicting subjective ratings of complexity for English single words and multi-word expressions, presented in context. Our approach relies on a combination of distributional models, both context-dependent and context-independent, together with behavioural norms and lexical resources.</abstract>
      <url hash="882348a8">2021.semeval-1.84</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.84</doi>
      <bibkey>rotaru-2021-andi</bibkey>
      <pwccode url="https://github.com/armandrotaru/teamandi-lcp" additional="false">armandrotaru/teamandi-lcp</pwccode>
      <pwcdataset url="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/conceptnet">ConceptNet</pwcdataset>
    </paper>
    <paper id="85">
      <title><fixed-case>JUST</fixed-case>-<fixed-case>BLUE</fixed-case> at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 1: Predicting Lexical Complexity using <fixed-case>BERT</fixed-case> and <fixed-case>R</fixed-case>o<fixed-case>BERT</fixed-case>a Pre-trained Language Models</title>
      <author><first>Tuqa</first><last>Bani Yaseen</last></author>
      <author><first>Qusai</first><last>Ismail</last></author>
      <author><first>Sarah</first><last>Al-Omari</last></author>
      <author><first>Eslam</first><last>Al-Sobh</last></author>
      <author><first>Malak</first><last>Abdullah</last></author>
      <pages>661–666</pages>
      <abstract>Predicting the complexity level of a word or a phrase is considered a challenging task. It is even recognized as a crucial step in numerous NLP applications, such as text rearrangements and text simplification. Early research treated the task as a binary classification task, where the systems anticipated the existence of a word’s complexity (complex versus uncomplicated). Other studies had been designed to assess the level of word complexity using regression models or multi-labeling classification models. Deep learning models show a significant improvement over machine learning models with the rise of transfer learning and pre-trained language models. This paper presents our approach that won the first rank in the SemEval-task1 (sub stask1). We have calculated the degree of word complexity from 0-1 within a text. We have been ranked first place in the competition using the pre-trained language models Bert and RoBERTa, with a Pearson correlation score of 0.788.</abstract>
      <url hash="566cc4e0">2021.semeval-1.85</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.85</doi>
      <bibkey>bani-yaseen-etal-2021-just</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="86">
      <title><fixed-case>B</fixed-case>ig<fixed-case>G</fixed-case>reen at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 1: Lexical Complexity Prediction with Assembly Models</title>
      <author><first>Aadil</first><last>Islam</last></author>
      <author><first>Weicheng</first><last>Ma</last></author>
      <author><first>Soroush</first><last>Vosoughi</last></author>
      <pages>667–677</pages>
      <abstract>This paper describes a system submitted by team BigGreen to LCP 2021 for predicting the lexical complexity of English words in a given context. We assemble a feature engineering-based model with a deep neural network model founded on BERT. While BERT itself performs competitively, our feature engineering-based model helps in extreme cases, eg. separating instances of easy and neutral difficulty. Our handcrafted features comprise a breadth of lexical, semantic, syntactic, and novel phonological measures. Visualizations of BERT attention maps offer insight into potential features that Transformers models may learn when fine-tuned for lexical complexity prediction. Our ensembled predictions score reasonably well for the single word subtask, and we demonstrate how they can be harnessed to perform well on the multi word expression subtask too.</abstract>
      <url hash="1c26f9e0">2021.semeval-1.86</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.86</doi>
      <bibkey>islam-etal-2021-biggreen</bibkey>
      <pwccode url="https://github.com/Aadil101/BigGreen-at-LCP-2021" additional="false">Aadil101/BigGreen-at-LCP-2021</pwccode>
    </paper>
    <paper id="87">
      <title>cs60075_team2 at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 1 : Lexical Complexity Prediction using Transformer-based Language Models pre-trained on various text corpora</title>
      <author><first>Abhilash</first><last>Nandy</last></author>
      <author><first>Sayantan</first><last>Adak</last></author>
      <author><first>Tanurima</first><last>Halder</last></author>
      <author><first>Sai Mahesh</first><last>Pokala</last></author>
      <pages>678–682</pages>
      <abstract>The main contribution of this paper is to fine-tune transformer-based language models pre-trained on several text corpora, some being general (E.g., Wikipedia, BooksCorpus), some being the corpora from which the CompLex Dataset was extracted, and others being from other specific domains such as Finance, Law, etc. We perform ablation studies on selecting the transformer models and how their individual complexity scores are aggregated to get the resulting complexity scores. Our method achieves a best Pearson Correlation of 0.784 in sub-task 1 (single word) and 0.836 in sub-task 2 (multiple word expressions).</abstract>
      <url hash="9b500b46">2021.semeval-1.87</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.87</doi>
      <bibkey>nandy-etal-2021-cs60075</bibkey>
      <pwccode url="https://github.com/abhi1nandy2/CS60075-Team-2-Task-1" additional="false">abhi1nandy2/CS60075-Team-2-Task-1</pwccode>
    </paper>
    <paper id="88">
      <title><fixed-case>C</fixed-case>3<fixed-case>SL</fixed-case> at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 1: Predicting Lexical Complexity of Words in Specific Contexts with Sentence Embeddings</title>
      <author><first>Raul</first><last>Almeida</last></author>
      <author><first>Hegler</first><last>Tissot</last></author>
      <author><first>Marcos Didonet Del</first><last>Fabro</last></author>
      <pages>683–687</pages>
      <abstract>We present our approach to predicting lexical complexity of words in specific contexts, as entered LCP Shared Task 1 at SemEval 2021. The approach consists of separating sentences into smaller chunks, embedding them with Sent2Vec, and reducing the embeddings into a simpler vector used as input to a neural network, the latter for predicting the complexity of words and expressions. Results show that the pre-trained sentence embeddings are not able to capture lexical complexity from the language when applied in cross-domain applications.</abstract>
      <url hash="45a85aa8">2021.semeval-1.88</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.88</doi>
      <bibkey>almeida-etal-2021-c3sl</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="89">
      <title><fixed-case>S</fixed-case>tanford <fixed-case>ML</fixed-case>ab at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 1: Tree-Based Modelling of Lexical Complexity using Word Embeddings</title>
      <author><first>Erik</first><last>Rozi</last></author>
      <author><first>Niveditha</first><last>Iyer</last></author>
      <author><first>Gordon</first><last>Chi</last></author>
      <author><first>Enok</first><last>Choe</last></author>
      <author><first>Kathy J.</first><last>Lee</last></author>
      <author><first>Kevin</first><last>Liu</last></author>
      <author><first>Patrick</first><last>Liu</last></author>
      <author><first>Zander</first><last>Lack</last></author>
      <author><first>Jillian</first><last>Tang</last></author>
      <author><first>Ethan A.</first><last>Chi</last></author>
      <pages>688–693</pages>
      <abstract>This paper presents our system for the single- and multi-word lexical complexity prediction tasks of SemEval Task 1: Lexical Complexity Prediction. Text comprehension depends on the reader’s ability to understand the words present in it; evaluating the lexical complexity of such texts can enable readers to find an appropriate text and systems to tailor a text to an audience’s needs. We present our model pipeline, which applies a combination of embedding-based and manual features to predict lexical complexity on the CompLex English dataset using various tree-based and linear models. Our method is ranked 27 / 54 on single-word prediction and 14 / 37 on multi-word prediction.</abstract>
      <url hash="c3cba112">2021.semeval-1.89</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.89</doi>
      <bibkey>rozi-etal-2021-stanford</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="90">
      <title>archer at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 1: Contextualising Lexical Complexity</title>
      <author><first>Irene</first><last>Russo</last></author>
      <pages>694–699</pages>
      <abstract>Evaluating the complexity of a target word in a sentential context is the aim of the Lexical Complexity Prediction task at SemEval-2021. This paper presents the system created to assess single words lexical complexity, combining linguistic and psycholinguistic variables in a set of experiments involving random forest and XGboost regressors. Beyond encoding out-of-context information about the lemma, we implemented features based on pre-trained language models to model the target word’s in-context complexity.</abstract>
      <url hash="05ab5f02">2021.semeval-1.90</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.90</doi>
      <bibkey>russo-2021-archer</bibkey>
      <pwcdataset url="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/visual-genome">Visual Genome</pwcdataset>
    </paper>
    <paper id="91">
      <title>katildakat at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 1: Lexical Complexity Prediction of Single Words and Multi-Word Expressions in <fixed-case>E</fixed-case>nglish</title>
      <author><first>Katja</first><last>Voskoboinik</last></author>
      <pages>700–705</pages>
      <abstract>This paper describes systems submitted to Se- mEval 2021 Task 1: Lexical Complexity Prediction (LCP). We compare a linear and a non-linear regression models trained to work for both tracks of the task. We show that both systems are able to generalize better when supplied with information about complexities of single word and multi-word expression (MWE) targets simultaneously. This approach proved to be the most beneficial for multi-word expression targets. We also demonstrate that some hand-crafted features differ in their importance for the target types.</abstract>
      <url hash="8cf3c84f">2021.semeval-1.91</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.91</doi>
      <bibkey>voskoboinik-2021-katildakat</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="92">
      <title><fixed-case>GX</fixed-case> at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 2: <fixed-case>BERT</fixed-case> with Lemma Information for <fixed-case>MCL</fixed-case>-<fixed-case>W</fixed-case>i<fixed-case>C</fixed-case> Task</title>
      <author><first>Wanying</first><last>Xie</last></author>
      <pages>706–712</pages>
      <abstract>This paper presents the GX system for the Multilingual and Cross-lingual Word-in-Context Disambiguation (MCL-WiC) task. The purpose of the MCL-WiC task is to tackle the challenge of capturing the polysemous nature of words without relying on a fixed sense inventory in a multilingual and cross-lingual setting. To solve the problems, we use context-specific word embeddings from BERT to eliminate the ambiguity between words in different contexts. For languages without an available training corpus, such as Chinese, we use neuron machine translation model to translate the English data released by the organizers to obtain available pseudo-data. In this paper, we apply our system to the English and Chinese multilingual setting and the experimental results show that our method has certain advantages.</abstract>
      <url hash="90b58e2c">2021.semeval-1.92</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.92</doi>
      <bibkey>xie-2021-gx-semeval</bibkey>
      <pwccode url="https://github.com/yingwaner/bert4wic" additional="false">yingwaner/bert4wic</pwccode>
      <pwcdataset url="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/wic">WiC</pwcdataset>
    </paper>
    <paper id="93">
      <title><fixed-case>PALI</fixed-case> at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 2: Fine-Tune <fixed-case>XLM</fixed-case>-<fixed-case>R</fixed-case>o<fixed-case>BERT</fixed-case>a for Word in Context Disambiguation</title>
      <author><first>Shuyi</first><last>Xie</last></author>
      <author><first>Jian</first><last>Ma</last></author>
      <author><first>Haiqin</first><last>Yang</last></author>
      <author><first>Lianxin</first><last>Jiang</last></author>
      <author><first>Yang</first><last>Mo</last></author>
      <author><first>Jianping</first><last>Shen</last></author>
      <pages>713–718</pages>
      <abstract>This paper presents the PALI team’s winning system for SemEval-2021 Task 2: Multilingual and Cross-lingual Word-in-Context Disambiguation. We fine-tune XLM-RoBERTa model to solve the task of word in context disambiguation, i.e., to determine whether the target word in the two contexts contains the same meaning or not. In implementation, we first specifically design an input tag to emphasize the target word in the contexts. Second, we construct a new vector on the fine-tuned embeddings from XLM-RoBERTa and feed it to a fully-connected network to output the probability of whether the target word in the context has the same meaning or not. The new vector is attained by concatenating the embedding of the [CLS] token and the embeddings of the target word in the contexts. In training, we explore several tricks, such as the Ranger optimizer, data augmentation, and adversarial training, to improve the model prediction. Consequently, we attain the first place in all four cross-lingual tasks.</abstract>
      <url hash="607fa0d2">2021.semeval-1.93</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.93</doi>
      <bibkey>xie-etal-2021-pali</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="94">
      <title>hub at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 2: Word Meaning Similarity Prediction Model Based on <fixed-case>R</fixed-case>o<fixed-case>BERT</fixed-case>a and Word Frequency</title>
      <author><first>Bo</first><last>Huang</last></author>
      <author><first>Yang</first><last>Bai</last></author>
      <author><first>Xiaobing</first><last>Zhou</last></author>
      <pages>719–723</pages>
      <abstract>This paper introduces the system description of the hub team, which explains the related work and experimental results of our team’s participation in SemEval 2021 Task 2: Multilingual and Cross-lingual Word-in-Context Disambiguation (MCL-WiC). The data of this shared task is mainly some cross-language or multi-language sentence pair corpus. The languages covered in the corpus include English, Chinese, French, Russian, and Arabic. The task goal is to judge whether the same words in these sentence pairs have the same meaning in the sentence. This can be seen as a task of binary classification of sentence pairs. What we need to do is to use our method to determine as accurately as possible the meaning of the words in a sentence pair are the same or different. The model used by our team is mainly composed of RoBERTa and Tf-Idf algorithms. The result evaluation index of task submission is the F1 score. We only participated in the English language task. The final score of the test set prediction results submitted by our team was 84.60.</abstract>
      <url hash="a4f87852">2021.semeval-1.94</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.94</doi>
      <bibkey>huang-etal-2021-hub-semeval</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="95">
      <title>Lotus at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 2: Combination of <fixed-case>BERT</fixed-case> and Paraphrasing for <fixed-case>E</fixed-case>nglish Word Sense Disambiguation</title>
      <author><first>Niloofar</first><last>Ranjbar</last></author>
      <author><first>Hossein</first><last>Zeinali</last></author>
      <pages>724–729</pages>
      <abstract>In this paper, we describe our proposed methods for the multilingual word-in-Context disambiguation task in SemEval-2021. In this task, systems should determine whether a word that occurs in two different sentences is used with the same meaning or not. We proposed several methods using a pre-trained BERT model. In two of them, we paraphrased sentences and add them as input to the BERT, and in one of them, we used WordNet to add some extra lexical information. We evaluated our proposed methods on test data in SemEval- 2021 task 2.</abstract>
      <url hash="e72f8374">2021.semeval-1.95</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.95</doi>
      <bibkey>ranjbar-zeinali-2021-lotus</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="96">
      <title><fixed-case>C</fixed-case>ambridge at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 2: Neural <fixed-case>W</fixed-case>i<fixed-case>C</fixed-case>-Model with Data Augmentation and Exploration of Representation</title>
      <author><first>Zheng</first><last>Yuan</last></author>
      <author><first>David</first><last>Strohmaier</last></author>
      <pages>730–737</pages>
      <abstract>This paper describes the system of the Cambridge team submitted to the SemEval-2021 shared task on Multilingual and Cross-lingual Word-in-Context Disambiguation. Building on top of a pre-trained masked language model, our system is first pre-trained on out-of-domain data, and then fine-tuned on in-domain data. We demonstrate the effectiveness of the proposed two-step training strategy and the benefits of data augmentation from both existing examples and new resources. We further investigate different representations and show that the addition of distance-based features is helpful in the word-in-context disambiguation task. Our system yields highly competitive results in the cross-lingual track without training on any cross-lingual data; and achieves state-of-the-art results in the multilingual track, ranking first in two languages (Arabic and Russian) and second in French out of 171 submitted systems.</abstract>
      <url hash="adbc63b4">2021.semeval-1.96</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.96</doi>
      <bibkey>yuan-strohmaier-2021-cambridge</bibkey>
      <pwcdataset url="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/wic">WiC</pwcdataset>
      <pwcdataset url="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/xl-wic">XL-WiC</pwcdataset>
    </paper>
    <paper id="97">
      <title><fixed-case>U</fixed-case>o<fixed-case>B</fixed-case>_<fixed-case>UK</fixed-case> at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val 2021 Task 2: Zero-Shot and Few-Shot Learning for Multi-lingual and Cross-lingual Word Sense Disambiguation.</title>
      <author><first>Wei</first><last>Li</last></author>
      <author><first>Harish</first><last>Tayyar Madabushi</last></author>
      <author><first>Mark</first><last>Lee</last></author>
      <pages>738–742</pages>
      <abstract>This paper describes our submission to SemEval 2021 Task 2. We compare XLM-RoBERTa Base and Large in the few-shot and zero-shot settings and additionally test the effectiveness of using a k-nearest neighbors classifier in the few-shot setting instead of the more traditional multi-layered perceptron. Our experiments on both the multi-lingual and cross-lingual data show that XLM-RoBERTa Large, unlike the Base version, seems to be able to more effectively transfer learning in a few-shot setting and that the k-nearest neighbors classifier is indeed a more powerful classifier than a multi-layered perceptron when used in few-shot learning.</abstract>
      <url hash="34d37cda">2021.semeval-1.97</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.97</doi>
      <bibkey>li-etal-2021-uob</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="98">
      <title><fixed-case>PAW</fixed-case> at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 2: Multilingual and Cross-lingual Word-in-Context Disambiguation : Exploring Cross Lingual Transfer, Augmentations and Adversarial Training</title>
      <author><first>Harsh</first><last>Goyal</last></author>
      <author><first>Aadarsh</first><last>Singh</last></author>
      <author><first>Priyanshu</first><last>Kumar</last></author>
      <pages>743–747</pages>
      <abstract>We experiment with XLM RoBERTa for Word in Context Disambiguation in the Multi Lingual and Cross Lingual setting so as to develop a single model having knowledge about both settings. We solve the problem as a binary classification problem and also experiment with data augmentation and adversarial training techniques. In addition, we also experiment with a 2-stage training technique. Our approaches prove to be beneficial for better performance and robustness.</abstract>
      <url hash="4e82f548">2021.semeval-1.98</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.98</doi>
      <bibkey>goyal-etal-2021-paw</bibkey>
      <pwcdataset url="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/wic">WiC</pwcdataset>
    </paper>
    <paper id="99">
      <title><fixed-case>LU</fixed-case>-<fixed-case>BZU</fixed-case> at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 2: <fixed-case>W</fixed-case>ord2<fixed-case>V</fixed-case>ec and <fixed-case>L</fixed-case>emma2<fixed-case>V</fixed-case>ec performance in <fixed-case>A</fixed-case>rabic Word-in-Context disambiguation</title>
      <author><first>Moustafa</first><last>Al-Hajj</last></author>
      <author><first>Mustafa</first><last>Jarrar</last></author>
      <pages>748–755</pages>
      <abstract>This paper presents a set of experiments to evaluate and compare between the performance of using CBOW Word2Vec and Lemma2Vec models for Arabic Word-in-Context (WiC) disambiguation without using sense inventories or sense embeddings. As part of the SemEval-2021 Shared Task 2 on WiC disambiguation, we used the dev.ar-ar dataset (2k sentence pairs) to decide whether two words in a given sentence pair carry the same meaning. We used two Word2Vec models: Wiki-CBOW, a pre-trained model on Arabic Wikipedia, and another model we trained on large Arabic corpora of about 3 billion tokens. Two Lemma2Vec models was also constructed based on the two Word2Vec models. Each of the four models was then used in the WiC disambiguation task, and then evaluated on the SemEval-2021 test.ar-ar dataset. At the end, we reported the performance of different models and compared between using lemma-based and word-based models.</abstract>
      <url hash="34b4e301">2021.semeval-1.99</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.99</doi>
      <bibkey>al-hajj-jarrar-2021-lu</bibkey>
      <pwcdataset url="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/wic">WiC</pwcdataset>
    </paper>
    <paper id="100">
      <title><fixed-case>G</fixed-case>loss<fixed-case>R</fixed-case>eader at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 2: Reading Definitions Improves Contextualized Word Embeddings</title>
      <author><first>Maxim</first><last>Rachinskiy</last></author>
      <author><first>Nikolay</first><last>Arefyev</last></author>
      <pages>756–762</pages>
      <abstract>Consulting a dictionary or a glossary is a familiar way for many humans to figure out what does a word in a particular context mean. We hypothesize that a system that can select a proper definition for a particular word occurrence can also naturally solve tasks related to word senses. To verify this hypothesis we developed a solution for the Multilingual and Cross-lingual Word-in-Context (MCL-WiC) task, that does not use any of the shared task data or other WiC data for training. Instead, it is trained to embed word definitions from English WordNet and word occurrences in English texts into the same vector space following an approach previously proposed for Word Sense Disambiguation (WSD). To estimate the similarity in meaning of two word occurrences, we compared different metrics in this shared vector space and found that L1-distance between normalized contextualized word embeddings outperforms traditionally employed cosine similarity and several other metrics. To solve the task for languages other than English, we rely on zero-shot cross-lingual transfer capabilities of the multilingual XLM-R masked language model. Despite not using MCL-WiC training data, in the shared task our approach achieves an accuracy of 89.5% on the English test set, which is only 4% less than the best system. In the multilingual subtask zero-shot cross-lingual transfer shows competitive results, that are within 2% from the best systems for Russian, French, and Arabic. In the cross-lingual subtask are within 2-4% from the best systems.</abstract>
      <url hash="a97418da">2021.semeval-1.100</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.100</doi>
      <bibkey>rachinskiy-arefyev-2021-glossreader</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="101">
      <title><fixed-case>UA</fixed-case>lberta at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 2: Determining Sense Synonymy via Translations</title>
      <author><first>Bradley</first><last>Hauer</last></author>
      <author><first>Hongchang</first><last>Bao</last></author>
      <author><first>Arnob</first><last>Mallik</last></author>
      <author><first>Grzegorz</first><last>Kondrak</last></author>
      <pages>763–770</pages>
      <abstract>We describe the University of Alberta systems for the SemEval-2021 Word-in-Context (WiC) disambiguation task. We explore the use of translation information for deciding whether two different tokens of the same word correspond to the same sense of the word. Our focus is on developing principled theoretical approaches which are grounded in linguistic phenomena, leading to more explainable models. We show that translations from multiple languages can be leveraged to improve the accuracy on the WiC task.</abstract>
      <url hash="5c214009">2021.semeval-1.101</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.101</doi>
      <bibkey>hauer-etal-2021-ualberta</bibkey>
      <pwcdataset url="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/opensubtitles">OpenSubtitles</pwcdataset>
      <pwcdataset url="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/wic">WiC</pwcdataset>
    </paper>
    <paper id="102">
      <title><fixed-case>T</fixed-case>rans<fixed-case>W</fixed-case>i<fixed-case>C</fixed-case> at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 2: Transformer-based Multilingual and Cross-lingual Word-in-Context Disambiguation</title>
      <author><first>Hansi</first><last>Hettiarachchi</last></author>
      <author><first>Tharindu</first><last>Ranasinghe</last></author>
      <pages>771–779</pages>
      <abstract>Identifying whether a word carries the same meaning or different meaning in two contexts is an important research area in natural language processing which plays a significant role in many applications such as question answering, document summarisation, information retrieval and information extraction. Most of the previous work in this area rely on language-specific resources making it difficult to generalise across languages. Considering this limitation, our approach to SemEval-2021 Task 2 is based only on pretrained transformer models and does not use any language-specific processing and resources. Despite that, our best model achieves 0.90 accuracy for English-English subtask which is very compatible compared to the best result of the subtask; 0.93 accuracy. Our approach also achieves satisfactory results in other monolingual and cross-lingual language pairs as well.</abstract>
      <url hash="e0e33864">2021.semeval-1.102</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.102</doi>
      <bibkey>hettiarachchi-ranasinghe-2021-transwic</bibkey>
      <pwcdataset url="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/wic">WiC</pwcdataset>
    </paper>
    <paper id="103">
      <title><fixed-case>LIORI</fixed-case> at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 2: Span Prediction and Binary Classification approaches to Word-in-Context Disambiguation</title>
      <author><first>Adis</first><last>Davletov</last></author>
      <author><first>Nikolay</first><last>Arefyev</last></author>
      <author><first>Denis</first><last>Gordeev</last></author>
      <author><first>Alexey</first><last>Rey</last></author>
      <pages>780–786</pages>
      <abstract>This paper presents our approaches to SemEval-2021 Task 2: Multilingual and Cross-lingual Word-in-Context Disambiguation task. The first approach attempted to reformulate the task as a question answering problem, while the second one framed it as a binary classification problem. Our best system, which is an ensemble of XLM-R based binary classifiers trained with data augmentation, is among the 3 best-performing systems for Russian, French and Arabic in the multilingual subtask. In the post-evaluation period, we experimented with batch normalization, subword pooling and target word occurrence aggregation methods, resulting in further performance improvements.</abstract>
      <url hash="cf75609c">2021.semeval-1.103</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.103</doi>
      <bibkey>davletov-etal-2021-liori</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="104">
      <title><fixed-case>FII</fixed-case>_<fixed-case>CROSS</fixed-case> at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 2: Multilingual and Cross-lingual Word-in-Context Disambiguation</title>
      <author><first>Ciprian</first><last>Bodnar</last></author>
      <author><first>Andrada</first><last>Tapuc</last></author>
      <author><first>Cosmin</first><last>Pintilie</last></author>
      <author><first>Daniela</first><last>Gifu</last></author>
      <author><first>Diana</first><last>Trandabat</last></author>
      <pages>787–792</pages>
      <abstract>This paper presents a word-in-context disambiguation system. The task focuses on capturing the polysemous nature of words in a multilingual and cross-lingual setting, without considering a strict inventory of word meanings. The system applies Natural Language Processing algorithms on datasets from SemEval 2021 Task 2, being able to identify the meaning of words for the languages Arabic, Chinese, English, French and Russian, without making use of any additional mono- or multilingual resources.</abstract>
      <url hash="e84b5e15">2021.semeval-1.104</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.104</doi>
      <bibkey>bodnar-etal-2021-fii</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="105">
      <title><fixed-case>XRJL</fixed-case>-<fixed-case>HKUST</fixed-case> at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 4: <fixed-case>W</fixed-case>ord<fixed-case>N</fixed-case>et-Enhanced Dual Multi-head Co-Attention for Reading Comprehension of Abstract Meaning</title>
      <author><first>Yuxin</first><last>Jiang</last></author>
      <author><first>Ziyi</first><last>Shou</last></author>
      <author><first>Qijun</first><last>Wang</last></author>
      <author><first>Hao</first><last>Wu</last></author>
      <author><first>Fangzhen</first><last>Lin</last></author>
      <pages>793–798</pages>
      <abstract>This paper presents our submitted system to SemEval 2021 Task 4: Reading Comprehension of Abstract Meaning. Our system uses a large pre-trained language model as the encoder and an additional dual multi-head co-attention layer to strengthen the relationship between passages and question-answer pairs, following the current state-of-the-art model DUMA. The main difference is that we stack the passage-question and question-passage attention modules instead of calculating parallelly to simulate re-considering process. We also add a layer normalization module to improve the performance of our model. Furthermore, to incorporate our known knowledge about abstract concepts, we retrieve the definitions of candidate answers from WordNet and feed them to the model as extra inputs. Our system, called WordNet-enhanced DUal Multi-head Co-Attention (WN-DUMA), achieves 86.67% and 89.99% accuracy on the official blind test set of subtask 1 and subtask 2 respectively.</abstract>
      <url hash="04d61da0">2021.semeval-1.105</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.105</doi>
      <bibkey>jiang-etal-2021-xrjl</bibkey>
      <pwccode url="https://github.com/zzshou/RCAM" additional="false">zzshou/RCAM</pwccode>
      <pwcdataset url="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/recam">ReCAM</pwcdataset>
    </paper>
    <paper id="106">
      <title><fixed-case>U</fixed-case>o<fixed-case>R</fixed-case> at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 4: Using Pre-trained <fixed-case>BERT</fixed-case> Token Embeddings for Question Answering of Abstract Meaning</title>
      <author><first>Thanet</first><last>Markchom</last></author>
      <author><first>Huizhi</first><last>Liang</last></author>
      <pages>799–804</pages>
      <abstract>Most question answering tasks focuses on predicting concrete answers, e.g., named entities. These tasks can be normally achieved by understanding the contexts without additional information required. In Reading Comprehension of Abstract Meaning (ReCAM) task, the abstract answers are introduced. To understand abstract meanings in the context, additional knowledge is essential. In this paper, we propose an approach that leverages the pre-trained BERT Token embeddings as a prior knowledge resource. According to the results, our approach using the pre-trained BERT outperformed the baselines. It shows that the pre-trained BERT token embeddings can be used as additional knowledge for understanding abstract meanings in question answering.</abstract>
      <url hash="821c685a">2021.semeval-1.106</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.106</doi>
      <bibkey>markchom-liang-2021-uor</bibkey>
      <pwcdataset url="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/recam">ReCAM</pwcdataset>
    </paper>
    <paper id="107">
      <title>Noobs at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>emeval-2021 Task 4: Masked Language Modeling for abstract answer prediction</title>
      <author><first>Shikhar</first><last>Shukla</last></author>
      <author><first>Sarthak</first><last>Sarthak</last></author>
      <author><first>Karm Veer</first><last>Arya</last></author>
      <pages>805–809</pages>
      <abstract>This paper presents the system developed by our team for Semeval 2021 Task 4: Reading Comprehension of Abstract Meaning. The aim of the task was to benchmark the NLP techniques in understanding the abstract concepts present in a passage, and then predict the missing word in a human written summary of the passage. We trained a Roberta-Large model trained with a masked language modeling objective. In cases where this model failed to predict one of the available options, another Roberta-Large model trained as a binary classifier was used to predict correct and incorrect options. We used passage summary generated by Pegasus model and question as inputs. Our best solution was an ensemble of these 2 systems. We achieved an accuracy of 86.22% on subtask 1 and 87.10% on subtask 2.</abstract>
      <url hash="6377373b">2021.semeval-1.107</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.107</doi>
      <bibkey>shukla-etal-2021-noobs</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="108">
      <title><fixed-case>ZJUKLAB</fixed-case> at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 4: Negative Augmentation with Language Model for Reading Comprehension of Abstract Meaning</title>
      <author><first>Xin</first><last>Xie</last></author>
      <author><first>Xiangnan</first><last>Chen</last></author>
      <author><first>Xiang</first><last>Chen</last></author>
      <author><first>Yong</first><last>Wang</last></author>
      <author><first>Ningyu</first><last>Zhang</last></author>
      <author><first>Shumin</first><last>Deng</last></author>
      <author><first>Huajun</first><last>Chen</last></author>
      <pages>810–819</pages>
      <abstract>This paper presents our systems for the three Subtasks of SemEval Task4: Reading Comprehension of Abstract Meaning (ReCAM). We explain the algorithms used to learn our models and the process of tuning the algorithms and selecting the best model. Inspired by the similarity of the ReCAM task and the language pre-training, we propose a simple yet effective technology, namely, negative augmentation with language model. Evaluation results demonstrate the effectiveness of our proposed approach. Our models achieve the 4th rank on both official test sets of Subtask 1 and Subtask 2 with an accuracy of 87.9% and an accuracy of 92.8%, respectively. We further conduct comprehensive model analysis and observe interesting error cases, which may promote future researches. The code and dataset used in our paper can be found at <url>https://github.com/CheaSim/SemEval2021</url>. The leaderboard can be found at <url>https://competitions.codalab.org/competitions/26153</url>.</abstract>
      <url hash="a11f27fb">2021.semeval-1.108</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.108</doi>
      <bibkey>xie-etal-2021-zjuklab</bibkey>
      <pwccode url="https://github.com/zjunlp/SemEval2021Task4" additional="false">zjunlp/SemEval2021Task4</pwccode>
      <pwcdataset url="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/recam">ReCAM</pwcdataset>
      <pwcdataset url="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/squad">SQuAD</pwcdataset>
    </paper>
    <paper id="109">
      <title><fixed-case>PINGAN</fixed-case> Omini-Sinitic at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 4:Reading Comprehension of Abstract Meaning</title>
      <author><first>Ye</first><last>Wang</last></author>
      <author><first>Yanmeng</first><last>Wang</last></author>
      <author><first>Haijun</first><last>Zhu</last></author>
      <author><first>Bo</first><last>Zeng</last></author>
      <author><first>Zhenghong</first><last>Hao</last></author>
      <author><first>Shaojun</first><last>Wang</last></author>
      <author><first>Jing</first><last>Xiao</last></author>
      <pages>820–826</pages>
      <abstract>This paper describes the winning system for subtask 2 and the second-placed system for subtask 1 in SemEval 2021 Task 4: ReadingComprehension of Abstract Meaning. We propose to use pre-trianed Electra discriminator to choose the best abstract word from five candidates. An upper attention and auto denoising mechanism is introduced to process the long sequences. The experiment results demonstrate that this contribution greatly facilitatesthe contextual language modeling in reading comprehension task. The ablation study is also conducted to show the validity of our proposed methods.</abstract>
      <url hash="5a5b7796">2021.semeval-1.109</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.109</doi>
      <bibkey>wang-etal-2021-pingan</bibkey>
      <pwcdataset url="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/recam">ReCAM</pwcdataset>
    </paper>
    <paper id="110">
      <title><fixed-case>NEU</fixed-case>er at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 4: Complete Summary Representation by Filling Answers into Question for Matching Reading Comprehension</title>
      <author><first>Zhixiang</first><last>Chen</last></author>
      <author><first>Yikun</first><last>Lei</last></author>
      <author><first>Pai</first><last>Liu</last></author>
      <author><first>Guibing</first><last>Guo</last></author>
      <pages>827–832</pages>
      <abstract>SemEval task 4 aims to find a proper option from multiple candidates to resolve the task of machine reading comprehension. Most existing approaches propose to concat question and option together to form a context-aware model. However, we argue that straightforward concatenation can only provide a coarse-grained context for the MRC task, ignoring the specific positions of the option relative to the question. In this paper, we propose a novel MRC model by filling options into the question to produce a fine-grained context (defined as summary) which can better reveal the relationship between option and question. We conduct a series of experiments on the given dataset, and the results show that our approach outperforms other counterparts to a large extent.</abstract>
      <url hash="a36226a7">2021.semeval-1.110</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.110</doi>
      <bibkey>chen-etal-2021-neuer</bibkey>
      <pwcdataset url="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/dream">DREAM</pwcdataset>
      <pwcdataset url="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/multinli">MultiNLI</pwcdataset>
      <pwcdataset url="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/race">RACE</pwcdataset>
      <pwcdataset url="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/recam">ReCAM</pwcdataset>
    </paper>
    <paper id="111">
      <title><fixed-case>WLV</fixed-case>-<fixed-case>RIT</fixed-case> at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 5: A Neural Transformer Framework for Detecting Toxic Spans</title>
      <author><first>Tharindu</first><last>Ranasinghe</last></author>
      <author><first>Diptanu</first><last>Sarkar</last></author>
      <author><first>Marcos</first><last>Zampieri</last></author>
      <author><first>Alexander</first><last>Ororbia</last></author>
      <pages>833–840</pages>
      <abstract>In recent years, the widespread use of social media has led to an increase in the generation of toxic and offensive content on online platforms. In response, social media platforms have worked on developing automatic detection methods and employing human moderators to cope with this deluge of offensive content. While various state-of-the-art statistical models have been applied to detect toxic posts, there are only a few studies that focus on detecting the words or expressions that make a post offensive. This motivates the organization of the SemEval-2021 Task 5: Toxic Spans Detection competition, which has provided participants with a dataset containing toxic spans annotation in English posts. In this paper, we present the WLV-RIT entry for the SemEval-2021 Task 5. Our best performing neural transformer model achieves an 0.68 F1-Score. Furthermore, we develop an open-source framework for multilingual detection of offensive spans, i.e., MUDES, based on neural transformers that detect toxic spans in texts.</abstract>
      <url hash="a9c8aebc">2021.semeval-1.111</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.111</doi>
      <bibkey>ranasinghe-etal-2021-wlv</bibkey>
      <pwccode url="https://github.com/tharindudr/MUDES" additional="false">tharindudr/MUDES</pwccode>
      <pwcdataset url="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/hateval">HatEval</pwcdataset>
      <pwcdataset url="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/hatexplain">HateXplain</pwcdataset>
    </paper>
    <paper id="112">
      <title><fixed-case>YNU</fixed-case>-<fixed-case>HPCC</fixed-case> at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 5: Using a Transformer-based Model with Auxiliary Information for Toxic Span Detection</title>
      <author><first>Ruijun</first><last>Chen</last></author>
      <author><first>Jin</first><last>Wang</last></author>
      <author><first>Xuejie</first><last>Zhang</last></author>
      <pages>841–845</pages>
      <abstract>Toxic span detection requires the detection of spans that make a text toxic instead of simply classifying the text. In this paper, a transformer-based model with auxiliary information is proposed for SemEval-2021 Task 5. The proposed model was implemented based on the BERT-CRF architecture. It consists of three parts: a transformer-based model that can obtain the token representation, an auxiliary information module that combines features from different layers, and an output layer used for the classification. Various BERT-based models, such as BERT, ALBERT, RoBERTa, and XLNET, were used to learn contextual representations. The predictions of these models were assembled to improve the sequence labeling tasks by using a voting strategy. Experimental results showed that the introduced auxiliary information can improve the performance of toxic spans detection. The proposed model ranked 5th of 91 in the competition. The code of this study is available at <url>https://github.com/Chenrj233/semeval2021_task5</url></abstract>
      <url hash="ebe84968">2021.semeval-1.112</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.112</doi>
      <bibkey>chen-etal-2021-ynu</bibkey>
      <pwccode url="https://github.com/chenrj233/semeval2021_task5" additional="false">chenrj233/semeval2021_task5</pwccode>
    </paper>
    <paper id="113">
      <title><fixed-case>UIT</fixed-case>-<fixed-case>ISE</fixed-case>-<fixed-case>NLP</fixed-case> at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 5: Toxic Spans Detection with <fixed-case>B</fixed-case>i<fixed-case>LSTM</fixed-case>-<fixed-case>CRF</fixed-case> and <fixed-case>T</fixed-case>oxic<fixed-case>BERT</fixed-case> Comment Classification</title>
      <author><first>Son T.</first><last>Luu</last></author>
      <author><first>Ngan</first><last>Nguyen</last></author>
      <pages>846–851</pages>
      <abstract>We present our works on SemEval-2021 Task 5 about Toxic Spans Detection. This task aims to build a model for identifying toxic words in whole posts. We use the BiLSTM-CRF model combining with ToxicBERT Classification to train the detection model for identifying toxic words in posts. Our model achieves 62.23% by F1-score on the Toxic Spans Detection task.</abstract>
      <url hash="c6a8d2d9">2021.semeval-1.113</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.113</doi>
      <bibkey>luu-nguyen-2021-uit</bibkey>
      <pwccode url="https://github.com/sonlam1102/toxic-spans-detection-bilstm_crf" additional="false">sonlam1102/toxic-spans-detection-bilstm_crf</pwccode>
    </paper>
    <paper id="114">
      <title><fixed-case>GHOST</fixed-case> at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 5: Is explanation all you need?</title>
      <author><first>Kamil</first><last>Pluciński</last></author>
      <author><first>Hanna</first><last>Klimczak</last></author>
      <pages>852–859</pages>
      <abstract>This paper discusses different approaches to the Toxic Spans Detection task. The problem posed by the task was to determine which words contribute mostly to recognising a document as toxic. As opposed to binary classification of entire texts, word-level assessment could be of great use during comment moderation, also allowing for a more in-depth comprehension of the model’s predictions. As the main goal was to ensure transparency and understanding, this paper focuses on the current state-of-the-art approaches based on the explainable AI concepts and compares them to a supervised learning solution with word-level labels. The work consists of two xAI approaches that automatically provide the explanation for models trained for binary classification of toxic documents: an LSTM model with attention as a model-specific approach and the Shapley values for interpreting BERT predictions as a model-agnostic method. The competing approach considers this problem as supervised token classification, where models like BERT and its modifications were tested. The paper aims to explore, compare and assess the quality of predictions for different methods on the task. The advantages of each approach and further research direction are also discussed.</abstract>
      <url hash="631440f7">2021.semeval-1.114</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.114</doi>
      <bibkey>plucinski-klimczak-2021-ghost</bibkey>
      <pwcdataset url="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/civil-comments">Civil Comments</pwcdataset>
    </paper>
    <paper id="115">
      <title><fixed-case>G</fixed-case>olden<fixed-case>W</fixed-case>ind at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 5: Orthrus - An Ensemble Approach to Identify Toxicity</title>
      <author><first>Marco</first><last>Palomino</last></author>
      <author><first>Dawid</first><last>Grad</last></author>
      <author><first>James</first><last>Bedwell</last></author>
      <pages>860–864</pages>
      <abstract>Many new developments to detect and mitigate toxicity are currently being evaluated. We are particularly interested in the correlation between toxicity and the emotions expressed in online posts. While toxicity may be disguised by amending the wording of posts, emotions will not. Therefore, we describe here an ensemble method to identify toxicity and classify the emotions expressed on a corpus of annotated posts published by Task 5 of SemEval 2021–our analysis shows that the majority of such posts express anger, sadness and fear. Our method to identify toxicity combines a lexicon-based approach, which on its own achieves an F1 score of 61.07%, with a supervised learning approach, which on its own achieves an F1 score of 60%. When both methods are combined, the ensemble achieves an F1 score of 66.37%.</abstract>
      <url hash="c1d1b952">2021.semeval-1.115</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.115</doi>
      <bibkey>palomino-etal-2021-goldenwind</bibkey>
      <pwcdataset url="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/civil-comments">Civil Comments</pwcdataset>
    </paper>
    <paper id="116">
      <title><fixed-case>LISAC</fixed-case> <fixed-case>FSDM</fixed-case> <fixed-case>USMBA</fixed-case> at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 5: Tackling Toxic Spans Detection Challenge with Supervised <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>pan<fixed-case>BERT</fixed-case>-based Model and Unsupervised <fixed-case>LIME</fixed-case>-based Model</title>
      <author><first>Abdessamad</first><last>Benlahbib</last></author>
      <author><first>Ahmed</first><last>Alami</last></author>
      <author><first>Hamza</first><last>Alami</last></author>
      <pages>865–869</pages>
      <abstract>Toxic spans detection is an emerging challenge that aims to find toxic spans within a toxic text. In this paper, we describe our solutions to tackle toxic spans detection. The first solution, which follows a supervised approach, is based on SpanBERT model. This latter is intended to better embed and predict spans of text. The second solution, which adopts an unsupervised approach, combines linear support vector machine with the Local Interpretable Model-Agnostic Explanations (LIME). This last is used to interpret predictions of learning-based models. Our supervised model outperformed the unsupervised model and achieved the f-score of 67,84% (ranked 22/85) in Task 5 at SemEval-2021: Toxic Spans Detection.</abstract>
      <url hash="437a013c">2021.semeval-1.116</url>
      <attachment type="OptionalSupplementaryMaterial" hash="9cf2c73b">2021.semeval-1.116.OptionalSupplementaryMaterial.zip</attachment>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.116</doi>
      <bibkey>benlahbib-etal-2021-lisac</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="117">
      <title><fixed-case>HITMI</fixed-case>&amp;<fixed-case>T</fixed-case> at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 5: Integrating Transformer and <fixed-case>CRF</fixed-case> for Toxic Spans Detection</title>
      <author><first>Chenyi</first><last>Wang</last></author>
      <author><first>Tianshu</first><last>Liu</last></author>
      <author><first>Tiejun</first><last>Zhao</last></author>
      <pages>870–874</pages>
      <abstract>This paper introduces our system at SemEval-2021 Task 5: Toxic Spans Detection. The task aims to accurately locate toxic spans within a text. Using BIO tagging scheme, we model the task as a token-level sequence labeling task. Our system uses a single model built on the model of multi-layer bidirectional transformer encoder. And we introduce conditional random field (CRF) to make the model learn the constraints between tags. We use ERNIE as pre-trained model, which is more suitable for the task accroding to our experiments. In addition, we use adversarial training with the fast gradient method (FGM) to improve the robustness of the system. Our system obtains 69.85% F1 score, ranking 3rd for the official evaluation.</abstract>
      <url hash="982ad5b7">2021.semeval-1.117</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.117</doi>
      <bibkey>wang-etal-2021-hitmi</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="118">
      <title><fixed-case>AS</fixed-case>tar<fixed-case>T</fixed-case>wice at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 5: Toxic Span Detection Using <fixed-case>R</fixed-case>o<fixed-case>BERT</fixed-case>a-<fixed-case>CRF</fixed-case>, Domain Specific Pre-Training and Self-Training</title>
      <author><first>Thakur Ashutosh</first><last>Suman</last></author>
      <author><first>Abhinav</first><last>Jain</last></author>
      <pages>875–880</pages>
      <abstract>This paper describes our contribution to SemEval-2021 Task 5: Toxic Spans Detection. Our solution is built upon RoBERTa language model and Conditional Random Fields (CRF). We pre-trained RoBERTa on Civil Comments dataset, enabling it to create better contextual representation for this task. We also employed the semi-supervised learning technique of self-training, which allowed us to extend our training dataset. In addition to these, we also identified some pre-processing steps that significantly improved our F1 score. Our proposed system achieved a rank of 41 with an F1 score of 66.16%.</abstract>
      <url hash="416a631e">2021.semeval-1.118</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.118</doi>
      <bibkey>suman-jain-2021-astartwice</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="119">
      <title><fixed-case>NLP</fixed-case>_<fixed-case>UIOWA</fixed-case> at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>emeval-2021 Task 5: Transferring Toxic Sets to Tag Toxic Spans</title>
      <author><first>Jonathan</first><last>Rusert</last></author>
      <pages>881–887</pages>
      <abstract>We leverage a BLSTM with attention to identify toxic spans in texts. We explore different dimensions which affect the model’s performance. The first dimension explored is the toxic set the model is trained on. Besides the provided dataset, we explore the transferability of 5 different toxic related sets, including offensive, toxic, abusive, and hate sets. We find that the solely offensive set shows the highest promise of transferability. The second dimension we explore is methodology, including leveraging attention, employing a greedy remove method, using a frequency ratio, and examining hybrid combinations of multiple methods. We conduct an error analysis to examine which types of toxic spans were missed and which were wrongly inferred as toxic along with the main reasons why they occurred. Finally, we extend our method via ensembles, which achieves our highest F1 score of 55.1.</abstract>
      <url hash="d3fd46e9">2021.semeval-1.119</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.119</doi>
      <bibkey>rusert-2021-nlp</bibkey>
      <pwcdataset url="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/olid">OLID</pwcdataset>
    </paper>
    <paper id="120">
      <title><fixed-case>S</fixed-case>-<fixed-case>NLP</fixed-case> at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 5: An Analysis of Dual Networks for Sequence Tagging</title>
      <author><first>Viet Anh</first><last>Nguyen</last></author>
      <author><first>Tam Minh</first><last>Nguyen</last></author>
      <author><first>Huy</first><last>Quang Dao</last></author>
      <author><first>Quang</first><last>Huu Pham</last></author>
      <pages>888–897</pages>
      <abstract>The SemEval 2021 task 5: Toxic Spans Detection is a task of identifying considered-toxic spans in text, which provides a valuable, automatic tool for moderating online contents. This paper represents the second-place method for the task, an ensemble of two approaches. While one approach relies on combining different embedding methods to extract diverse semantic and syntactic representations of words in context; the other utilizes extra data with a slightly customized Self-training, a semi-supervised learning technique, for sequence tagging problems. Both of our architectures take advantage of a strong language model, which was fine-tuned on a toxic classification task. Although experimental evidence indicates higher effectiveness of the first approach than the second one, combining them leads to our best results of 70.77 F1-score on the test dataset.</abstract>
      <url hash="663ddfda">2021.semeval-1.120</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.120</doi>
      <bibkey>nguyen-etal-2021-nlp</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="121">
      <title><fixed-case>UA</fixed-case>ntwerp at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 5: Spans are Spans, stacking a binary word level approach to toxic span detection</title>
      <author><first>Ben</first><last>Burtenshaw</last></author>
      <author><first>Mike</first><last>Kestemont</last></author>
      <pages>898–903</pages>
      <abstract>This paper describes the system developed by the Antwerp Centre for Digital humanities and literary Criticism [UAntwerp] for toxic span detection. We used a stacked generalisation ensemble of five component models, with two distinct interpretations of the task. Two models attempted to predict binary word toxicity based on ngram sequences, whilst 3 categorical span based models were trained to predict toxic token labels based on complete sequence tokens. The five models’ predictions were ensembled within an LSTM model. As well as describing the system, we perform error analysis to explore model performance in relation to textual features. The system described in this paper scored 0.6755 and ranked 26th.</abstract>
      <url hash="cbe44c5a">2021.semeval-1.121</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.121</doi>
      <bibkey>burtenshaw-kestemont-2021-uantwerp</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="122">
      <title>hub at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 5: Toxic Span Detection Based on Word-Level Classification</title>
      <author><first>Bo</first><last>Huang</last></author>
      <author><first>Yang</first><last>Bai</last></author>
      <author><first>Xiaobing</first><last>Zhou</last></author>
      <pages>904–908</pages>
      <abstract>This article introduces the system description of the hub team, which explains the related work and experimental results of our team’s participation in SemEval 2021 Task 5: Toxic Spans Detection. The data for this shared task comes from some posts on the Internet. The task goal is to identify the toxic content contained in these text data. We need to find the span of the toxic text in the text data as accurately as possible. In the same post, the toxic text may be one paragraph or multiple paragraphs. Our team uses a classification scheme based on word-level to accomplish this task. The system we used to submit the results is ALBERT+BILSTM+CRF. The result evaluation index of the task submission is the F1 score, and the final score of the prediction result of the test set submitted by our team is 0.6640226029.</abstract>
      <url hash="3aa59e37">2021.semeval-1.122</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.122</doi>
      <bibkey>huang-etal-2021-hub-semeval-2021</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="123">
      <title>Sefamerve <fixed-case>ARGE</fixed-case> at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 5: Toxic Spans Detection Using Segmentation Based 1-<fixed-case>D</fixed-case> Convolutional Neural Network Model</title>
      <author><first>Selman</first><last>Delil</last></author>
      <author><first>Birol</first><last>Kuyumcu</last></author>
      <author><first>Cüneyt</first><last>Aksakallı</last></author>
      <pages>909–912</pages>
      <abstract>This paper describes our contribution to SemEval-2021 Task 5: Toxic Spans Detection. Our approach considers toxic spans detection as a segmentation problem. The system, Waw-unet, consists of a 1-D convolutional neural network adopted from U-Net architecture commonly applied for semantic segmentation. We customize existing architecture by adding a special network block considering for text segmentation, as an essential component of the model. We compared the model with two transformers-based systems RoBERTa and XLM-RoBERTa to see its performance against pre-trained language models. We obtained 0.6251 f1 score with Waw-unet while 0.6390 and 0.6601 with the compared models respectively.</abstract>
      <url hash="15368855">2021.semeval-1.123</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.123</doi>
      <bibkey>delil-etal-2021-sefamerve</bibkey>
      <pwccode url="https://github.com/birolkuyumcu/wawunet_for_toxicspan" additional="false">birolkuyumcu/wawunet_for_toxicspan</pwccode>
    </paper>
    <paper id="124">
      <title><fixed-case>MIPT</fixed-case>-<fixed-case>NSU</fixed-case>-<fixed-case>UTMN</fixed-case> at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 5: Ensembling Learning with Pre-trained Language Models for Toxic Spans Detection</title>
      <author><first>Mikhail</first><last>Kotyushev</last></author>
      <author><first>Anna</first><last>Glazkova</last></author>
      <author><first>Dmitry</first><last>Morozov</last></author>
      <pages>913–918</pages>
      <abstract>This paper describes our system for SemEval-2021 Task 5 on Toxic Spans Detection. We developed ensemble models using BERT-based neural architectures and post-processing to combine tokens into spans. We evaluated several pre-trained language models using various ensemble techniques for toxic span identification and achieved sizable improvements over our baseline fine-tuned BERT models. Finally, our system obtained a F1-score of 67.55% on test data.</abstract>
      <url hash="3cd22cfb">2021.semeval-1.124</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.124</doi>
      <bibkey>kotyushev-etal-2021-mipt</bibkey>
      <pwccode url="https://github.com/morozowdmitry/semeval21" additional="false">morozowdmitry/semeval21</pwccode>
    </paper>
    <paper id="125">
      <title><fixed-case>UIT</fixed-case>-E10dot3 at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 5: Toxic Spans Detection with Named Entity Recognition and Question-Answering Approaches</title>
      <author><first>Phu</first><last>Gia Hoang</last></author>
      <author><first>Luan</first><last>Thanh Nguyen</last></author>
      <author><first>Kiet</first><last>Nguyen</last></author>
      <pages>919–926</pages>
      <abstract>The increment of toxic comments on online space is causing tremendous effects on other vulnerable users. For this reason, considerable efforts are made to deal with this, and SemEval-2021 Task 5: Toxic Spans Detection is one of those. This task asks competitors to extract spans that have toxicity from the given texts, and we have done several analyses to understand its structure before doing experiments. We solve this task by two approaches, Named Entity Recognition with spaCy’s library and Question-Answering with RoBERTa combining with ToxicBERT, and the former gains the highest F1-score of 66.99%.</abstract>
      <url hash="2224d5c1">2021.semeval-1.125</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.125</doi>
      <bibkey>gia-hoang-etal-2021-uit</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="126">
      <title><fixed-case>S</fixed-case>koltech<fixed-case>NLP</fixed-case> at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 5: Leveraging Sentence-level Pre-training for Toxic Span Detection</title>
      <author><first>David</first><last>Dale</last></author>
      <author><first>Igor</first><last>Markov</last></author>
      <author><first>Varvara</first><last>Logacheva</last></author>
      <author><first>Olga</first><last>Kozlova</last></author>
      <author><first>Nikita</first><last>Semenov</last></author>
      <author><first>Alexander</first><last>Panchenko</last></author>
      <pages>927–934</pages>
      <abstract>This work describes the participation of the Skoltech NLP group team (Sk) in the Toxic Spans Detection task at SemEval-2021. The goal of the task is to identify the most toxic fragments of a given sentence, which is a binary sequence tagging problem. We show that fine-tuning a RoBERTa model for this problem is a strong baseline. This baseline can be further improved by pre-training the RoBERTa model on a large dataset labeled for toxicity at the sentence level. While our solution scored among the top 20% participating models, it is only 2 points below the best result. This suggests the viability of our approach.</abstract>
      <url hash="459da539">2021.semeval-1.126</url>
      <attachment type="OptionalSupplementaryMaterial" hash="c0f56b96">2021.semeval-1.126.OptionalSupplementaryMaterial.zip</attachment>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.126</doi>
      <bibkey>dale-etal-2021-skoltechnlp</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="127">
      <title>Entity at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 5: Weakly Supervised Token Labelling for Toxic Spans Detection</title>
      <author><first>Vaibhav</first><last>Jain</last></author>
      <author><first>Mina</first><last>Naghshnejad</last></author>
      <pages>935–940</pages>
      <abstract>Detection of toxic spans - detecting toxicity of contents in the granularity of tokens - is crucial for effective moderation of online discussions. The baseline approach for this problem using the transformer model is to add a token classification head to the language model and fine-tune the layers with the token labeled dataset. One of the limitations of such a baseline approach is the scarcity of labeled data. To improve the results, We studied leveraging existing public datasets for a related but different task of entire comment/sentence classification. We propose two approaches: the first approach fine-tunes transformer models that are pre-trained on sentence classification samples. In the second approach, we perform weak supervision with soft attention to learn token level labels from sentence labels. Our experiments show improvements in the F1 score over the baseline approach. The implementation has been released publicly.</abstract>
      <url hash="5714085a">2021.semeval-1.127</url>
      <attachment type="OptionalSupplementaryMaterial" hash="cbb28c4b">2021.semeval-1.127.OptionalSupplementaryMaterial.zip</attachment>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.127</doi>
      <bibkey>jain-naghshnejad-2021-entity</bibkey>
      <pwccode url="https://github.com/vaibhav29498/toxic-spans-detection" additional="false">vaibhav29498/toxic-spans-detection</pwccode>
      <pwcdataset url="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/hatexplain">HateXplain</pwcdataset>
    </paper>
    <paper id="128">
      <title><fixed-case>B</fixed-case>ennett<fixed-case>NLP</fixed-case> at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 5: Toxic Spans Detection using Stacked Embedding Powered Toxic Entity Recognizer</title>
      <author><first>Harsh</first><last>Kataria</last></author>
      <author><first>Ambuje</first><last>Gupta</last></author>
      <author><first>Vipul</first><last>Mishra</last></author>
      <pages>941–947</pages>
      <abstract>With the rapid growth in technology, social media activity has seen a boom across all age groups. It is humanly impossible to check all the tweets, comments and status manually whether they follow proper community guidelines. A lot of toxicity is regularly posted on these social media platforms. This research aims to find toxic words in a sentence so that a healthy social community is built across the globe and the users receive censored content with specific warnings and facts. To solve this challenging problem, authors have combined concepts of Linked List for pre-processing and then used the idea of stacked embeddings like BERT Embeddings, Flair Embeddings and Word2Vec on the flairNLP framework to get the desired results. F1 metric was used to evaluate the model. The authors were able to produce a 0.74 F1 score on their test set.</abstract>
      <url hash="4f7df8f3">2021.semeval-1.128</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.128</doi>
      <bibkey>kataria-etal-2021-bennettnlp</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="129">
      <title><fixed-case>U</fixed-case>o<fixed-case>T</fixed-case>-<fixed-case>UWF</fixed-case>-<fixed-case>P</fixed-case>art<fixed-case>AI</fixed-case> at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 5: Self Attention Based <fixed-case>B</fixed-case>i-<fixed-case>GRU</fixed-case> with Multi-Embedding Representation for Toxicity Highlighter</title>
      <author><first>Hamed</first><last>Babaei Giglou</last></author>
      <author><first>Taher</first><last>Rahgooy</last></author>
      <author><first>Mostafa</first><last>Rahgouy</last></author>
      <author><first>Jafar</first><last>Razmara</last></author>
      <pages>948–952</pages>
      <abstract>Toxic Spans Detection(TSD) task is defined as highlighting spans that make a text toxic. Many works have been done to classify a given comment or document as toxic or non-toxic. However, none of those proposed models work at the token level. In this paper, we propose a self-attention-based bidirectional gated recurrent unit(BiGRU) with a multi-embedding representation of the tokens. Our proposed model enriches the representation by a combination of GPT-2, GloVe, and RoBERTa embeddings, which led to promising results. Experimental results show that our proposed approach is very effective in detecting span tokens.</abstract>
      <url hash="06bba31c">2021.semeval-1.129</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.129</doi>
      <bibkey>babaei-giglou-etal-2021-uot</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="130">
      <title><fixed-case>Y</fixed-case>oung<fixed-case>S</fixed-case>heldon at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 5: Fine-tuning Pre-trained Language Models for Toxic Spans Detection using Token classification Objective</title>
      <author><first>Mayukh</first><last>Sharma</last></author>
      <author><first>Ilanthenral</first><last>Kandasamy</last></author>
      <author><first>W.b.</first><last>Vasantha</last></author>
      <pages>953–959</pages>
      <abstract>In this paper, we describe our system used for SemEval 2021 Task 5: Toxic Spans Detection. Our proposed system approaches the problem as a token classification task. We trained our model to find toxic words and concatenate their spans to predict the toxic spans within a sentence. We fine-tuned Pre-trained Language Models (PLMs) for identifying the toxic words. For fine-tuning, we stacked the classification layer on top of the PLM features of each word to classify if it is toxic or not. PLMs are pre-trained using different objectives and their performance may differ on downstream tasks. We, therefore, compare the performance of BERT, ELECTRA, RoBERTa, XLM-RoBERTa, T5, XLNet, and MPNet for identifying toxic spans within a sentence. Our best performing system used RoBERTa. It performed well, achieving an F1 score of 0.6841 and secured a rank of 16 on the official leaderboard.</abstract>
      <url hash="5dc2313f">2021.semeval-1.130</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.130</doi>
      <bibkey>sharma-etal-2021-youngsheldon</bibkey>
      <pwccode url="https://github.com/04mayukh/YoungSheldon-at-SemEval-2021-Task-5-Toxic-Spans-Detection" additional="false">04mayukh/YoungSheldon-at-SemEval-2021-Task-5-Toxic-Spans-Detection</pwccode>
    </paper>
    <paper id="131">
      <title><fixed-case>HLE</fixed-case>-<fixed-case>UPC</fixed-case> at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 5: Multi-Depth <fixed-case>D</fixed-case>istil<fixed-case>BERT</fixed-case> for Toxic Spans Detection</title>
      <author><first>Rafel</first><last>Palliser-Sans</last></author>
      <author><first>Albert</first><last>Rial-Farràs</last></author>
      <pages>960–966</pages>
      <abstract>This paper presents our submission to SemEval-2021 Task 5: Toxic Spans Detection. The purpose of this task is to detect the spans that make a text toxic, which is a complex labour for several reasons. Firstly, because of the intrinsic subjectivity of toxicity, and secondly, due to toxicity not always coming from single words like insults or offends, but sometimes from whole expressions formed by words that may not be toxic individually. Following this idea of focusing on both single words and multi-word expressions, we study the impact of using a multi-depth DistilBERT model, which uses embeddings from different layers to estimate the final per-token toxicity. Our quantitative results show that using information from multiple depths boosts the performance of the model. Finally, we also analyze our best model qualitatively.</abstract>
      <url hash="d343869f">2021.semeval-1.131</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.131</doi>
      <bibkey>palliser-sans-rial-farras-2021-hle</bibkey>
      <pwccode url="https://github.com/rafelps/HLE-UPC-SemEval-2021-ToxicSpansDetection" additional="false">rafelps/HLE-UPC-SemEval-2021-ToxicSpansDetection</pwccode>
    </paper>
    <paper id="132">
      <title>Lone Pine at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 5: Fine-Grained Detection of Hate Speech Using <fixed-case>BERT</fixed-case>oxic</title>
      <author><first>Yakoob</first><last>Khan</last></author>
      <author><first>Weicheng</first><last>Ma</last></author>
      <author><first>Soroush</first><last>Vosoughi</last></author>
      <pages>967–973</pages>
      <abstract>This paper describes our approach to the Toxic Spans Detection problem (SemEval-2021 Task 5). We propose BERToxic, a system that fine-tunes a pre-trained BERT model to locate toxic text spans in a given text and utilizes additional post-processing steps to refine the boundaries. The post-processing steps involve (1) labeling character offsets between consecutive toxic tokens as toxic and (2) assigning a toxic label to words that have at least one token labeled as toxic. Through experiments, we show that these two post-processing steps improve the performance of our model by 4.16% on the test set. We also studied the effects of data augmentation and ensemble modeling strategies on our system. Our system significantly outperformed the provided baseline and achieved an F1-score of 0.683, placing Lone Pine in the 17th place out of 91 teams in the competition. Our code is made available at <url>https://github.com/Yakoob-Khan/Toxic-Spans-Detection</url></abstract>
      <url hash="3bc8fdf1">2021.semeval-1.132</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.132</doi>
      <bibkey>khan-etal-2021-lone</bibkey>
      <pwccode url="https://github.com/Yakoob-Khan/Toxic-Spans-Detection" additional="false">Yakoob-Khan/Toxic-Spans-Detection</pwccode>
      <pwcdataset url="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/hatexplain">HateXplain</pwcdataset>
    </paper>
    <paper id="133">
      <title><fixed-case>SRPOL</fixed-case> <fixed-case>DIALOGUE</fixed-case> <fixed-case>SYSTEMS</fixed-case> at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 5: Automatic Generation of Training Data for Toxic Spans Detection</title>
      <author><first>Michał</first><last>Satława</last></author>
      <author><first>Katarzyna</first><last>Zamłyńska</last></author>
      <author><first>Jarosław</first><last>Piersa</last></author>
      <author><first>Joanna</first><last>Kolis</last></author>
      <author><first>Klaudia</first><last>Firląg</last></author>
      <author><first>Katarzyna</first><last>Beksa</last></author>
      <author><first>Zuzanna</first><last>Bordzicka</last></author>
      <author><first>Christian</first><last>Goltz</last></author>
      <author><first>Paweł</first><last>Bujnowski</last></author>
      <author><first>Piotr</first><last>Andruszkiewicz</last></author>
      <pages>974–983</pages>
      <abstract>This paper presents a system used for SemEval-2021 Task 5: Toxic Spans Detection. Our system is an ensemble of BERT-based models for binary word classification, trained on a dataset extended by toxic comments modified and generated by two language models. For the toxic word classification, the prediction threshold value was optimized separately for every comment, in order to maximize the expected F1 value.</abstract>
      <url hash="0e9f62d8">2021.semeval-1.133</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.133</doi>
      <bibkey>satlawa-etal-2021-srpol</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="134">
      <title><fixed-case>SINAI</fixed-case> at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 5: Combining Embeddings in a <fixed-case>B</fixed-case>i<fixed-case>LSTM</fixed-case>-<fixed-case>CRF</fixed-case> model for Toxic Spans Detection</title>
      <author><first>Flor Miriam</first><last>Plaza-del-Arco</last></author>
      <author><first>Pilar</first><last>López-Úbeda</last></author>
      <author><first>L. Alfonso</first><last>Ureña-López</last></author>
      <author><first>M. Teresa</first><last>Martín-Valdivia</last></author>
      <pages>984–989</pages>
      <abstract>This paper describes the participation of SINAI team at Task 5: Toxic Spans Detection which consists of identifying spans that make a text toxic. Although several resources and systems have been developed so far in the context of offensive language, both annotation and tasks have mainly focused on classifying whether a text is offensive or not. However, detecting toxic spans is crucial to identify why a text is toxic and can assist human moderators to locate this type of content on social media. In order to accomplish the task, we follow a deep learning-based approach using a Bidirectional variant of a Long Short Term Memory network along with a stacked Conditional Random Field decoding layer (BiLSTM-CRF). Specifically, we test the performance of the combination of different pre-trained word embeddings for recognizing toxic entities in text. The results show that the combination of word embeddings helps in detecting offensive content. Our team ranks 29th out of 91 participants.</abstract>
      <url hash="00e3f120">2021.semeval-1.134</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.134</doi>
      <bibkey>plaza-del-arco-etal-2021-sinai</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="135">
      <title><fixed-case>CSECU</fixed-case>-<fixed-case>DSG</fixed-case> at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 5: Leveraging Ensemble of Sequence Tagging Models for Toxic Spans Detection</title>
      <author><first>Tashin</first><last>Hossain</last></author>
      <author><first>Jannatun</first><last>Naim</last></author>
      <author><first>Fareen</first><last>Tasneem</last></author>
      <author><first>Radiathun</first><last>Tasnia</last></author>
      <author><first>Abu Nowshed</first><last>Chy</last></author>
      <pages>990–994</pages>
      <abstract>The upsurge of prolific blogging and microblogging platforms enabled the abusers to spread negativity and threats greater than ever. Detecting the toxic portions substantially aids to moderate or exclude the abusive parts for maintaining sound online platforms. This paper describes our participation in the SemEval 2021 toxic span detection task. The task requires detecting spans that convey toxic remarks from the given text. We explore an ensemble of sequence labeling models including the BiLSTM-CRF, spaCy NER model with custom toxic tags, and fine-tuned BERT model to identify the toxic spans. Finally, a majority voting ensemble method is used to determine the unified toxic spans. Experimental results depict the competitive performance of our model among the participants.</abstract>
      <url hash="fddb0463">2021.semeval-1.135</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.135</doi>
      <bibkey>hossain-etal-2021-csecu</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="136">
      <title><fixed-case>UTNLP</fixed-case> at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 5: A Comparative Analysis of Toxic Span Detection using Attention-based, Named Entity Recognition, and Ensemble Models</title>
      <author><first>Alireza</first><last>Salemi</last></author>
      <author><first>Nazanin</first><last>Sabri</last></author>
      <author><first>Emad</first><last>Kebriaei</last></author>
      <author><first>Behnam</first><last>Bahrak</last></author>
      <author><first>Azadeh</first><last>Shakery</last></author>
      <pages>995–1002</pages>
      <abstract>Detecting which parts of a sentence contribute to that sentence’s toxicity—rather than providing a sentence-level verdict of hatefulness— would increase the interpretability of models and allow human moderators to better understand the outputs of the system. This paper presents our team’s, UTNLP, methodology and results in the SemEval-2021 shared task 5 on toxic spans detection. We test multiple models and contextual embeddings and report the best setting out of all. The experiments start with keyword-based models and are followed by attention-based, named entity- based, transformers-based, and ensemble models. Our best approach, an ensemble model, achieves an F1 of 0.684 in the competition’s evaluation phase.</abstract>
      <url hash="75e8984e">2021.semeval-1.136</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.136</doi>
      <bibkey>salemi-etal-2021-utnlp</bibkey>
      <pwccode url="https://github.com/alirezasalemi7/SemEval2021-Toxic-Spans-Detection" additional="false">alirezasalemi7/SemEval2021-Toxic-Spans-Detection</pwccode>
      <pwcdataset url="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/civil-comments">Civil Comments</pwcdataset>
    </paper>
    <paper id="137">
      <title>macech at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 5: Toxic Spans Detection</title>
      <author><first>Maggie</first><last>Cech</last></author>
      <pages>1003–1008</pages>
      <abstract>Toxic language is often present in online forums, especially when politics and other polarizing topics arise, and can lead to people becoming discouraged from joining or continuing conversations. In this paper, we use data consisting of comments with the indices of toxic text labelled to train an RNN to deter-mine which parts of the comments make them toxic, which could aid online moderators. We compare results using both the original dataset and an augmented set, as well as GRU versus LSTM RNN models.</abstract>
      <url hash="e419f8d2">2021.semeval-1.137</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.137</doi>
      <bibkey>cech-2021-macech</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="138">
      <title><fixed-case>LZ</fixed-case>1904 at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 5: <fixed-case>B</fixed-case>i-<fixed-case>LSTM</fixed-case>-<fixed-case>CRF</fixed-case> for Toxic Span Detection using Pretrained Word Embedding</title>
      <author><first>Liang</first><last>Zou</last></author>
      <author><first>Wen</first><last>Li</last></author>
      <pages>1009–1014</pages>
      <abstract>Recurrent Neural Networks (RNN) have been widely used in various Natural Language Processing (NLP) tasks such as text classification, sequence tagging, and machine translation. Long Short Term Memory (LSTM), a special unit of RNN, has the benefit of memorizing past and even future information in a sentence (especially for bidirectional LSTM). In the shared task of detecting spans which make texts toxic, we first apply pretrained word embedding (GloVe) to generate the word vectors after tokenization. And then we construct Bidirectional Long Short Term Memory-Conditional Random Field (Bi-LSTM-CRF) model by Baidu research to predict whether each word in the sentence is toxic or not. We tune hyperparameters of dropout rate, number of LSTM units, embedding size with 10 epochs and choose the best epoch with validation recall. Our model achieves an F1 score of 66.99 percent in test dataset.</abstract>
      <url hash="8530cac2">2021.semeval-1.138</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.138</doi>
      <bibkey>zou-li-2021-lz1904</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="139">
      <title><fixed-case>LIIR</fixed-case> at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 task 6: Detection of Persuasion Techniques In Texts and Images using <fixed-case>CLIP</fixed-case> features</title>
      <author><first>Erfan</first><last>Ghadery</last></author>
      <author><first>Damien</first><last>Sileo</last></author>
      <author><first>Marie-Francine</first><last>Moens</last></author>
      <pages>1015–1019</pages>
      <abstract>We describe our approach for SemEval-2021 task 6 on detection of persuasion techniques in multimodal content (memes). Our system combines pretrained multimodal models (CLIP) and chained classifiers. Also, we propose to enrich the data by a data augmentation technique. Our submission achieves a rank of 8/16 in terms of F1-micro and 9/16 with F1-macro on the test set.</abstract>
      <url hash="e4638769">2021.semeval-1.139</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.139</doi>
      <bibkey>ghadery-etal-2021-liir</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="140">
      <title><fixed-case>AIMH</fixed-case> at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 6: Multimodal Classification Using an Ensemble of Transformer Models</title>
      <author><first>Nicola</first><last>Messina</last></author>
      <author><first>Fabrizio</first><last>Falchi</last></author>
      <author><first>Claudio</first><last>Gennaro</last></author>
      <author><first>Giuseppe</first><last>Amato</last></author>
      <pages>1020–1026</pages>
      <abstract>This paper describes the system used by the AIMH Team to approach the SemEval Task 6. We propose an approach that relies on an architecture based on the transformer model to process multimodal content (text and images) in memes. Our architecture, called DVTT (Double Visual Textual Transformer), approaches Subtasks 1 and 3 of Task 6 as multi-label classification problems, where the text and/or images of the meme are processed, and the probabilities of the presence of each possible persuasion technique are returned as a result. DVTT uses two complete networks of transformers that work on text and images that are mutually conditioned. One of the two modalities acts as the main one and the second one intervenes to enrich the first one, thus obtaining two distinct ways of operation. The two transformers outputs are merged by averaging the inferred probabilities for each possible label, and the overall network is trained end-to-end with a binary cross-entropy loss.</abstract>
      <url hash="b93fad50">2021.semeval-1.140</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.140</doi>
      <bibkey>messina-etal-2021-aimh</bibkey>
      <pwccode url="https://github.com/mesnico/memepersuasiondetection" additional="false">mesnico/memepersuasiondetection</pwccode>
    </paper>
    <paper id="141">
      <title><fixed-case>HOMADOS</fixed-case> at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 6: Multi-Task Learning for Propaganda Detection</title>
      <author><first>Konrad</first><last>Kaczyński</last></author>
      <author><first>Piotr</first><last>Przybyła</last></author>
      <pages>1027–1031</pages>
      <abstract>Among the tasks motivated by the proliferation of misinformation, propaganda detection is particularly challenging due to the deficit of fine-grained manual annotations required to train machine learning models. Here we show how data from other related tasks, including credibility assessment, can be leveraged in multi-task learning (MTL) framework to accelerate the training process. To that end, we design a BERT-based model with multiple output layers, train it in several MTL scenarios and perform evaluation against the SemEval gold standard.</abstract>
      <url hash="9f976e42">2021.semeval-1.141</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.141</doi>
      <bibkey>kaczynski-przybyla-2021-homados</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="142">
      <title>1213<fixed-case>L</fixed-case>i at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 6: Detection of Propaganda with Multi-modal Attention and Pre-trained Models</title>
      <author><first>Peiguang</first><last>Li</last></author>
      <author><first>Xuan</first><last>Li</last></author>
      <author><first>Xian</first><last>Sun</last></author>
      <pages>1032–1036</pages>
      <abstract>This paper presents the solution proposed by the 1213Li team for subtask 3 in SemEval-2021 Task 6: identifying the multiple persuasion techniques used in the multi-modal content of the meme. We explored various approaches in feature extraction and the detection of persuasion labels. Our final model employs pre-trained models including RoBERTa and ResNet-50 as a feature extractor for texts and images, respectively, and adopts a label embedding layer with multi-modal attention mechanism to measure the similarity of labels with the multi-modal information and fuse features for label prediction. Our proposed method outperforms the provided baseline method and achieves 3rd out of 16 participants with 0.54860/0.22830 for Micro/Macro F1 scores.</abstract>
      <url hash="80a3f25e">2021.semeval-1.142</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.142</doi>
      <bibkey>li-etal-2021-1213li</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="143">
      <title><fixed-case>NL</fixed-case>ytics<fixed-case>FKIE</fixed-case> at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 6: Detection of Persuasion Techniques In Texts And Images</title>
      <author><first>Albert</first><last>Pritzkau</last></author>
      <pages>1037–1044</pages>
      <abstract>The following system description presents our approach to the detection of persuasion techniques in texts and images. The given task has been framed as a multi-label classification problem with the different techniques serving as class labels. The multi-label classification problem is one in which a list of target variables such as our class labels is associated with every input chunk and assumes that a document can simultaneously and independently be assigned to multiple labels or classes. In order to assign class labels to the given memes, we opted for RoBERTa (A Robustly Optimized BERT Pretraining Approach) as a neural network architecture for token and sequence classification. Starting off with a pre-trained model for language representation we fine-tuned this model on the given classification task with the provided annotated data in supervised training steps. To incorporate image features in the multi-modal setting, we rely on the pre-trained VGG-16 model architecture.</abstract>
      <url hash="169b5893">2021.semeval-1.143</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.143</doi>
      <bibkey>pritzkau-2021-nlyticsfkie</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="144">
      <title><fixed-case>YNU</fixed-case>-<fixed-case>HPCC</fixed-case> at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 6: Combining <fixed-case>ALBERT</fixed-case> and Text-<fixed-case>CNN</fixed-case> for Persuasion Detection in Texts and Images</title>
      <author><first>Xingyu</first><last>Zhu</last></author>
      <author><first>Jin</first><last>Wang</last></author>
      <author><first>Xuejie</first><last>Zhang</last></author>
      <pages>1045–1050</pages>
      <abstract>In recent years, memes combining image and text have been widely used in social media, and memes are one of the most popular types of content used in online disinformation campaigns. In this paper, our study on the detection of persuasion techniques in texts and images in SemEval-2021 Task 6 is summarized. For propaganda technology detection in text, we propose a combination model of both ALBERT and Text CNN for text classification, as well as a BERT-based multi-task sequence labeling model for propaganda technology coverage span detection. For the meme classification task involved in text understanding and visual feature extraction, we designed a parallel channel model divided into text and image channels. Our method achieved a good performance on subtasks 1 and 3. The micro F1-scores of 0.492, 0.091, and 0.446 achieved on the test sets of the three subtasks ranked 12th, 7th, and 11th, respectively, and all are higher than the baseline model.</abstract>
      <url hash="2c64dfa5">2021.semeval-1.144</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.144</doi>
      <bibkey>zhu-etal-2021-ynu</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="145">
      <title><fixed-case>LT</fixed-case>3 at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 6: Using Multi-Modal Compact Bilinear Pooling to Combine Visual and Textual Understanding in Memes</title>
      <author><first>Pranaydeep</first><last>Singh</last></author>
      <author><first>Els</first><last>Lefever</last></author>
      <pages>1051–1055</pages>
      <abstract>Internet memes have become ubiquitous in social media networks today. Due to their popularity, they are also a widely used mode of expression to spread disinformation online. As memes consist of a mixture of text and image, they require a multi-modal approach for automatic analysis. In this paper, we describe our contribution to the SemEval-2021 Detection of Persuasian Techniques in Texts and Images Task. We propose a Multi-Modal learning system, which incorporates “memebeddings”, viz. joint text and vision features by combining them with compact bilinear pooling, to automatically identify rhetorical and psychological disinformation techniques. The experimental results show that the proposed system constantly outperforms the competition’s baseline, and achieves the 2nd best Macro F1-score and 14th best Micro F1-score out of all participants.</abstract>
      <url hash="3eddf6b9">2021.semeval-1.145</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.145</doi>
      <bibkey>singh-lefever-2021-lt3</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="146">
      <title><fixed-case>FPAI</fixed-case> at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 6: <fixed-case>BERT</fixed-case>-<fixed-case>MRC</fixed-case> for Propaganda Techniques Detection</title>
      <author><first>Xiaolong</first><last>Hou</last></author>
      <author><first>Junsong</first><last>Ren</last></author>
      <author><first>Gang</first><last>Rao</last></author>
      <author><first>Lianxin</first><last>Lian</last></author>
      <author><first>Zhihao</first><last>Ruan</last></author>
      <author><first>Yang</first><last>Mo</last></author>
      <author><first>JIanping</first><last>Shen</last></author>
      <pages>1056–1060</pages>
      <abstract>The objective of subtask 2 of SemEval-2021 Task 6 is to identify techniques used together with the span(s) of text covered by each technique. This paper describes the system and model we developed for the task. We first propose a pipeline system to identify spans, then to classify the technique in the input sequence. But it severely suffers from handling the overlapping in nested span. Then we propose to formulize the task as a question answering task by MRC framework which achieves a better result compared to the pipeline method. Moreover, data augmentation and loss design techniques are also explored to alleviate the problem of data sparse and imbalance. Finally, we attain the 3rd place in the final evaluation phase.</abstract>
      <url hash="ca4fe49f">2021.semeval-1.146</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.146</doi>
      <bibkey>hou-etal-2021-fpai</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="147">
      <title><fixed-case>NLPIITR</fixed-case> at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 6: <fixed-case>R</fixed-case>o<fixed-case>BERT</fixed-case>a Model with Data Augmentation for Persuasion Techniques Detection</title>
      <author><first>Vansh</first><last>Gupta</last></author>
      <author><first>Raksha</first><last>Sharma</last></author>
      <pages>1061–1067</pages>
      <abstract>This paper describes and examines different systems to address Task 6 of SemEval-2021: Detection of Persuasion Techniques In Texts And Images, Subtask 1. The task aims to build a model for identifying rhetorical and psycho- logical techniques (such as causal oversimplification, name-calling, smear) in the textual content of a meme which is often used in a disinformation campaign to influence the users. The paper provides an extensive comparison among various machine learning systems as a solution to the task. We elaborate on the pre-processing of the text data in favor of the task and present ways to overcome the class imbalance. The results show that fine-tuning a RoBERTa model gave the best results with an F1-Micro score of 0.51 on the development set.</abstract>
      <url hash="df07c2ca">2021.semeval-1.147</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.147</doi>
      <bibkey>gupta-sharma-2021-nlpiitr</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="148">
      <title><fixed-case>L</fixed-case>e<fixed-case>C</fixed-case>un at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 6: Detecting Persuasion Techniques in Text Using Ensembled Pretrained Transformers and Data Augmentation</title>
      <author><first>Dia</first><last>Abujaber</last></author>
      <author><first>Ahmed</first><last>Qarqaz</last></author>
      <author><first>Malak A.</first><last>Abdullah</last></author>
      <pages>1068–1074</pages>
      <abstract>We developed a system for task 6 sub-task 1 for detecting propaganda in memes. An external dataset and augmentation data-set were used to extend the official competition data-set. Data augmentation techniques were applied on the external data-set and competition data-set to come up with the augmented data-set. We trained 5 transformers (DeBERTa, and 4 RoBERTa) and ensembled them to make the prediction. We trained 1 RoBERTa model initially on the augmented data-set for a few epochs and then fine-tuned it on the competition data-set which improved the f1-micro up to 0.1 scores. After that, another initial RoBERTa model was trained on the external data-set merged with the augmented data-set for few epochs and fine-tuned it on the competition data-set. Furthermore, we ensembled the initial models with the models after fine-tuning. For the final model in the ensemble, we trained a DeBERTa model on the augmented data-set without fine-tuning it on the competition data-set. Finally, we averaged the output of each model in the ensemble to make the prediction.</abstract>
      <url hash="538434bc">2021.semeval-1.148</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.148</doi>
      <bibkey>abujaber-etal-2021-lecun</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="149">
      <title><fixed-case>V</fixed-case>olta at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 6: Towards Detecting Persuasive Texts and Images using Textual and Multimodal Ensemble</title>
      <author><first>Kshitij</first><last>Gupta</last></author>
      <author><first>Devansh</first><last>Gautam</last></author>
      <author><first>Radhika</first><last>Mamidi</last></author>
      <pages>1075–1081</pages>
      <abstract>Memes are one of the most popular types of content used to spread information online. They can influence a large number of people through rhetorical and psychological techniques. The task, Detection of Persuasion Techniques in Texts and Images, is to detect these persuasive techniques in memes. It consists of three subtasks: (A) Multi-label classification using textual content, (B) Multi-label classification and span identification using textual content, and (C) Multi-label classification using visual and textual content. In this paper, we propose a transfer learning approach to fine-tune BERT-based models in different modalities. We also explore the effectiveness of ensembles of models trained in different modalities. We achieve an F1-score of 57.0, 48.2, and 52.1 in the corresponding subtasks.</abstract>
      <url hash="6cf09dbe">2021.semeval-1.149</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.149</doi>
      <bibkey>gupta-etal-2021-volta</bibkey>
      <pwccode url="https://github.com/kshitij98/multimodal-propaganda" additional="false">kshitij98/multimodal-propaganda</pwccode>
    </paper>
    <paper id="150">
      <title><fixed-case>M</fixed-case>in<fixed-case>D</fixed-case> at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 6: Propaganda Detection using Transfer Learning and Multimodal Fusion</title>
      <author><first>Junfeng</first><last>Tian</last></author>
      <author><first>Min</first><last>Gui</last></author>
      <author><first>Chenliang</first><last>Li</last></author>
      <author><first>Ming</first><last>Yan</last></author>
      <author><first>Wenming</first><last>Xiao</last></author>
      <pages>1082–1087</pages>
      <abstract>We describe our systems of subtask1 and subtask3 for SemEval-2021 Task 6 on Detection of Persuasion Techniques in Texts and Images. The purpose of subtask1 is to identify propaganda techniques given textual content, and the goal of subtask3 is to detect them given both textual and visual content. For subtask1, we investigate transfer learning based on pre-trained language models (PLMs) such as BERT, RoBERTa to solve data sparsity problems. For subtask3, we extract heterogeneous visual representations (i.e., face features, OCR features, and multimodal representations) and explore various multimodal fusion strategies to combine the textual and visual representations. The official evaluation shows our ensemble model ranks 1st for subtask1 and 2nd for subtask3.</abstract>
      <url hash="11e6eb23">2021.semeval-1.150</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.150</doi>
      <bibkey>tian-etal-2021-mind</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="151">
      <title><fixed-case>CSECU</fixed-case>-<fixed-case>DSG</fixed-case> at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 6: Orchestrating Multimodal Neural Architectures for Identifying Persuasion Techniques in Texts and Images</title>
      <author><first>Tashin</first><last>Hossain</last></author>
      <author><first>Jannatun</first><last>Naim</last></author>
      <author><first>Fareen</first><last>Tasneem</last></author>
      <author><first>Radiathun</first><last>Tasnia</last></author>
      <author><first>Abu Nowshed</first><last>Chy</last></author>
      <pages>1088–1095</pages>
      <abstract>Inscribing persuasion techniques in memes is the most impactful way to influence peoples’ mindsets. People are more inclined to memes as they are more stimulating and convincing and hence memes are often exploited by tactfully engraving propaganda in its context with the intent of attaining specific agenda. This paper describes our participation in the three subtasks featured by SemEval 2021 task 6 on the detection of persuasion techniques in texts and images. We utilize a fusion of logistic regression, decision tree, and fine-tuned DistilBERT for tackling subtask 1. As for subtask 2, we propose a system that consolidates a span identification model and a multi-label classification model based on pre-trained BERT. We address the multi-modal multi-label classification of memes defined in subtask 3 by utilizing a ResNet50 based image model, DistilBERT based text model, and a multi-modal architecture based on multikernel CNN+LSTM and MLP model. The outcomes illustrated the competitive performance of our systems.</abstract>
      <url hash="4fbd2a9b">2021.semeval-1.151</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.151</doi>
      <bibkey>hossain-etal-2021-csecu-dsg</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="152">
      <title><fixed-case>UMUT</fixed-case>eam at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 7: Detecting and Rating Humor and Offense with Linguistic Features and Word Embeddings</title>
      <author><first>José Antonio</first><last>García-Díaz</last></author>
      <author><first>Rafael</first><last>Valencia-García</last></author>
      <pages>1096–1101</pages>
      <abstract>In writing, humor is mainly based on figurative language in which words and expressions change their conventional meaning to refer to something without saying it directly. This flip in the meaning of the words prevents Natural Language Processing from revealing the real intention of a communication and, therefore, reduces the effectiveness of tasks such as Sentiment Analysis or Emotion Detection. In this manuscript we describe the participation of the UMUTeam in HaHackathon 2021, whose objective is to detect and rate humorous and controversial content. Our proposal is based on the combination of linguistic features with contextual and non-contextual word embeddings. We participate in all the proposed subtasks achieving our best result in the controversial humor subtask.</abstract>
      <url hash="74fe961f">2021.semeval-1.152</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.152</doi>
      <bibkey>garcia-diaz-valencia-garcia-2021-umuteam</bibkey>
      <pwccode url="https://github.com/smolky/hahackathon-2021" additional="false">smolky/hahackathon-2021</pwccode>
    </paper>
    <paper id="153">
      <title><fixed-case>ES</fixed-case>-<fixed-case>JUST</fixed-case> at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 7: Detecting and Rating Humor and Offensive Text Using Deep Learning</title>
      <author><first>Emran</first><last>Al Bashabsheh</last></author>
      <author><first>Sanaa</first><last>Abu Alasal</last></author>
      <pages>1102–1107</pages>
      <abstract>This research presents the work of the team’s ES-JUST at semEval-2021 task 7 for detecting and rating humor and offensive text using deep learning. The team evaluates several approaches (<i>i.e.Bert, Roberta, XLM-Roberta, and Bert embedding + Bi-LSTM</i>) that employ in four sub-tasks. The first sub-task deal with whether the text is humorous or not. The second sub-task is the degree of humor in the text if the first sub-task is humorous. The third sub-task represents the text is controversial or not if it is humorous. While in the last task is the degree of an offensive in the text. However, Roberta pre-trained model outperforms other approaches and score the highest in all sub-tasks. We rank on the leader board at the evaluation phase are 14, 15, 20, and 5 through 0.9564 F-score, 0.5709 RMSE, 0.4888 F-score, and 0.4467 RMSE results, respectively, for each of the first, second, third, and fourth sub-task, respectively.</abstract>
      <url hash="77c8076d">2021.semeval-1.153</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.153</doi>
      <bibkey>al-bashabsheh-abu-alasal-2021-es</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="154">
      <title>Tsia at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 7: Detecting and Rating Humor and Offense</title>
      <author><first>Zhengyi</first><last>Guan</last></author>
      <author><first>Xiaobing ZXB</first><last>Zhou</last></author>
      <pages>1108–1113</pages>
      <abstract>This paper describes our contribution to SemEval-2021 Task 7: Detecting and Rating Humor and Of-fense.This task contains two sub-tasks, sub-task 1and sub-task 2. Among them, sub-task 1 containsthree sub-tasks, sub-task 1a ,sub-task 1b and sub-task 1c.Sub-task 1a is to predict if the text would beconsidered humorous. Sub-task 1c is described asfollows: if the text is classed as humorous, predictif the humor rating would be considered controver-sial, i.e. the variance of the rating between annota-tors is higher than the median.we combined threepre-trained model with CNN to complete these twoclassification sub-tasks. Sub-task 1b is to judge thedegree of humor. Sub-task 2 aims to predict how of-fensive a text would be with values between 0 and5.We use the idea of regression to deal with thesetwo sub-tasks. We analyze the performance of ourmethod and demonstrate the contribution of eachcomponent of our architecture. We have achievedgood results under the combination of multiple pre-training models and optimization methods.</abstract>
      <url hash="e4e56018">2021.semeval-1.154</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.154</doi>
      <bibkey>guan-zhou-2021-tsia</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="155">
      <title><fixed-case>DLJUST</fixed-case> at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 7: Hahackathon: Linking Humor and Offense</title>
      <author><first>Hani</first><last>Al-Omari</last></author>
      <author><first>Isra’a</first><last>AbedulNabi</last></author>
      <author><first>Rehab</first><last>Duwairi</last></author>
      <pages>1114–1119</pages>
      <abstract>Humor detection and rating poses interesting linguistic challenges to NLP; it is highly subjective depending on the perceptions of a joke and the context in which it is used. This paper utilizes and compares transformers models; BERT base and Large, BERTweet, RoBERTa base and Large, and RoBERTa base irony, for detecting and rating humor and offense. The proposed models, where given a text in cased and uncased type obtained from SemEval-2021 Task7: HaHackathon: Linking Humor and Offense Across Different Age Groups. The highest scored model for the first subtask: Humor Detection, is BERTweet base cased model with 0.9540 F1-score, for the second subtask: Average Humor Rating Score, it is BERT Large cased with the minimum RMSE of 0.5555, for the fourth subtask: Average Offensiveness Rating Score, it is BERTweet base cased model with minimum RMSE of 0.4822.</abstract>
      <url hash="c334075f">2021.semeval-1.155</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.155</doi>
      <bibkey>al-omari-etal-2021-dljust</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="156">
      <title><fixed-case>G</fixed-case>ulu at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 7: Detecting and Rating Humor and Offense</title>
      <author><first>Maoqin</first><last>Yang</last></author>
      <pages>1120–1124</pages>
      <abstract>Humor recognition is a challenging task in natural language processing. This document presents my approaches to detect and rate humor and offense from the given text. This task includes 2 tasks: task 1 which contains 3 subtasks (1a, 1b, and 1c), and task 2. Subtask 1a and 1c can be regarded as classification problems and take ALBERT as the basic model. Subtask 1b and 2 can be viewed as regression issues and take RoBERTa as the basic model.</abstract>
      <url hash="e9fb19db">2021.semeval-1.156</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.156</doi>
      <bibkey>yang-2021-gulu</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="157">
      <title><fixed-case>DUTH</fixed-case> at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 7: Is Conventional Machine Learning for Humorous and Offensive Tasks enough in 2021?</title>
      <author><first>Alexandros</first><last>Karasakalidis</last></author>
      <author><first>Dimitrios</first><last>Effrosynidis</last></author>
      <author><first>Avi</first><last>Arampatzis</last></author>
      <pages>1125–1129</pages>
      <abstract>This paper describes the approach that was developed for SemEval 2021 Task 7 (Hahackathon: Incorporating Demographic Factors into Shared Humor Tasks) by the DUTH Team. We used and compared a variety of preprocessing techniques, vectorization methods, and numerous conventional machine learning algorithms, in order to construct classification and regression models for the given tasks. We used majority voting to combine the models’ outputs with small Neural Networks (NN) for classification tasks and their mean for regression for improving our system’s performance. While these methods proved weaker than modern, deep learning models, they are still relevant in research tasks because of their low requirements on computational power and faster training.</abstract>
      <url hash="2c56ce44">2021.semeval-1.157</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.157</doi>
      <bibkey>karasakalidis-etal-2021-duth</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="158">
      <title><fixed-case>D</fixed-case>eep<fixed-case>B</fixed-case>lue<fixed-case>AI</fixed-case> at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 7: Detecting and Rating Humor and Offense with Stacking Diverse Language Model-Based Methods</title>
      <author><first>Bingyan</first><last>Song</last></author>
      <author><first>Chunguang</first><last>Pan</last></author>
      <author><first>Shengguang</first><last>Wang</last></author>
      <author><first>Zhipeng</first><last>Luo</last></author>
      <pages>1130–1134</pages>
      <abstract>This paper describes the winning system for SemEval-2021 Task 7: Detecting and Rating Humor and Offense. Our strategy is stacking diverse pre-trained language models (PLMs) such as RoBERTa and ALBERT. We first perform fine-tuning on these two PLMs with various hyperparameters and different training strategies. Then a valid stacking mechanism is applied on top of the fine-tuned PLMs to get the final prediction. Experimental results on the dataset released by the organizer of the task show the validity of our method and we win first place and third place for subtask 2 and 1a.</abstract>
      <url hash="bbd914d3">2021.semeval-1.158</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.158</doi>
      <bibkey>song-etal-2021-deepblueai-semeval</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="159">
      <title><fixed-case>CS</fixed-case>-<fixed-case>UM</fixed-case>6<fixed-case>P</fixed-case> at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 7: Deep Multi-Task Learning Model for Detecting and Rating Humor and Offense</title>
      <author><first>Kabil</first><last>Essefar</last></author>
      <author><first>Abdellah</first><last>El Mekki</last></author>
      <author><first>Abdelkader</first><last>El Mahdaouy</last></author>
      <author><first>Nabil</first><last>El Mamoun</last></author>
      <author><first>Ismail</first><last>Berrada</last></author>
      <pages>1135–1140</pages>
      <abstract>Humor detection has become a topic of interest for several research teams, especially those involved in socio-psychological studies, with the aim to detect the humor and the temper of a targeted population (e.g. a community, a city, a country, the employees of a given company). Most of the existing studies have formulated the humor detection problem as a binary classification task, whereas it revolves around learning the sense of humor by evaluating its different degrees. In this paper, we propose an end-to-end deep Multi-Task Learning (MTL) model to detect and rate humor and offense. It consists of a pre-trained transformer encoder and task-specific attention layers. The model is trained using MTL uncertainty loss weighting to adaptively combine all sub-tasks objective functions. Our MTL model tackles all sub-tasks of the SemEval-2021 Task-7 in one end-to-end deep learning system and shows very promising results.</abstract>
      <url hash="fab56d7c">2021.semeval-1.159</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.159</doi>
      <bibkey>essefar-etal-2021-cs</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="160">
      <title>hub at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 7: Fusion of <fixed-case>ALBERT</fixed-case> and Word Frequency Information Detecting and Rating Humor and Offense</title>
      <author><first>Bo</first><last>Huang</last></author>
      <author><first>Yang</first><last>Bai</last></author>
      <pages>1141–1145</pages>
      <abstract>This paper introduces the system description of the hub team, which explains the related work and experimental results of our team’s participation in SemEval 2021 Task 7: HaHackathon: Detecting and Rating Humor and Offense. We successfully submitted the test set prediction results of the two subtasks in the task. The goal of the task is to perform humor detection, grade evaluation, and offensive evaluation on each English text data in the data set. Tasks can be divided into two types of subtasks. One is a text classification task, and the other is a text regression task. What we need to do is to use our method to detect the humor and offensive information of the sentence as accurately as possible. The methods used in the results submitted by our team are mainly composed of ALBERT, CNN, and Tf-Idf algorithms. The result evaluation indicators submitted by the classification task are F1 score and Accuracy. The result evaluation index of the regression task submission is the RMSE. The final scores of the prediction results of the two subtask test sets submitted by our team are task1a 0.921 (F1), task1a 0.9364 (Accuracy), task1b 0.6288 (RMSE), task1c 0.5333 (F1), task1c 0.0.5591 (Accuracy), and task2 0.5027 (RMSE) respectively.</abstract>
      <url hash="eb0b169b">2021.semeval-1.160</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.160</doi>
      <bibkey>huang-bai-2021-hub-semeval</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="161">
      <title><fixed-case>Y</fixed-case>oung<fixed-case>S</fixed-case>heldon at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 7: Fine-tuning Is All You Need</title>
      <author><first>Mayukh</first><last>Sharma</last></author>
      <author><first>Ilanthenral</first><last>Kandasamy</last></author>
      <author><first>W.b.</first><last>Vasantha</last></author>
      <pages>1146–1152</pages>
      <abstract>In this paper, we describe our system used for SemEval 2021 Task 7: HaHackathon: Detecting and Rating Humor and Offense. We used a simple fine-tuning approach using different Pre-trained Language Models (PLMs) to evaluate their performance for humor and offense detection. For regression tasks, we averaged the scores of different models leading to better performance than the original models. We participated in all SubTasks. Our best performing system was ranked 4 in SubTask 1-b, 8 in SubTask 1-c, 12 in SubTask 2, and performed well in SubTask 1-a. We further show comprehensive results using different pre-trained language models which will help as baselines for future work.</abstract>
      <url hash="1c690e48">2021.semeval-1.161</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.161</doi>
      <bibkey>sharma-etal-2021-youngsheldon-semeval</bibkey>
      <pwccode url="https://github.com/04mayukh/YoungSheldon-at-SemEval-2021-Task-7-HaHackathon" additional="false">04mayukh/YoungSheldon-at-SemEval-2021-Task-7-HaHackathon</pwccode>
    </paper>
    <paper id="162">
      <title><fixed-case>M</fixed-case>agic<fixed-case>P</fixed-case>ai at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 7: Method for Detecting and Rating Humor Based on Multi-Task Adversarial Training</title>
      <author><first>Jian</first><last>Ma</last></author>
      <author><first>Shuyi</first><last>Xie</last></author>
      <author><first>Haiqin</first><last>Yang</last></author>
      <author><first>Lianxin</first><last>Jiang</last></author>
      <author><first>Mengyuan</first><last>Zhou</last></author>
      <author><first>Xiaoyi</first><last>Ruan</last></author>
      <author><first>Yang</first><last>Mo</last></author>
      <pages>1153–1159</pages>
      <abstract>This paper describes MagicPai’s system for SemEval 2021 Task 7, HaHackathon: Detecting and Rating Humor and Offense. This task aims to detect whether the text is humorous and how humorous it is. There are four subtasks in the competition. In this paper, we mainly present our solution, a multi-task learning model based on adversarial examples, for task 1a and 1b. More specifically, we first vectorize the cleaned dataset and add the perturbation to obtain more robust embedding representations. We then correct the loss via the confidence level. Finally, we perform interactive joint learning on multiple tasks to capture the relationship between whether the text is humorous and how humorous it is. The final result shows the effectiveness of our system.</abstract>
      <url hash="e209a487">2021.semeval-1.162</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.162</doi>
      <bibkey>ma-etal-2021-magicpai</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="163">
      <title><fixed-case>UPB</fixed-case> at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 7: Adversarial Multi-Task Learning for Detecting and Rating Humor and Offense</title>
      <author><first>Răzvan-Alexandru</first><last>Smădu</last></author>
      <author><first>Dumitru-Clementin</first><last>Cercel</last></author>
      <author><first>Mihai</first><last>Dascalu</last></author>
      <pages>1160–1168</pages>
      <abstract>Detecting humor is a challenging task since words might share multiple valences and, depending on the context, the same words can be even used in offensive expressions. Neural network architectures based on Transformer obtain state-of-the-art results on several Natural Language Processing tasks, especially text classification. Adversarial learning, combined with other techniques such as multi-task learning, aids neural models learn the intrinsic properties of data. In this work, we describe our adversarial multi-task network, AMTL-Humor, used to detect and rate humor and offensive texts from Task 7 at SemEval-2021. Each branch from the model is focused on solving a related task, and consists of a BiLSTM layer followed by Capsule layers, on top of BERTweet used for generating contextualized embeddings. Our best model consists of an ensemble of all tested configurations, and achieves a 95.66% F1-score and 94.70% accuracy for Task 1a, while obtaining RMSE scores of 0.6200 and 0.5318 for Tasks 1b and 2, respectively.</abstract>
      <url hash="a0864d8b">2021.semeval-1.163</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.163</doi>
      <bibkey>smadu-etal-2021-upb</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="164">
      <title><fixed-case>T</fixed-case>eam_<fixed-case>KGP</fixed-case> at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 7: A Deep Neural System to Detect Humor and Offense with Their Ratings in the Text Data</title>
      <author><first>Anik</first><last>Mondal</last></author>
      <author><first>Raksha</first><last>Sharma</last></author>
      <pages>1169–1174</pages>
      <abstract>This paper describes the system submitted to SemEval-2021 Task-7 for all four subtasks. Two subtasks focus on detecting humor and offense from the text (binary classification). On the other hand, the other two subtasks predict humor and offense ratings of the text (linear regression). In this paper, we present two different types of fine-tuning methods by using linear layers and bi-LSTM layers on top of the pre-trained BERT model. Results show that our system is able to outperform baseline models by a significant margin. We report F1 scores of 0.90 for the first subtask and 0.53 for the third subtask, while we report an RMSE of 0.57 and 0.58 for the second and fourth subtasks, respectively.</abstract>
      <url hash="acd85aeb">2021.semeval-1.164</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.164</doi>
      <bibkey>mondal-sharma-2021-team</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="165">
      <title><fixed-case>ZYJ</fixed-case> at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 7: <fixed-case>H</fixed-case>a<fixed-case>H</fixed-case>ackathon: Detecting and Rating Humor and Offense with <fixed-case>ALBERT</fixed-case>-Based Model</title>
      <author><first>Yingjia</first><last>Zhao</last></author>
      <author><first>Xin</first><last>Tao</last></author>
      <pages>1175–1178</pages>
      <abstract>This article introduces the submission of subtask 1 and subtask 2 that we participate in SemEval-2021 Task 7: HaHackathon: Detecting and Rating Humor and Offense, we use a model based on ALBERT that uses ALBERT as the module for extracting text features. We modify the upper layer structure by adding specific networks to better summarize the semantic information. Finally, our system achieves an F-Score of 0.9348 in subtask 1a, RMSE of 0.7214 in subtask 1b, F-Score of 0.4603 in subtask 1c, and RMSE of 0.5204 in subtask 2.</abstract>
      <url hash="74364edc">2021.semeval-1.165</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.165</doi>
      <bibkey>zhao-tao-2021-zyj-semeval</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="166">
      <title><fixed-case>U</fixed-case>o<fixed-case>R</fixed-case> at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 7: Utilizing Pre-trained <fixed-case>D</fixed-case>istil<fixed-case>BERT</fixed-case> Model and Multi-scale <fixed-case>CNN</fixed-case> for Humor Detection</title>
      <author><first>Zehao</first><last>Liu</last></author>
      <author><first>Carl</first><last>Haines</last></author>
      <author><first>Huizhi</first><last>Liang</last></author>
      <pages>1179–1184</pages>
      <abstract>Humour detection is an interesting but difficult task in NLP. Because humorous might not be obvious in text, it can be embedded into context, hide behind the literal meaning and require prior knowledge to understand. We explored different shallow and deep methods to create a humour detection classifier for task 7-1a. Models like Logistic Regression, LSTM, MLP, CNN were used, and pre-trained models like DistilBert were introduced to generate accurate vector representation for textual data. We focused on applying multi-scale strategy on modelling, and compared different models. Our best model is the DistilBERT+MultiScale CNN, it used different sizes of CNN kernel to get multiple scales of features, which achieved 93.7% F1-score and 92.1% accuracy on the test set.</abstract>
      <url hash="ab13b8d1">2021.semeval-1.166</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.166</doi>
      <bibkey>liu-etal-2021-uor</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="167">
      <title><fixed-case>TECHSSN</fixed-case> at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 7: Humor and Offense detection and classification using <fixed-case>C</fixed-case>ol<fixed-case>BERT</fixed-case> embeddings</title>
      <author><first>Rajalakshmi</first><last>Sivanaiah</last></author>
      <author><first>Angel Deborah</first><last>S</last></author>
      <author><first>S Milton</first><last>Rajendram</last></author>
      <author><first>Mirnalinee</first><last>Tt</last></author>
      <author><first>Abrit Pal</first><last>Singh</last></author>
      <author><first>Aviansh</first><last>Gupta</last></author>
      <author><first>Ayush</first><last>Nanda</last></author>
      <pages>1185–1189</pages>
      <abstract>This paper describes the system used for detecting humor in text. The system developed by the team TECHSSN uses binary classification techniques to classify the text. The data undergoes preprocessing and is given to ColBERT (Contextualized Late Interaction over BERT), a modification of Bidirectional Encoder Representations from Transformers (BERT). The model is re-trained and the weights are learned for the dataset. This system was developed for the task 7 of the competition, SemEval 2021.</abstract>
      <url hash="5a2abb24">2021.semeval-1.167</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.167</doi>
      <bibkey>sivanaiah-etal-2021-techssn</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="168">
      <title>Amherst685 at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 7: Joint Modeling of Classification and Regression for Humor and Offense</title>
      <author><first>Brian</first><last>Zylich</last></author>
      <author><first>Akshay</first><last>Gugnani</last></author>
      <author><first>Gabriel</first><last>Brookman</last></author>
      <author><first>Nicholas</first><last>Samoray</last></author>
      <pages>1190–1195</pages>
      <abstract>This paper describes our submission to theSemEval’21: Task 7- HaHackathon: Detecting and Rating Humor and Offense. In this challenge, we explore intermediate finetuning, backtranslation augmentation, multitask learning, and ensembling of different language models. Curiously, intermediate finetuning and backtranslation do not improve performance, while multitask learning and ensembling do improve performance. We explore why intermediate finetuning and backtranslation do not provide the same benefit as other natural language processing tasks and offer insight into the errors that our model makes. Our best performing system ranks 7th on Task 1bwith an RMSE of 0.5339</abstract>
      <url hash="3bf96a57">2021.semeval-1.168</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.168</doi>
      <bibkey>zylich-etal-2021-amherst685</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="169">
      <title><fixed-case>D</fixed-case>uluth<fixed-case>NLP</fixed-case> at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 7: Fine-Tuning <fixed-case>R</fixed-case>o<fixed-case>BERT</fixed-case>a Model for Humor Detection and Offense Rating</title>
      <author><first>Samuel</first><last>Akrah</last></author>
      <pages>1196–1203</pages>
      <abstract>This paper presents the DuluthNLP submission to Task 7 of the SemEval 2021 competition on Detecting and Rating Humor and Offense. In it, we explain the approach used to train the model together with the process of fine-tuning our model in getting the results. We focus on humor detection, rating, and of-fense rating, representing three out of the four subtasks that were provided. We show that optimizing hyper-parameters for learning rate, batch size and number of epochs can increase the accuracy and F1 score for humor detection</abstract>
      <url hash="43c79325">2021.semeval-1.169</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.169</doi>
      <bibkey>akrah-2021-duluthnlp</bibkey>
      <pwccode url="https://github.com/akrahdan/semeval2021" additional="false">akrahdan/semeval2021</pwccode>
    </paper>
    <paper id="170">
      <title><fixed-case>CSECU</fixed-case>-<fixed-case>DSG</fixed-case> at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 7: Detecting and Rating Humor and Offense Employing Transformers</title>
      <author><first>Afrin</first><last>Sultana</last></author>
      <author><first>Nabila</first><last>Ayman</last></author>
      <author><first>Abu Nowshed</first><last>Chy</last></author>
      <pages>1204–1208</pages>
      <abstract>With the emerging trends of using online platforms, peoples are increasingly interested in express their opinion through humorous texts. Identifying and rating humorous texts poses unique challenges to NLP due to subjective phenomena i.e. humor may vary to gender, profession, age, and classes of people. Besides, words with multiple senses, cultural domain, and pragmatic competence also need to be considered. A humorous text may be offensive to others. To address these challenges SemEval-2021 introduced a HaHackathon task focusing on detecting and rating humorous and offensive texts. This paper describes our participation in this task. We employed a stacked embedding and fine-tuned transformer models based classification and regression approach from the features from GPT2 medium, BERT, and RoBERTa transformer models. Besides, we utilized the fine-tuned BERT and RoBERTa models to examine the performances. Our method achieved competitive performances in this task.</abstract>
      <url hash="1007a806">2021.semeval-1.170</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.170</doi>
      <bibkey>sultana-etal-2021-csecu</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="171">
      <title><fixed-case>R</fixed-case>edwood<fixed-case>NLP</fixed-case> at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 7: Ensembled Pretrained and Lightweight Models for Humor Detection</title>
      <author><first>Nathan</first><last>Chi</last></author>
      <author><first>Ryan</first><last>Chi</last></author>
      <pages>1209–1214</pages>
      <abstract>An understanding of humor is an essential component of human-facing NLP systems. In this paper, we investigate several methods for detecting humor in short statements as part of Semeval-2021 Shared Task 7. For Task 1a, we apply an ensemble of fine-tuned pre-trained language models; for Tasks 1b, 1c, and 2a, we investigate various tree-based and linear machine learning models. Our final system achieves an F1-score of 0.9571 (ranked 24 / 58) on Task 1a, an RMSE of 0.5580 (ranked 18 / 50) on Task 1b, an F1-score of 0.5024 (ranked 26 / 36) on Task 1c, and an RMSE of 0.7229 (ranked 45 / 48) on Task 2a.</abstract>
      <url hash="06895130">2021.semeval-1.171</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.171</doi>
      <bibkey>chi-chi-2021-redwoodnlp</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="172">
      <title><fixed-case>E</fixed-case>nd<fixed-case>T</fixed-case>imes at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 7: Detecting and Rating Humor and Offense with <fixed-case>BERT</fixed-case> and Ensembles</title>
      <author><first>Chandan Kumar</first><last>Pandey</last></author>
      <author><first>Chirag</first><last>Singh</last></author>
      <author><first>Karan</first><last>Mangla</last></author>
      <pages>1215–1220</pages>
      <abstract>This paper describes Humor-BERT, a set of BERT Large based models that we used in the SemEval-2021 Task 7: Detecting and Rating Humor and Offense. It presents pre and post processing techniques, variable threshold learning, meta learning and Ensemble approach to solve various sub-tasks that were part of the challenge. We also present a comparative analysis of various models we tried. Our method was ranked 4th in Humor Controversy Detection, 8th in Humor Detection, 19th in Average Offense Score prediction and 40th in Average Humor Score prediction globally. F1 score obtained for Humor classification was 0.9655 and for Controversy detection it was 0.6261. Our user name on the leader board is ThisIstheEnd and team name is EndTimes.</abstract>
      <url hash="ef655998">2021.semeval-1.172</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.172</doi>
      <bibkey>pandey-etal-2021-endtimes</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="173">
      <title><fixed-case>IIITH</fixed-case> at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 7: Leveraging transformer-based humourous and offensive text detection architectures using lexical and hurtlex features and task adaptive pretraining</title>
      <author><first>Tathagata</first><last>Raha</last></author>
      <author><first>Ishan Sanjeev</first><last>Upadhyay</last></author>
      <author><first>Radhika</first><last>Mamidi</last></author>
      <author><first>Vasudeva</first><last>Varma</last></author>
      <pages>1221–1225</pages>
      <abstract>This paper describes our approach (IIITH) for SemEval-2021 Task 5: HaHackathon: Detecting and Rating Humor and Offense. Our results focus on two major objectives: (i) Effect of task adaptive pretraining on the performance of transformer based models (ii) How does lexical and hurtlex features help in quantifying humour and offense. In this paper, we provide a detailed description of our approach along with comparisions mentioned above.</abstract>
      <url hash="f0067e0d">2021.semeval-1.173</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.173</doi>
      <bibkey>raha-etal-2021-iiith</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="174">
      <title><fixed-case>FII</fixed-case> <fixed-case>FUNNY</fixed-case> at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 7: <fixed-case>H</fixed-case>a<fixed-case>H</fixed-case>ackathon: Detecting and rating Humor and Offense</title>
      <author><first>Mihai</first><last>Samson</last></author>
      <author><first>Daniela</first><last>Gifu</last></author>
      <pages>1226–1231</pages>
      <abstract>The “HaHackathon: Detecting and Rating Humor and Offense” task at the SemEval 2021 competition focuses on detecting and rating the humor level in sentences, as well as the level of offensiveness contained in these texts with humoristic tones. In this paper, we present an approach based on recent Deep Learning techniques by both trying to train the models based on the dataset solely and by trying to fine-tune pre-trained models on the gigantic corpus.</abstract>
      <url hash="9538f099">2021.semeval-1.174</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.174</doi>
      <bibkey>samson-gifu-2021-fii</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="175">
      <title>Counts@<fixed-case>IITK</fixed-case> at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 8: <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>ci<fixed-case>BERT</fixed-case> Based Entity And Semantic Relation Extraction For Scientific Data</title>
      <author><first>Akash</first><last>Gangwar</last></author>
      <author><first>Sabhay</first><last>Jain</last></author>
      <author><first>Shubham</first><last>Sourav</last></author>
      <author><first>Ashutosh</first><last>Modi</last></author>
      <pages>1232–1238</pages>
      <abstract>This paper presents the system for SemEval 2021 Task 8 (MeasEval). MeasEval is a novel span extraction, classification, and relation extraction task focused on finding quantities, attributes of these quantities, and additional information, including the related measured entities, properties, and measurement contexts. Our submitted system, which placed fifth (team rank) on the leaderboard, consisted of SciBERT with [CLS] token embedding and CRF layer on top. We were also placed first in Quantity (tied) and Unit subtasks, second in MeasuredEntity, Modifier and Qualifies subtasks, and third in Qualifier subtask.</abstract>
      <url hash="e9db7ca5">2021.semeval-1.175</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.175</doi>
      <bibkey>gangwar-etal-2021-counts</bibkey>
      <pwccode url="https://github.com/akashgnr31/Counts-And-Measurement" additional="false">akashgnr31/Counts-And-Measurement</pwccode>
    </paper>
    <paper id="176">
      <title><fixed-case>CONNER</fixed-case>: A Cascade Count and Measurement Extraction Tool for Scientific Discourse</title>
      <author><first>Jiarun</first><last>Cao</last></author>
      <author><first>Yuejia</first><last>Xiang</last></author>
      <author><first>Yunyan</first><last>Zhang</last></author>
      <author><first>Zhiyuan</first><last>Qi</last></author>
      <author><first>Xi</first><last>Chen</last></author>
      <author><first>Yefeng</first><last>Zheng</last></author>
      <pages>1239–1244</pages>
      <abstract>This paper presents our wining contribution to SemEval 2021 Task 8: MeasEval. The purpose of this task is identifying the counts and measurements from clinical scientific discourse, including quantities, entities, properties, qualifiers, units, modifiers, and their mutual relations. This task can be induced to a joint entity and relation extraction problem. Accordingly, we propose CONNER, a cascade count and measurement extraction tool that can identify entities and the corresponding relations in a two-step pipeline model. We provide a detailed description of the proposed model hereinafter. Furthermore, the impact of the essential modules and our in-process technical schemes are also investigated.</abstract>
      <url hash="2d1e7f0e">2021.semeval-1.176</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.176</doi>
      <bibkey>cao-etal-2021-conner</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="177">
      <title><fixed-case>S</fixed-case>tanford <fixed-case>ML</fixed-case>ab at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 8: 48 Hours Is All You Need</title>
      <author><first>Patrick</first><last>Liu</last></author>
      <author><first>Niveditha</first><last>Iyer</last></author>
      <author><first>Erik</first><last>Rozi</last></author>
      <author><first>Ethan A.</first><last>Chi</last></author>
      <pages>1245–1248</pages>
      <abstract>This paper presents our system for the Quantity span identification, Unit of measurement identification and Value modifier classification subtasks of the MeasEval 2021 task. The purpose of the Quantity span identification task was to locate spans of text that contain a count or measurement, consisting of a value, usually followed by a unit and occasionally additional modifiers. The goal of the modifier classification task was to determine whether an associated text fragment served to indicate range, tolerance, mean value, etc. of a quantity. The developed systems used pre-trained BERT models which were fine-tuned for the task at hand. We present our system, investigate how architectural decisions affected model predictions, and conduct an error analysis. Overall, our system placed 12 / 19 in the shared task and in the 2nd place for the Unit subcategory.</abstract>
      <url hash="7111f86e">2021.semeval-1.177</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.177</doi>
      <bibkey>liu-etal-2021-stanford</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="178">
      <title><fixed-case>LIORI</fixed-case> at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 8: Ask Transformer for measurements</title>
      <author><first>Adis</first><last>Davletov</last></author>
      <author><first>Denis</first><last>Gordeev</last></author>
      <author><first>Nikolay</first><last>Arefyev</last></author>
      <author><first>Emil</first><last>Davletov</last></author>
      <pages>1249–1254</pages>
      <abstract>This work describes our approach for subtasks of SemEval-2021 Task 8: MeasEval: Counts and Measurements which took the official first place in the competition. To solve all subtasks we use multi-task learning in a question-answering-like manner. We also use learnable scalar weights to weight subtasks’ contribution to the final loss in multi-task training. We fine-tune LUKE to extract quantity spans and we fine-tune RoBERTa to extract everything related to found quantities, including quantities themselves.</abstract>
      <url hash="0300b709">2021.semeval-1.178</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.178</doi>
      <bibkey>davletov-etal-2021-liori-semeval</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="179">
      <title>Sattiy at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 9: An Ensemble Solution for Statement Verification and Evidence Finding with Tables</title>
      <author><first>Xiaoyi</first><last>Ruan</last></author>
      <author><first>Meizhi</first><last>Jin</last></author>
      <author><first>Jian</first><last>Ma</last></author>
      <author><first>Haiqin</first><last>Yang</last></author>
      <author><first>Lianxin</first><last>Jiang</last></author>
      <author><first>Yang</first><last>Mo</last></author>
      <author><first>Mengyuan</first><last>Zhou</last></author>
      <pages>1255–1261</pages>
      <abstract>Question answering from semi-structured tables can be seen as a semantic parsing task and is significant and practical for pushing the boundary of natural language understanding. Existing research mainly focuses on understanding contents from unstructured evidence, e.g., news, natural language sentences and documents. The task of verification from structured evidence, such as tables, charts, and databases, is still less-explored. This paper describes sattiy team’s system in SemEval-2021 task 9: Statement Verification and Evidence Finding with Tables (SEM-TAB-FACT)(CITATION). This competition aims to verify statements and to find evidence from tables for scientific articles and to promote proper interpretation of the surrounding article. In this paper we exploited ensemble models of pre-trained language models over tables, TaPas and TaBERT, for Task A and adjust the result based on some rules extracted for Task B. Finally, in the leadboard, we attain the F1 scores of 0.8496 and 0.7732 in Task A for the 2-way and 3-way evaluation, respectively, and the F1 score of 0.4856 in Task B.</abstract>
      <url hash="0f40cc73">2021.semeval-1.179</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.179</doi>
      <bibkey>ruan-etal-2021-sattiy</bibkey>
      <pwcdataset url="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/tabfact">TabFact</pwcdataset>
      <pwcdataset url="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/wikisql">WikiSQL</pwcdataset>
    </paper>
    <paper id="180">
      <title><fixed-case>V</fixed-case>olta at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 9: Statement Verification and Evidence Finding with Tables using <fixed-case>TAPAS</fixed-case> and Transfer Learning</title>
      <author><first>Devansh</first><last>Gautam</last></author>
      <author><first>Kshitij</first><last>Gupta</last></author>
      <author><first>Manish</first><last>Shrivastava</last></author>
      <pages>1262–1270</pages>
      <abstract>Tables are widely used in various kinds of documents to present information concisely. Understanding tables is a challenging problem that requires an understanding of language and table structure, along with numerical and logical reasoning. In this paper, we present our systems to solve Task 9 of SemEval-2021: Statement Verification and Evidence Finding with Tables (SEM-TAB-FACTS). The task consists of two subtasks: (A) Given a table and a statement, predicting whether the table supports the statement and (B) Predicting which cells in the table provide evidence for/against the statement. We fine-tune TAPAS (a model which extends BERT’s architecture to capture tabular structure) for both the subtasks as it has shown state-of-the-art performance in various table understanding tasks. In subtask A, we evaluate how transfer learning and standardizing tables to have a single header row improves TAPAS’ performance. In subtask B, we evaluate how different fine-tuning strategies can improve TAPAS’ performance. Our systems achieve an F1 score of 67.34 in subtask A three-way classification, 72.89 in subtask A two-way classification, and 62.95 in subtask B.</abstract>
      <url hash="7cb9f3e6">2021.semeval-1.180</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.180</doi>
      <bibkey>gautam-etal-2021-volta</bibkey>
      <pwccode url="https://github.com/devanshg27/sem-tab-fact" additional="false">devanshg27/sem-tab-fact</pwccode>
      <pwcdataset url="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/sqa">SQA</pwcdataset>
      <pwcdataset url="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/tabfact">TabFact</pwcdataset>
      <pwcdataset url="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/wikisql">WikiSQL</pwcdataset>
    </paper>
    <paper id="181">
      <title><fixed-case>K</fixed-case>aushik<fixed-case>A</fixed-case>charya at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 9: Candidate Generation for Fact Verification over Tables</title>
      <author><first>Kaushik</first><last>Acharya</last></author>
      <pages>1271–1275</pages>
      <abstract>This paper describes the system submitted in the SemEval-2021 Statement Verification and Evidence Finding with Tables task. The system relies on candidate generation for logical forms on the table based on keyword matching and dependency parsing on the claim statements.</abstract>
      <url hash="90094ff4">2021.semeval-1.181</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.181</doi>
      <bibkey>acharya-2021-kaushikacharya</bibkey>
      <pwccode url="https://github.com/kaushikacharya/statement_verification_evidence_finding" additional="false">kaushikacharya/statement_verification_evidence_finding</pwccode>
      <pwcdataset url="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/wikitablequestions">WikiTableQuestions</pwcdataset>
    </paper>
    <paper id="182">
      <title><fixed-case>A</fixed-case>ttes<fixed-case>T</fixed-case>able at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 9: Extending Statement Verification with Tables for Unknown Class, and Semantic Evidence Finding</title>
      <author><first>Harshit</first><last>Varma</last></author>
      <author><first>Aadish</first><last>Jain</last></author>
      <author><first>Pratik</first><last>Ratadiya</last></author>
      <author><first>Abhishek</first><last>Rathi</last></author>
      <pages>1276–1282</pages>
      <abstract>This paper describes our approach for Task 9 of SemEval 2021: Statement Verification and Evidence Finding with Tables. We participated in both subtasks, namely statement verification and evidence finding. For the subtask of statement verification, we extend the TAPAS model to adapt to the ‘unknown’ class of statements by finetuning it on an augmented version of the task data. For the subtask of evidence finding, we finetune the DistilBERT model in a Siamese setting.</abstract>
      <url hash="e1a5e779">2021.semeval-1.182</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.182</doi>
      <bibkey>varma-etal-2021-attestable</bibkey>
      <pwccode url="https://github.com/vCreaTek/attestable-semeval" additional="false">vCreaTek/attestable-semeval</pwccode>
      <pwcdataset url="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/multinli">MultiNLI</pwcdataset>
      <pwcdataset url="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/snli">SNLI</pwcdataset>
      <pwcdataset url="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/tabfact">TabFact</pwcdataset>
    </paper>
    <paper id="183">
      <title><fixed-case>M</fixed-case>ed<fixed-case>AI</fixed-case> at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 10: Negation-aware Pre-training for Source-free Negation Detection Domain Adaptation</title>
      <author><first>Jinquan</first><last>Sun</last></author>
      <author><first>Qi</first><last>Zhang</last></author>
      <author><first>Yu</first><last>Wang</last></author>
      <author><first>Lei</first><last>Zhang</last></author>
      <pages>1283–1288</pages>
      <abstract>Due to the increasing concerns for data privacy, source-free unsupervised domain adaptation attracts more and more research attention, where only a trained source model is assumed to be available, while the labeled source data remain private. To get promising adaptation results, we need to find effective ways to transfer knowledge learned in source domain and leverage useful domain specific information from target domain at the same time. This paper describes our winning contribution to SemEval 2021 Task 10: Source-Free Domain Adaptation for Semantic Processing. Our key idea is to leverage the model trained on source domain data to generate pseudo labels for target domain samples. Besides, we propose Negation-aware Pre-training (NAP) to incorporate negation knowledge into model. Our method win the 1st place with F1-score of 0.822 on the official blind test set of Negation Detection Track.</abstract>
      <url hash="bf723f00">2021.semeval-1.183</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.183</doi>
      <bibkey>sun-etal-2021-medai</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="184">
      <title><fixed-case>YNU</fixed-case>-<fixed-case>HPCC</fixed-case> at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 10: Using a Transformer-based Source-Free Domain Adaptation Model for Semantic Processing</title>
      <author><first>Zhewen</first><last>Yu</last></author>
      <author><first>Jin</first><last>Wang</last></author>
      <author><first>Xuejie</first><last>Zhang</last></author>
      <pages>1289–1294</pages>
      <abstract>Data sharing restrictions are common in NLP datasets. The purpose of this task is to develop a model trained in a source domain to make predictions for a target domain with related domain data. To address the issue, the organizers provided the models that fine-tuned a large number of source domain data on pre-trained models and the dev data for participants. But the source domain data was not distributed. This paper describes the provided model to the NER (Name entity recognition) task and the ways to develop the model. As a little data provided, pre-trained models are suitable to solve the cross-domain tasks. The models fine-tuned by large number of another domain could be effective in new domain because the task had no change.</abstract>
      <url hash="6d99ab08">2021.semeval-1.184</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.184</doi>
      <bibkey>yu-etal-2021-ynu</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="185">
      <title><fixed-case>ECNUICA</fixed-case> at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 11: Rule based Information Extraction Pipeline</title>
      <author><first>Jiaju</first><last>Lin</last></author>
      <author><first>Jing</first><last>Ling</last></author>
      <author><first>Zhiwei</first><last>Wang</last></author>
      <author><first>Jiawei</first><last>Liu</last></author>
      <author><first>Qin</first><last>Chen</last></author>
      <author><first>Liang</first><last>He</last></author>
      <pages>1295–1302</pages>
      <abstract>This paper presents our endeavor for solving task11, NLPContributionGraph, of SemEval-2021. The purpose of the task was to extract triples from a paper in the Nature Language Processing field for constructing an Open Research Knowledge Graph. The task includes three sub-tasks: detecting the contribution sentences in papers, identifying scientific terms and predicate phrases from the contribution sentences; and inferring triples in the form of (subject, predicate, object) as statements for Knowledge Graph building. In this paper, we apply an ensemble of various fine-tuned pre-trained language models (PLM) for tasks one and two. In addition, self-training methods are adopted for tackling the shortage of annotated data. For the third task, rather than using classic neural open information extraction (OIE) architectures, we generate potential triples via manually designed rules and develop a binary classifier to differentiate positive ones from others. The quantitative results show that we obtain the 4th, 2nd, and 2nd rank in three evaluation phases.</abstract>
      <url hash="c985bc92">2021.semeval-1.185</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.185</doi>
      <bibkey>lin-etal-2021-ecnuica</bibkey>
      <pwcdataset url="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/semeval-2021-task-11-nlpcontributiongraph">SemEval-2021 Task-11</pwcdataset>
    </paper>
    <paper id="186">
      <title><fixed-case>UOR</fixed-case> at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>em<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>val-2021 Task 12: On Crowd Annotations; Learning with Disagreements to optimise crowd truth</title>
      <author><first>Emmanuel</first><last>Osei-Brefo</last></author>
      <author><first>Thanet</first><last>Markchom</last></author>
      <author><first>Huizhi</first><last>Liang</last></author>
      <pages>1303–1309</pages>
      <abstract>Crowdsourcing has been ubiquitously used for annotating enormous collections of data. However, the major obstacles to using crowd-sourced labels are noise and errors from non-expert annotations. In this work, two approaches dealing with the noise and errors in crowd-sourced labels are proposed. The first approach uses Sharpness-Aware Minimization (SAM), an optimization technique robust to noisy labels. The other approach leverages a neural network layer called softmax-Crowdlayer specifically designed to learn from crowd-sourced annotations. According to the results, the proposed approaches can improve the performance of the Wide Residual Network model and Multi-layer Perception model applied on crowd-sourced datasets in the image processing domain. It also has similar and comparable results with the majority voting technique when applied to the sequential data domain whereby the Bidirectional Encoder Representations from Transformers (BERT) is used as the base model in both instances.</abstract>
      <url hash="2fd78e6c">2021.semeval-1.186</url>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2021.semeval-1.186</doi>
      <bibkey>osei-brefo-etal-2021-uor</bibkey>
    </paper>
  </volume>
</collection>
