<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<collection id="2022.dadc">
  <volume id="1" ingest-date="2022-06-29" type="proceedings">
    <meta>
      <booktitle>Proceedings of the First Workshop on Dynamic Adversarial Data Collection</booktitle>
      <editor><first>Max</first><last>Bartolo</last></editor>
      <editor><first>Hannah</first><last>Kirk</last></editor>
      <editor><first>Pedro</first><last>Rodriguez</last></editor>
      <editor><first>Katerina</first><last>Margatina</last></editor>
      <editor><first>Tristan</first><last>Thrush</last></editor>
      <editor><first>Robin</first><last>Jia</last></editor>
      <editor><first>Pontus</first><last>Stenetorp</last></editor>
      <editor><first>Adina</first><last>Williams</last></editor>
      <editor><first>Douwe</first><last>Kiela</last></editor>
      <publisher>Association for Computational Linguistics</publisher>
      <address>Seattle, WA</address>
      <month>July</month>
      <year>2022</year>
      <url hash="8e1dd949">2022.dadc-1</url>
      <venue>dadc</venue>
    </meta>
    <frontmatter>
      <url hash="81f7e087">2022.dadc-1.0</url>
      <bibkey>dadc-2022-dynamic</bibkey>
    </frontmatter>
    <paper id="1">
      <title>Resilience of Named Entity Recognition Models under Adversarial Attack</title>
      <author><first>Sudeshna</first><last>Das</last></author>
      <author><first>Jiaul</first><last>Paik</last></author>
      <pages>1-6</pages>
      <abstract>Named entity recognition (NER) is a popular language processing task with wide applications. Progress in NER has been noteworthy, as evidenced by the F1 scores obtained on standard datasets. In practice, however, the end-user uses an NER model on their dataset out-of-the-box, on text that may not be pristine. In this paper we present four model-agnostic adversarial attacks to gauge the resilience of NER models in such scenarios. Our experiments on four state-of-the-art NER methods with five English datasets suggest that the NER models are over-reliant on case information and do not utilise contextual information well. As such, they are highly susceptible to adversarial attacks based on these features.</abstract>
      <url hash="4b1b6e70">2022.dadc-1.1</url>
      <bibkey>das-paik-2022-resilience</bibkey>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2022.dadc-1.1</doi>
      <pwccode url="https://github.com/das-sudeshna/adversarial-ner" additional="false">das-sudeshna/adversarial-ner</pwccode>
      <pwcdataset url="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/conll-2003">CoNLL 2003</pwcdataset>
    </paper>
    <paper id="2">
      <title><fixed-case>G</fixed-case>rease<fixed-case>V</fixed-case>ision: Rewriting the Rules of the Interface</title>
      <author><first>Siddhartha</first><last>Datta</last></author>
      <author><first>Konrad</first><last>Kollnig</last></author>
      <author><first>Nigel</first><last>Shadbolt</last></author>
      <pages>7-22</pages>
      <abstract>Digital harms can manifest across any interface. Key problems in addressing these harms include the high individuality of harms and the fast-changing nature of digital systems. We put forth GreaseVision, a collaborative human-in-the-loop learning framework that enables end-users to analyze their screenomes to annotate harms as well as render overlay interventions. We evaluate HITL intervention development with a set of completed tasks in a cognitive walkthrough, and test scalability with one-shot element removal and fine-tuning hate speech classification models. The contribution of the framework and tool allow individual end-users to study their usage history and create personalized interventions. Our contribution also enables researchers to study the distribution of multi-modal harms and interventions at scale.</abstract>
      <url hash="326235f6">2022.dadc-1.2</url>
      <bibkey>datta-etal-2022-greasevision</bibkey>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2022.dadc-1.2</doi>
      <video href="2022.dadc-1.2.mp4"/>
    </paper>
    <paper id="3">
      <title>Posthoc Verification and the Fallibility of the Ground Truth</title>
      <author><first>Yifan</first><last>Ding</last></author>
      <author><first>Nicholas</first><last>Botzer</last></author>
      <author><first>Tim</first><last>Weninger</last></author>
      <pages>23-29</pages>
      <abstract>Classifiers commonly make use of pre-annotated datasets, wherein a model is evaluated by pre-defined metrics on a held-out test set typically made of human-annotated labels. Metrics used in these evaluations are tied to the availability of well-defined ground truth labels, and these metrics typically do not allow for inexact matches. These noisy ground truth labels and strict evaluation metrics may compromise the validity and realism of evaluation results. In the present work, we conduct a systematic label verification experiment on the entity linking (EL) task. Specifically, we ask annotators to verify the correctness of annotations after the fact (, posthoc). Compared to pre-annotation evaluation, state-of-the-art EL models performed extremely well according to the posthoc evaluation methodology. Surprisingly, we find predictions from EL models had a similar or higher verification rate than the ground truth. We conclude with a discussion on these findings and recommendations for future evaluations. The source code, raw results, and evaluation scripts are publicly available via the MIT license at <url>https://github.com/yifding/e2e_EL_evaluate</url></abstract>
      <url hash="69e8ba6a">2022.dadc-1.3</url>
      <bibkey>ding-etal-2022-posthoc</bibkey>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2022.dadc-1.3</doi>
      <pwccode url="https://github.com/yifding/e2e_EL_evaluate" additional="false">yifding/e2e_EL_evaluate</pwccode>
    </paper>
    <paper id="4">
      <title>Overconfidence in the Face of Ambiguity with Adversarial Data</title>
      <author><first>Margaret</first><last>Li</last></author>
      <author><first>Julian</first><last>Michael</last></author>
      <pages>30-40</pages>
      <abstract>Adversarial data collection has shown promise as a method for building models which are more robust to the spurious correlations that generally appear in naturalistic data. However, adversarially-collected data may itself be subject to biases, particularly with regard to ambiguous or arguable labeling judgments. Searching for examples where an annotator disagrees with a model might over-sample ambiguous inputs, and filtering the results for high inter-annotator agreement may under-sample them. In either case, training a model on such data may produce predictable and unwanted biases. In this work, we investigate whether models trained on adversarially-collected data are miscalibrated with respect to the ambiguity of their inputs. Using Natural Language Inference models as a testbed, we find no clear difference in accuracy between naturalistically and adversarially trained models, but our model trained only on adversarially-sourced data is considerably more overconfident of its predictions and demonstrates worse calibration, especially on ambiguous inputs. This effect is mitigated, however, when naturalistic and adversarial training data are combined.</abstract>
      <url hash="cfea1be9">2022.dadc-1.4</url>
      <bibkey>li-michael-2022-overconfidence</bibkey>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2022.dadc-1.4</doi>
      <pwccode url="https://github.com/julianmichael/aeae" additional="false">julianmichael/aeae</pwccode>
      <pwcdataset url="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/anli">ANLI</pwcdataset>
      <pwcdataset url="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/chaosnli">ChaosNLI</pwcdataset>
      <pwcdataset url="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/multinli">MultiNLI</pwcdataset>
    </paper>
    <paper id="5">
      <title>longhorns at <fixed-case>DADC</fixed-case> 2022: How many linguists does it take to fool a Question Answering model? A systematic approach to adversarial attacks.</title>
      <author><first>Venelin</first><last>Kovatchev</last></author>
      <author><first>Trina</first><last>Chatterjee</last></author>
      <author><first>Venkata S</first><last>Govindarajan</last></author>
      <author><first>Jifan</first><last>Chen</last></author>
      <author><first>Eunsol</first><last>Choi</last></author>
      <author><first>Gabriella</first><last>Chronis</last></author>
      <author><first>Anubrata</first><last>Das</last></author>
      <author><first>Katrin</first><last>Erk</last></author>
      <author><first>Matthew</first><last>Lease</last></author>
      <author><first>Junyi Jessy</first><last>Li</last></author>
      <author><first>Yating</first><last>Wu</last></author>
      <author><first>Kyle</first><last>Mahowald</last></author>
      <pages>41-52</pages>
      <abstract>Developing methods to adversarially challenge NLP systems is a promising avenue for improving both model performance and interpretability. Here, we describe the approach of the team “longhorns” on Task 1 of the The First Workshop on Dynamic Adversarial Data Collection (DADC), which asked teams to manually fool a model on an Extractive Question Answering task. Our team finished first (pending validation), with a model error rate of 62%. We advocate for a systematic, linguistically informed approach to formulating adversarial questions, and we describe the results of our pilot experiments, as well as our official submission.</abstract>
      <url hash="abcce460">2022.dadc-1.5</url>
      <bibkey>kovatchev-etal-2022-longhorns</bibkey>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2022.dadc-1.5</doi>
    </paper>
    <paper id="6">
      <title>Collecting high-quality adversarial data for machine reading comprehension tasks with humans and models in the loop</title>
      <author><first>Damian Y.</first><last>Romero Diaz</last></author>
      <author><first>Magdalena</first><last>Anioł</last></author>
      <author><first>John</first><last>Culnan</last></author>
      <pages>53-60</pages>
      <abstract>We present our experience as annotators in the creation of high-quality, adversarial machine-reading-comprehension data for extractive QA for Task 1 of the First Workshop on Dynamic Adversarial Data Collection (DADC). DADC is an emergent data collection paradigm with both models and humans in the loop. We set up a quasi-experimental annotation design and perform quantitative analyses across groups with different numbers of annotators focusing on successful adversarial attacks, cost analysis, and annotator confidence correlation. We further perform a qualitative analysis of our perceived difficulty of the task given the different topics of the passages in our dataset and conclude with recommendations and suggestions that might be of value to people working on future DADC tasks and related annotation interfaces.</abstract>
      <url hash="7d734bc4">2022.dadc-1.6</url>
      <bibkey>romero-diaz-etal-2022-collecting</bibkey>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2022.dadc-1.6</doi>
    </paper>
    <paper id="7">
      <title>Generalized Quantifiers as a Source of Error in Multilingual <fixed-case>NLU</fixed-case> Benchmarks</title>
      <author><first>Ruixiang</first><last>Cui</last></author>
      <author><first>Daniel</first><last>Hershcovich</last></author>
      <author><first>Anders</first><last>Søgaard</last></author>
      <pages>61-61</pages>
      <abstract>Logical approaches to representing language have developed and evaluated computational models of quantifier words since the 19th century, but today’s NLU models still struggle to capture their semantics. We rely on Generalized Quantifier Theory for language-independent representations of the semantics of quantifier words, to quantify their contribution to the errors of NLU models. We find that quantifiers are pervasive in NLU benchmarks, and their occurrence at test time is associated with performance drops. Multilingual models also exhibit unsatisfying quantifier reasoning abilities, but not necessarily worse for non-English languages. To facilitate directly-targeted probing, we present an adversarial generalized quantifier NLI task (GQNLI) and show that pre-trained language models have a clear lack of robustness in generalized quantifier reasoning.</abstract>
      <url hash="e516bbdc">2022.dadc-1.7</url>
      <bibkey>cui-etal-2022-generalized</bibkey>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2022.dadc-1.7</doi>
      <video href="2022.dadc-1.7.mp4"/>
      <pwccode url="https://github.com/ruixiangcui/gqnli" additional="false">ruixiangcui/gqnli</pwccode>
      <pwcdataset url="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/anli">ANLI</pwcdataset>
      <pwcdataset url="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/mlqa">MLQA</pwcdataset>
      <pwcdataset url="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/multinli">MultiNLI</pwcdataset>
      <pwcdataset url="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/snli">SNLI</pwcdataset>
      <pwcdataset url="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/taxinli">TaxiNLI</pwcdataset>
      <pwcdataset url="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/xnli">XNLI</pwcdataset>
      <pwcdataset url="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/xquad">XQuAD</pwcdataset>
    </paper>
    <paper id="8">
      <title>Adversarially Constructed Evaluation Sets Are More Challenging, but May Not Be Fair</title>
      <author><first>Jason</first><last>Phang</last></author>
      <author><first>Angelica</first><last>Chen</last></author>
      <author><first>William</first><last>Huang</last></author>
      <author><first>Samuel R.</first><last>Bowman</last></author>
      <pages>62-62</pages>
      <abstract>Large language models increasingly saturate existing task benchmarks, in some cases outperforming humans, leaving little headroom with which to measure further progress. Adversarial dataset creation, which builds datasets using examples that a target system outputs incorrect predictions for, has been proposed as a strategy to construct more challenging datasets, avoiding the more serious challenge of building more precise benchmarks by conventional means. In this work, we study the impact of applying three common approaches for adversarial dataset creation: (1) filtering out easy examples (AFLite), (2) perturbing examples (TextFooler), and (3) model-in-the-loop data collection (ANLI and AdversarialQA), across 18 different adversary models. We find that all three methods can produce more challenging datasets, with stronger adversary models lowering the performance of evaluated models more. However, the resulting ranking of the evaluated models can also be unstable and highly sensitive to the choice of adversary model. Moreover, we find that AFLite oversamples examples with low annotator agreement, meaning that model comparisons hinge on the examples that are most contentious for humans. We recommend that researchers tread carefully when using adversarial methods for building evaluation datasets.</abstract>
      <url hash="8ab06218">2022.dadc-1.8</url>
      <bibkey>phang-etal-2022-adversarially</bibkey>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2022.dadc-1.8</doi>
      <pwcdataset url="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/anli">ANLI</pwcdataset>
      <pwcdataset url="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/adversarialqa">AdversarialQA</pwcdataset>
      <pwcdataset url="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/cosmosqa">CosmosQA</pwcdataset>
      <pwcdataset url="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/glue">GLUE</pwcdataset>
      <pwcdataset url="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/multinli">MultiNLI</pwcdataset>
      <pwcdataset url="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/snli">SNLI</pwcdataset>
      <pwcdataset url="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/squad">SQuAD</pwcdataset>
      <pwcdataset url="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/swag">SWAG</pwcdataset>
    </paper>
  </volume>
</collection>
