<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<collection id="2022.pandl">
  <volume id="1" ingest-date="2022-10-06" type="proceedings">
    <meta>
      <booktitle>Proceedings of the First Workshop on Pattern-based Approaches to NLP in the Age of Deep Learning</booktitle>
      <editor><first>Laura</first><last>Chiticariu</last></editor>
      <editor><first>Yoav</first><last>Goldberg</last></editor>
      <editor><first>Gus</first><last>Hahn-Powell</last></editor>
      <editor><first>Clayton T.</first><last>Morrison</last></editor>
      <editor><first>Aakanksha</first><last>Naik</last></editor>
      <editor><first>Rebecca</first><last>Sharp</last></editor>
      <editor><first>Mihai</first><last>Surdeanu</last></editor>
      <editor><first>Marco</first><last>Valenzuela-Escárcega</last></editor>
      <editor><first>Enrique</first><last>Noriega-Atala</last></editor>
      <publisher>International Conference on Computational Linguistics</publisher>
      <address>Gyeongju, Republic of Korea</address>
      <month>October</month>
      <year>2022</year>
      <url hash="442ee0d9">2022.pandl-1</url>
      <venue>pandl</venue>
    </meta>
    <frontmatter>
      <url hash="7575f417">2022.pandl-1.0</url>
      <bibkey>pandl-2022-pattern</bibkey>
    </frontmatter>
    <paper id="1">
      <title><fixed-case>P</fixed-case>attern<fixed-case>R</fixed-case>ank: Jointly Ranking Patterns and Extractions for Relation Extraction Using Graph-Based Algorithms</title>
      <author><first>Robert</first><last>Vacareanu</last></author>
      <author><first>Dane</first><last>Bell</last></author>
      <author><first>Mihai</first><last>Surdeanu</last></author>
      <pages>1–10</pages>
      <abstract>In this paper we revisit the direction of using lexico-syntactic patterns for relation extraction instead of today’s ubiquitous neural classifiers. We propose a semi-supervised graph-based algorithm for pattern acquisition that scores patterns and the relations they extract jointly, using a variant of PageRank. We insert light supervision in the form of seed patterns or relations, and model it with several custom teleportation probabilities that bias random-walk scores of patterns/relations based on their proximity to correct information. We evaluate our approach on Few-Shot TACRED, and show that our method outperforms (or performs competitively with) more expensive and opaque deep neural networks. Lastly, we thoroughly compare our proposed approach with the seminal RlogF pattern acquisition algorithm of, showing that it outperforms it for all the hyper parameters tested, in all settings.</abstract>
      <url hash="71ec03d0">2022.pandl-1.1</url>
      <bibkey>vacareanu-etal-2022-patternrank</bibkey>
      <pwcdataset url="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/tacred">TACRED</pwcdataset>
    </paper>
    <paper id="2">
      <title>Key Information Extraction in Purchase Documents using Deep Learning and Rule-based Corrections</title>
      <author><first>Roberto</first><last>Arroyo</last></author>
      <author><first>Javier</first><last>Yebes</last></author>
      <author><first>Elena</first><last>Martínez</last></author>
      <author><first>Héctor</first><last>Corrales</last></author>
      <author><first>Javier</first><last>Lorenzo</last></author>
      <pages>11–20</pages>
      <abstract>Deep Learning (DL) is dominating the fields of Natural Language Processing (NLP) and Computer Vision (CV) in the recent times. However, DL commonly relies on the availability of large data annotations, so other alternative or complementary pattern-based techniques can help to improve results. In this paper, we build upon Key Information Extraction (KIE) in purchase documents using both DL and rule-based corrections. Our system initially trusts on Optical Character Recognition (OCR) and text understanding based on entity tagging to identify purchase facts of interest (e.g., product codes, descriptions, quantities, or prices). These facts are then linked to a same product group, which is recognized by means of line detection and some grouping heuristics. Once these DL approaches are processed, we contribute several mechanisms consisting of rule-based corrections for improving the baseline DL predictions. We prove the enhancements provided by these rule-based corrections over the baseline DL results in the presented experiments for purchase documents from public and NielsenIQ datasets.</abstract>
      <url hash="8e82ff19">2022.pandl-1.2</url>
      <bibkey>arroyo-etal-2022-key</bibkey>
      <pwcdataset url="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/cord">CORD</pwcdataset>
      <pwcdataset url="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/funsd">FUNSD</pwcdataset>
      <pwcdataset url="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/sroie">SROIE</pwcdataset>
    </paper>
    <paper id="3">
      <title>Unsupervised Generation of Long-form Technical Questions from Textbook Metadata using Structured Templates</title>
      <author><first>Indrajit</first><last>Bhattacharya</last></author>
      <author><first>Subhasish</first><last>Ghosh</last></author>
      <author><first>Arpita</first><last>Kundu</last></author>
      <author><first>Pratik</first><last>Saini</last></author>
      <author><first>Tapas</first><last>Nayak</last></author>
      <pages>21–28</pages>
      <abstract>We explore the task of generating long-form technical questions from textbooks. Semi-structured metadata of a textbook — the table of contents and the index — provide rich cues for technical question generation. Existing literature for long-form question generation focuses mostly on reading comprehension assessment, and does not use semi-structured metadata for question generation. We design unsupervised template based algorithms for generating questions based on structural and contextual patterns in the index and ToC. We evaluate our approach on textbooks on diverse subjects and show that our approach generates high quality questions of diverse types. We show that, in comparison, zero-shot question generation using pre-trained LLMs on the same meta-data has much poorer quality.</abstract>
      <url hash="24dfe152">2022.pandl-1.3</url>
      <bibkey>bhattacharya-etal-2022-unsupervised</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="4">
      <title>Building <fixed-case>K</fixed-case>orean Linguistic Resource for <fixed-case>NLU</fixed-case> Data Generation of Banking App <fixed-case>CS</fixed-case> Dialog System</title>
      <author><first>Jeongwoo</first><last>Yoon</last></author>
      <author><first>Onyu</first><last>Park</last></author>
      <author><first>Changhoe</first><last>Hwang</last></author>
      <author><first>Gwanghoon</first><last>Yoo</last></author>
      <author><first>Eric</first><last>Laporte</last></author>
      <author><first>Jeesun</first><last>Nam</last></author>
      <pages>29–37</pages>
      <abstract>Natural language understanding (NLU) is integral to task-oriented dialog systems, but demands a considerable amount of annotated training data to increase the coverage of diverse utterances. In this study, we report the construction of a linguistic resource named FIAD (Financial Annotated Dataset) and its use to generate a Korean annotated training data for NLU in the banking customer service (CS) domain. By an empirical examination of a corpus of banking app reviews, we identified three linguistic patterns occurring in Korean request utterances: TOPIC (ENTITY, FEATURE), EVENT, and DISCOURSE MARKER. We represented them in LGGs (Local Grammar Graphs) to generate annotated data covering diverse intents and entities. To assess the practicality of the resource, we evaluate the performances of DIET-only (Intent: 0.91 /Topic [entity+feature]: 0.83), DIET+ HANBERT (I:0.94/T:0.85), DIET+ KoBERT (I:0.94/T:0.86), and DIET+ KorBERT (I:0.95/T:0.84) models trained on FIAD-generated data to extract various types of semantic items.</abstract>
      <url hash="33c130c4">2022.pandl-1.4</url>
      <bibkey>yoon-etal-2022-building</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="5">
      <title><fixed-case>SSP</fixed-case>-Based Construction of Evaluation-Annotated Data for Fine-Grained Aspect-Based Sentiment Analysis</title>
      <author><first>Suwon</first><last>Choi</last></author>
      <author><first>Shinwoo</first><last>Kim</last></author>
      <author><first>Changhoe</first><last>Hwang</last></author>
      <author><first>Gwanghoon</first><last>Yoo</last></author>
      <author><first>Eric</first><last>Laporte</last></author>
      <author><first>Jeesun</first><last>Nam</last></author>
      <pages>38–44</pages>
      <abstract>We report the construction of a Korean evaluation-annotated corpus, hereafter called ‘Evaluation Annotated Dataset (EVAD)’, and its use in Aspect-Based Sentiment Analysis (ABSA) extended in order to cover e-commerce reviews containing sentiment and non-sentiment linguistic patterns. The annotation process uses Semi-Automatic Symbolic Propagation (SSP). We built extensive linguistic resources formalized as a Finite-State Transducer (FST) to annotate corpora with detailed ABSA components in the fashion e-commerce domain. The ABSA approach is extended, in order to analyze user opinions more accurately and extract more detailed features of targets, by including aspect values in addition to topics and aspects, and by classifying aspect-value pairs depending whether values are unary, binary, or multiple. For evaluation, the KoBERT and KcBERT models are trained on the annotated dataset, showing robust performances of F1 0.88 and F1 0.90, respectively, on recognition of aspect-value pairs.</abstract>
      <url hash="6d491d07">2022.pandl-1.5</url>
      <bibkey>choi-etal-2022-ssp</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="6">
      <title>Accelerating Human Authorship of Information Extraction Rules</title>
      <author><first>Dayne</first><last>Freitag</last></author>
      <author><first>John</first><last>Cadigan</last></author>
      <author><first>John</first><last>Niekrasz</last></author>
      <author><first>Robert</first><last>Sasseen</last></author>
      <pages>45–55</pages>
      <abstract>We consider whether machine models can facilitate the human development of rule sets for information extraction. Arguing that rule-based methods possess a speed advantage in the early development of new extraction capabilities, we ask whether this advantage can be increased further through the machine facilitation of common recurring manual operations in the creation of an extraction rule set from scratch. Using a historical rule set, we reconstruct and describe the putative manual operations required to create it. In experiments targeting one key operation—the enumeration of words occurring in particular contexts—we simulate the process or corpus review and word list creation, showing that several simple interventions greatly improve recall as a function of simulated labor.</abstract>
      <url hash="473719b0">2022.pandl-1.6</url>
      <bibkey>freitag-etal-2022-accelerating</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="7">
      <title>Syntax-driven Data Augmentation for Named Entity Recognition</title>
      <author><first>Arie</first><last>Sutiono</last></author>
      <author><first>Gus</first><last>Hahn-Powell</last></author>
      <pages>56–60</pages>
      <abstract>In low resource settings, data augmentation strategies are commonly leveraged to improve performance. Numerous approaches have attempted document-level augmentation (e.g., text classification), but few studies have explored token-level augmentation. Performed naively, data augmentation can produce semantically incongruent and ungrammatical examples. In this work, we compare simple masked language model replacement and an augmentation method using constituency tree mutations to improve the performance of named entity recognition in low-resource settings with the aim of preserving linguistic cohesion of the augmented sentences.</abstract>
      <url hash="5e37bcb1">2022.pandl-1.7</url>
      <bibkey>sutiono-hahn-powell-2022-syntax</bibkey>
      <pwccode url="https://github.com/ariepratama/syntax-driven-da" additional="false">ariepratama/syntax-driven-da</pwccode>
    </paper>
    <paper id="8">
      <title>Query Processing and Optimization for a Custom Retrieval Language</title>
      <author><first>Yakov</first><last>Kuzin</last></author>
      <author><first>Anna</first><last>Smirnova</last></author>
      <author><first>Evgeniy</first><last>Slobodkin</last></author>
      <author><first>George</first><last>Chernishev</last></author>
      <pages>61–70</pages>
      <abstract>Data annotation has been a pressing issue ever since the rise of machine learning and associated areas. It is well-known that obtaining high-quality annotated data incurs high costs, be they financial or time-related. In our previous work, we have proposed a custom, SQL-like retrieval language used to query collections of short documents, such as chat transcripts or tweets. Its main purpose is enabling a human annotator to select “situations” from such collections, i.e. subsets of documents that are related both thematically and temporally. This language, named Matcher, was prototyped in our custom annotation tool. Entering the next stage of development of the tool, we have tested the prototype implementation. Given the language’s rich semantics, many possible execution options with various costs arise. We have found out we could provide tangible improvement in terms of speed and memory consumption by carefully selecting the execution strategy in each particular case. In this work, we present the improved algorithms and proposed optimization methods, as well as a benchmark suite whose results show the significance of the presented techniques. While this is an initial work and not a full-fledged optimization framework, it nevertheless yields good results, providing up to tenfold improvement.</abstract>
      <url hash="1d841eba">2022.pandl-1.8</url>
      <bibkey>kuzin-etal-2022-query</bibkey>
      <pwccode url="https://github.com/yakovypg/chat-corpora-annotator" additional="false">yakovypg/chat-corpora-annotator</pwccode>
    </paper>
    <paper id="9">
      <title>Rule Based Event Extraction for Artificial Social Intelligence</title>
      <author><first>Remo</first><last>Nitschke</last></author>
      <author><first>Yuwei</first><last>Wang</last></author>
      <author><first>Chen</first><last>Chen</last></author>
      <author><first>Adarsh</first><last>Pyarelal</last></author>
      <author><first>Rebecca</first><last>Sharp</last></author>
      <pages>71–84</pages>
      <abstract>Natural language (as opposed to structured communication modes such as Morse code) is by far the most common mode of communication between humans, and can thus provide significant insight into both individual mental states and interpersonal dynamics. As part of DARPA’s Artificial Social Intelligence for Successful Teams (ASIST) program, we are developing an AI agent team member that constructs and maintains models of their human teammates and provides appropriate task-relevant advice to improve team processes and mission performance. One of the key components of this agent is a module that uses a rule-based approach to extract task-relevant events from natural language utterances in real time, and publish them for consumption by downstream components. In this case study, we evaluate the performance of our rule-based event extraction system on a recently conducted ASIST experiment consisting of a simulated urban search and rescue mission in Minecraft. We compare the performance of our approach with that of a zero-shot neural classifier, and find that our approach outperforms the classifier for all event types, even when the classifier is used in an oracle setting where it knows how many events should be extracted from each utterance.</abstract>
      <url hash="8c5a7bfa">2022.pandl-1.9</url>
      <bibkey>nitschke-etal-2022-rule</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="10">
      <title>Neural-Guided Program Synthesis of Information Extraction Rules Using Self-Supervision</title>
      <author><first>Enrique</first><last>Noriega-Atala</last></author>
      <author><first>Robert</first><last>Vacareanu</last></author>
      <author><first>Gus</first><last>Hahn-Powell</last></author>
      <author><first>Marco A.</first><last>Valenzuela-Escárcega</last></author>
      <pages>85–93</pages>
      <abstract>We propose a neural-based approach for rule synthesis designed to help bridge the gap between the interpretability, precision and maintainability exhibited by rule-based information extraction systems with the scalability and convenience of statistical information extraction systems. This is achieved by avoiding placing the burden of learning another specialized language on domain experts and instead asking them to provide a small set of examples in the form of highlighted spans of text. We introduce a transformer-based architecture that drives a rule synthesis system that leverages a self-supervised approach for pre-training a large-scale language model complemented by an analysis of different loss functions and aggregation mechanisms for variable length sequences of user-annotated spans of text. The results are encouraging and point to different desirable properties, such as speed and quality, depending on the choice of loss and aggregation method.</abstract>
      <url hash="48b65a94">2022.pandl-1.10</url>
      <bibkey>noriega-atala-etal-2022-neural</bibkey>
    </paper>
  </volume>
</collection>
