<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<collection id="2022.digitam">
  <volume id="1" ingest-date="2022-09-22" type="proceedings">
    <meta>
      <booktitle>Proceedings of the Workshop on Processing Language Variation: Digital Armenian (DigitAm) within the 13th Language Resources and Evaluation Conference</booktitle>
      <editor><first>Victoria</first><last>Khurshudyan</last></editor>
      <editor><first>Nadi</first><last>Tomeh</last></editor>
      <editor><first>Damien</first><last>Nouvel</last></editor>
      <editor><first>Anaid</first><last>Donabedian</last></editor>
      <editor><first>Chahan</first><last>Vidal-Gorene</last></editor>
      <publisher>European Language Resources Association</publisher>
      <address>Marseille, France</address>
      <month>June</month>
      <year>2022</year>
      <url hash="34e1b551">2022.digitam-1</url>
      <venue>digitam</venue>
    </meta>
    <frontmatter>
      <url hash="54f0a744">2022.digitam-1.0</url>
      <bibkey>digitam-2022-processing</bibkey>
      <revision id="1" href="2022.digitam-1.0v1" hash="81279b06"/>
      <revision id="2" href="2022.digitam-1.0v2" hash="54f0a744" date="2022-11-04">Updated papers 1.3 and 1.4.</revision>
    </frontmatter>
    <paper id="1">
      <title>A Free/Open-Source Morphological Transducer for <fixed-case>W</fixed-case>estern <fixed-case>A</fixed-case>rmenian</title>
      <author><first>Hossep</first><last>Dolatian</last></author>
      <author><first>Daniel</first><last>Swanson</last></author>
      <author><first>Jonathan</first><last>Washington</last></author>
      <pages>1–7</pages>
      <abstract>We present a free/open-source morphological transducer for Western Armenian, an endangered and low-resource Indo-European language. The transducer has virtually complete coverage of the language’s inflectional morphology. We built the lexicon by scraping online dictionaries. As of submission, the transducer has a lexicon of 75K words. It has over 90% naive coverage on different Western Armenian corpora, and high precision.</abstract>
      <url hash="513528e1">2022.digitam-1.1</url>
      <bibkey>dolatian-etal-2022-free</bibkey>
      <pwccode url="https://github.com/apertium/apertium-hyw" additional="false">apertium/apertium-hyw</pwccode>
    </paper>
    <paper id="2">
      <title>Dialects Identification of <fixed-case>A</fixed-case>rmenian Language</title>
      <author><first>Karen</first><last>Avetisyan</last></author>
      <pages>8–12</pages>
      <abstract>The Armenian language has many dialects that differ from each other syntactically, morphologically, and phonetically. In this work, we implement and evaluate models that determine the dialect of a given passage of text. The proposed models are evaluated for the three major variations of the Armenian language: Eastern, Western, and Classical. Previously, there were no instruments of dialect identification in the Armenian language. The paper presents three approaches: a statistical which relies on a stop words dictionary, a modified statistical one with a dictionary of most frequently encountered words, and the third one that is based on Facebook’s fastText language identification neural network model. Two types of neural network models were trained, one with the usage of pre-trained word embeddings and the other without. Approaches were tested on sentence-level and document-level data. The results show that the neural network-based method works sufficiently better than the statistical ones, achieving almost 98% accuracy at the sentence level and nearly 100% at the document level.</abstract>
      <url hash="e97c6b27">2022.digitam-1.2</url>
      <bibkey>avetisyan-2022-dialects</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="3">
      <title>Analyse Automatique de l’Ancien Arménien. Évaluation d’une méthode hybride « dictionnaire » et « réseau de neurones » sur un Extrait de l’Adversus Haereses d’Irénée de Lyon</title>
      <author><first>Bastien</first><last>Kindt</last></author>
      <author><first>Gabriel</first><last>Kepeklian</last></author>
      <pages>13–20</pages>
      <abstract>The aim of this paper is to evaluate a lexical analysis (mainly lemmatization and POS-tagging) of a sample of the Ancient Armenian version of the Adversus Haereses by Irenaeus of Lyons (2nd c.) by using hybrid approach based on digital dictionaries on the one hand, and on Recurrent Neural Network (RNN) on the other hand. The quality of the results is checked by comparing data obtained by implementing these two methods with data manually checked. In the present case, 98,37% of the results are correct by using the first (lexical) approach, and 74,64% by using the second (RNN). But, in fact, both methods present advantages and disadvantages and argue for the hybrid method. The linguistic resources implemented here are jointly developed and tested by GREgORI and Calfa.</abstract>
      <url hash="dbb3c419">2022.digitam-1.3</url>
      <bibkey>kindt-kepeklian-2022-analyse</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="4">
      <title>Describing Language Variation in the Colophons of <fixed-case>A</fixed-case>rmenian Manuscripts</title>
      <author><first>Bastien</first><last>Kindt</last></author>
      <author><first>Emmanuel</first><last>Van Elverdinghe</last></author>
      <pages>20–27</pages>
      <abstract>The colophons of Armenian manuscripts constitute a large textual corpus spanning a millennium of written culture. These texts are highly diverse and rich in terms of linguistic variation. This poses a challenge to NLP tools, especially considering the fact that linguistic resources designed or suited for Armenian are still scarce. In this paper, we deal with a sub-corpus of colophons written to commemorate the rescue of a manuscript and dating from 1286 to ca. 1450, a thematic group distinguished by a particularly high concentration of words exhibiting linguistic variation. The text is processed (lemmatization, POS-tagging, and inflectional tagging) using the tools of the GREgORI Project and evaluated. Through a selection of examples, we show how variation is dealt with at each linguistic level (phonology, orthography, flexion, vocabulary, syntax). Complex variation, at the level of tokens or lemmata, is considered as well. The results of this work are used to enrich and refine the linguistic resources of the GREgORI project, which in turn benefits the processing of other texts.</abstract>
      <url hash="0ea54dc9">2022.digitam-1.4</url>
      <bibkey>kindt-van-elverdinghe-2022-describing</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="5">
      <title><fixed-case>E</fixed-case>astern <fixed-case>A</fixed-case>rmenian National Corpus: State of the Art and Perspectives</title>
      <author><first>Victoria</first><last>Khurshudyan</last></author>
      <author><first>Timofey</first><last>Arkhangelskiy</last></author>
      <author><first>Misha</first><last>Daniel</last></author>
      <author><first>Vladimir</first><last>Plungian</last></author>
      <author><first>Dmitri</first><last>Levonian</last></author>
      <author><first>Alex</first><last>Polyakov</last></author>
      <author><first>Sergei</first><last>Rubakov</last></author>
      <pages>28–37</pages>
      <abstract>Eastern Armenian National Corpus (EANC) is a comprehensive corpus of Modern Eastern Armenian with about 110 million tokens, covering written and oral discourses from the mid-19th century to the present. The corpus is provided with morphological, semantic and metatext annotation, as well as English translations. EANC is open access and available at www.eanc.net.</abstract>
      <url hash="23cc3498">2022.digitam-1.5</url>
      <bibkey>khurshudyan-etal-2022-eastern</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="6">
      <title>Towards a Unified <fixed-case>ASR</fixed-case> System for the <fixed-case>A</fixed-case>rmenian Standards</title>
      <author><first>Samuel</first><last>Chakmakjian</last></author>
      <author><first>Ilaine</first><last>Wang</last></author>
      <pages>38–42</pages>
      <abstract>Armenian is a traditionally under-resourced language, which has seen a recent uptick in interest in the development of its tools and presence in the digital domain. Some of this recent interest has centred around the development of Automatic Speech Recognition (ASR) technologies. However, the language boasts two standard variants which diverge on multiple typological and structural levels. In this work, we examine some of the available bodies of data for ASR construction, present the challenges in the processing of these data and propose a methodology going forward.</abstract>
      <url hash="6d424679">2022.digitam-1.6</url>
      <bibkey>chakmakjian-wang-2022-towards</bibkey>
    </paper>
  </volume>
</collection>
