<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<collection id="2022.icon">
  <volume id="1" ingest-date="2023-02-10">
    <meta>
      <booktitle>Proceedings of the 19th International Conference on Natural Language Processing (ICON)</booktitle>
      <editor><first>Bharathi Raja</first><last>Chakravarthi</last></editor>
      <editor><first>Abirami</first><last>Murugappan</last></editor>
      <editor><first>Dhivya</first><last>Chinnappa</last></editor>
      <editor><first>Adeep</first><last>Hane</last></editor>
      <editor><first>Prasanna Kumar</first><last>Kumeresan</last></editor>
      <editor><first>Rahul</first><last>Ponnusamy</last></editor>
      <publisher>Association for Computational Linguistics</publisher>
      <address>IIIT Delhi, New Delhi, India</address>
      <month>December</month>
      <year>2022</year>
      <url hash="4d029884">2022.icon-1</url>
      <venue>icon</venue>
    </meta>
    <frontmatter>
      <url hash="7cfebad8">2022.icon-1.0</url>
      <bibkey>icon-2022-international</bibkey>
    </frontmatter>
    <paper id="1">
      <title>Language Identification at the Word Level in Code-Mixed Texts Using Character Sequence and Word Embedding</title>
      <author><first>O.</first><last>E. Ojo</last></author>
      <author><first>A.</first><last>Gelbukh</last></author>
      <author><first>H.</first><last>Calvo</last></author>
      <author><first>A.</first><last>Feldman</last></author>
      <author><first>O.</first><last>O. Adebanji</last></author>
      <author><first>J.</first><last>Armenta-Segura</last></author>
      <pages>1-6</pages>
      <abstract>People often switch languages in conversations or written communication in order to communicate thoughts on social media platforms. The languages in texts of this type, also known as code-mixed texts, can be mixed at the sentence, word, or even sub-word level. In this paper, we address the problem of identifying language at the word level in code-mixed texts using a sequence of characters and word embedding. We feed machine learning and deep neural networks with a range of character-based and word-based text features as input. The data for this experiment was created by combining YouTube video comments from code-mixed Kannada and English (Kn-En) texts. The texts were pre-processed, split into words, and categorized as ‘Kannada’, ‘English’, ‘Mixed-Language’, ‘Name’, ‘Location’, and ‘Other’. The proposed techniques were able to learn from these features and were able to effectively identify the language of the words in the dataset. The proposed CK-Keras model with pre-trained Word2Vec embedding was our best-performing system, as it outperformed other methods when evaluated by the F1 scores.</abstract>
      <url hash="7d191b57">2022.icon-1.1</url>
      <bibkey>e-ojo-etal-2022-language</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="2">
      <title><fixed-case>C</fixed-case>o<fixed-case>LI</fixed-case>-Kanglish: Word-Level Language Identification in Code-Mixed <fixed-case>K</fixed-case>annada-<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>nglish Texts Shared Task using the Distilka model</title>
      <author><first>Vajratiya</first><last>Vajrobol</last></author>
      <pages>7-11</pages>
      <abstract>Due to the intercultural demographic of online users, code-mixed language is often used by them to express themselves on social media. Language support to such users is based on the ability of a system to identify the constituent languages of the code-mixed language. Therefore, the process of language identification that helps in determining the language of individual textual entities from a code-mixed corpus is a current and relevant classification problem. Code-mixed texts are difficult to interpret and analyze from an algorithmic perspective. However, highly complex transformer- based techniques can be used to analyze and identify distinct languages of words in code-mixed texts. Kannada is one of the Dravidian languages which is spoken and written in Karnataka, India. This study aims to identify the language of individual words of texts from a corpus of code-mixed Kannada-English texts using transformer-based techniques. The proposed Distilka model was developed by fine-tuning the DistilBERT model using the code-mixed corpus. This model performed best on the official test dataset with a macro-averaged F1-score of 0.62 and weighted precision score of 0.86. The proposed solution ranked first in the shared task.</abstract>
      <url hash="4afdda36">2022.icon-1.2</url>
      <bibkey>vajrobol-2022-coli</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="3">
      <title><fixed-case>BERT</fixed-case>-based Language Identification in Code-Mix <fixed-case>K</fixed-case>annada-<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>nglish Text at the <fixed-case>C</fixed-case>o<fixed-case>LI</fixed-case>-Kanglish Shared Task@<fixed-case>ICON</fixed-case> 2022</title>
      <author><first>Pritam</first><last>Deka</last></author>
      <author><first>Nayan</first><last>Jyoti Kalita</last></author>
      <author><first>Shikhar</first><last>Kumar Sarma</last></author>
      <pages>12-17</pages>
      <abstract>Language identification has recently gained research interest in code-mixed languages due to the extensive use of social media among people. People who speak multiple languages tend to use code-mixed languages when communicating with each other. It has become necessary to identify the languages in such code-mixed environment to detect hate speeches, fake news, misinformation or disinformation and for tasks such as sentiment analysis. In this work, we have proposed a BERT-based approach for language identification in the CoLI-Kanglish shared task at ICON 2022. Our approach achieved 86% weighted average F-1 score and a macro average F-1 score of 57% in the test set.</abstract>
      <url hash="2b5caa40">2022.icon-1.3</url>
      <bibkey>deka-etal-2022-bert</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="4">
      <title>Word Level Language Identification in Code-mixed <fixed-case>K</fixed-case>annada-<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>nglish Texts using traditional machine learning algorithms</title>
      <author><first>Atnafu</first><last>Lambebo Tonja</last></author>
      <author><first>Mesay</first><last>Gemeda Yigezu</last></author>
      <author><first>Olga</first><last>Kolesnikova</last></author>
      <author><first>Moein</first><last>Shahiki Tash</last></author>
      <author><first>Grigori</first><last>Sidorov</last></author>
      <author><first>Alexander</first><last>Gelbukh</last></author>
      <pages>18-21</pages>
      <abstract>Language Identification at the Word Level in Kannada-English Texts. This paper describes the system paper of CoLI-Kanglish 2022 shared task. The goal of this task is to identify the different languages used in CoLI-Kanglish 2022. This dataset is distributed into different categories including Kannada, English, Mixed-Language, Location, Name, and Others. This Code-Mix was compiled by CoLI-Kanglish 2022 organizers from posts on social media. We use two classification techniques, KNN and SVM, and achieve an F1-score of 0.58 and place third out of nine competitors.</abstract>
      <url hash="2d5385e4">2022.icon-1.4</url>
      <bibkey>lambebo-tonja-etal-2022-word</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="5">
      <title>Word Level Language Identification in Code-mixed <fixed-case>K</fixed-case>annada-<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>nglish Texts using traditional machine learning algorithms</title>
      <author><first>M.</first><last>Shahiki Tash</last></author>
      <author><first>Z.</first><last>Ahani</last></author>
      <author><first>A.l.</first><last>Tonja</last></author>
      <author><first>M.</first><last>Gemeda</last></author>
      <author><first>N.</first><last>Hussain</last></author>
      <author><first>O.</first><last>Kolesnikova</last></author>
      <pages>22-25</pages>
      <abstract>Language Identification at the Word Level in Kannada-English Texts. This paper de- scribes the system paper of CoLI-Kanglish 2022 shared task. The goal of this task is to identify the different languages used in CoLI- Kanglish 2022. This dataset is distributed into different categories including Kannada, En- glish, Mixed-Language, Location, Name, and Others. This Code-Mix was compiled by CoLI- Kanglish 2022 organizers from posts on social media. We use two classification techniques, KNN and SVM, and achieve an F1-score of 0.58 and place third out of nine competitors.</abstract>
      <url hash="2d5385e4">2022.icon-1.5</url>
      <bibkey>shahiki-tash-etal-2022-word</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="6">
      <title>Word Level Language Identification in Code-mixed <fixed-case>K</fixed-case>annada-<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>nglish Texts using Deep Learning Approach</title>
      <author><first>Mesay</first><last>Gemeda Yigezu</last></author>
      <author><first>Atnafu</first><last>Lambebo Tonja</last></author>
      <author><first>Olga</first><last>Kolesnikova</last></author>
      <author><first>Moein</first><last>Shahiki Tash</last></author>
      <author><first>Grigori</first><last>Sidorov</last></author>
      <author><first>Alexander</first><last>Gelbukh</last></author>
      <pages>26-30</pages>
      <abstract>The goal of code-mixed language identification (LID) is to determine which language is spoken or written in a given segment of a speech, word, sentence, or document. Our task is to identify English, Kannada, and mixed language from the provided data. To train a model we used the CoLI-Kenglish dataset, which contains English, Kannada, and mixed-language words. In our work, we conducted several experiments in order to obtain the best performing model. Then, we implemented the best model by using Bidirectional Long Short Term Memory (Bi-LSTM), which outperformed the other trained models with an F1-score of 0.61%.</abstract>
      <url hash="fee3a75e">2022.icon-1.6</url>
      <bibkey>gemeda-yigezu-etal-2022-word</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="7">
      <title><fixed-case>B</fixed-case>o<fixed-case>NC</fixed-case>: Bag of N-Characters Model for Word Level Language Identification</title>
      <author><first>Shimaa</first><last>Ismail</last></author>
      <author><first>Mai</first><last>K. Gallab</last></author>
      <author><first>Hamada</first><last>Nayel</last></author>
      <pages>31-34</pages>
      <abstract>This paper describes the model submitted by NLP_BFCAI team for Kanglish shared task held at ICON 2022. The proposed model used a very simple approach based on the word representation. Simple machine learning classification algorithms, Random Forests, Support Vector Machines, Stochastic Gradient Descent and Multi-Layer Perceptron have been imple- mented. Our submission, RF, securely ranked fifth among all other submissions.</abstract>
      <url hash="fbc4722b">2022.icon-1.7</url>
      <bibkey>ismail-etal-2022-bonc</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="8">
      <title>Overview of <fixed-case>C</fixed-case>o<fixed-case>LI</fixed-case>-Kanglish: Word Level Language Identification in Code-mixed <fixed-case>K</fixed-case>annada-<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>nglish Texts at <fixed-case>ICON</fixed-case> 2022</title>
      <author><first>F.</first><last>Balouchzahi</last></author>
      <author><first>S.</first><last>Butt</last></author>
      <author><first>A.</first><last>Hegde</last></author>
      <author><first>N.</first><last>Ashraf</last></author>
      <author><first>H.l.</first><last>Shashirekha</last></author>
      <author><first>Grigori</first><last>Sidorov</last></author>
      <author><first>Alexander</first><last>Gelbukh</last></author>
      <pages>35-42</pages>
      <abstract>The task of Language Identification (LI) in text processing refers to automatically identifying the languages used in a text document. LI task is usually been studied at the document level and often in high-resource languages while giving less importance to low-resource languages. However, with the recent advance- ment in technologies, in a multilingual country like India, many low-resource language users post their comments using English and one or more language(s) in the form of code-mixed texts. Combination of Kannada and English is one such code-mixed text of mixing Kannada and English languages at various levels. To address the word level LI in code-mixed text, in CoLI-Kanglish shared task, we have focused on open-sourcing a Kannada-English code-mixed dataset for word level LI of Kannada, English and mixed-language words written in Roman script. The task includes classifying each word in the given text into one of six predefined categories, namely: Kannada (kn), English (en), Kannada-English (kn-en), Name (name), Lo-cation (location), and Other (other). Among the models submitted by all the participants, the best performing model obtained averaged-weighted and averaged-macro F1 scores of 0.86 and 0.62 respectively.</abstract>
      <url hash="f14cad71">2022.icon-1.8</url>
      <bibkey>balouchzahi-etal-2022-overview</bibkey>
    </paper>
  </volume>
</collection>
