<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<collection id="2022.sdp">
  <volume id="1" ingest-date="2022-10-06" type="proceedings">
    <meta>
      <booktitle>Proceedings of the Third Workshop on Scholarly Document Processing</booktitle>
      <editor><first>Arman</first><last>Cohan</last></editor>
      <editor><first>Guy</first><last>Feigenblat</last></editor>
      <editor><first>Dayne</first><last>Freitag</last></editor>
      <editor><first>Tirthankar</first><last>Ghosal</last></editor>
      <editor><first>Drahomira</first><last>Herrmannova</last></editor>
      <editor><first>Petr</first><last>Knoth</last></editor>
      <editor><first>Kyle</first><last>Lo</last></editor>
      <editor><first>Philipp</first><last>Mayr</last></editor>
      <editor><first>Michal</first><last>Shmueli-Scheuer</last></editor>
      <editor><first>Anita</first><last>de Waard</last></editor>
      <editor><first>Lucy Lu</first><last>Wang</last></editor>
      <publisher>Association for Computational Linguistics</publisher>
      <address>Gyeongju, Republic of Korea</address>
      <month>October</month>
      <year>2022</year>
      <url hash="fade8984">2022.sdp-1</url>
      <venue>sdp</venue>
    </meta>
    <frontmatter>
      <url hash="78a637a6">2022.sdp-1.0</url>
      <bibkey>sdp-2022-scholarly</bibkey>
    </frontmatter>
    <paper id="1">
      <title>Overview of the Third Workshop on Scholarly Document Processing</title>
      <author><first>Arman</first><last>Cohan</last></author>
      <author><first>Guy</first><last>Feigenblat</last></author>
      <author><first>Dayne</first><last>Freitag</last></author>
      <author><first>Tirthankar</first><last>Ghosal</last></author>
      <author><first>Drahomira</first><last>Herrmannova</last></author>
      <author><first>Petr</first><last>Knoth</last></author>
      <author><first>Kyle</first><last>Lo</last></author>
      <author><first>Philipp</first><last>Mayr</last></author>
      <author><first>Michal</first><last>Shmueli-Scheuer</last></author>
      <author><first>Anita</first><last>de Waard</last></author>
      <author><first>Lucy Lu</first><last>Wang</last></author>
      <pages>1–6</pages>
      <abstract>With the ever-increasing pace of research and high volume of scholarly communication, scholars face a daunting task. Not only must they keep up with the growing literature in their own and related fields, scholars increasingly also need to rebut pseudo-science and disinformation. These needs have motivated an increasing focus on computational methods for enhancing search, summarization, and analysis of scholarly documents. However, the various strands of research on scholarly document processing remain fragmented. To reach out to the broader NLP and AI/ML community, pool distributed efforts in this area, and enable shared access to published research, we held the 3rd Workshop on Scholarly Document Processing (SDP) at COLING as a hybrid event (<url>https://sdproc.org/2022/</url>). The SDP workshop consisted of a research track, three invited talks and five Shared Tasks: 1) MSLR22: Multi-Document Summarization for Literature Reviews, 2) DAGPap22: Detecting automatically generated scientific papers, 3) SV-Ident 2022: Survey Variable Identification in Social Science Publications, 4) SKGG: Scholarly Knowledge Graph Generation, 5) MuP 2022: Multi Perspective Scientific Document Summarization. The program was geared towards NLP, information retrieval, and data mining for scholarly documents, with an emphasis on identifying and providing solutions to open challenges.</abstract>
      <url hash="dec8b0e6">2022.sdp-1.1</url>
      <bibkey>cohan-etal-2022-overview</bibkey>
      <pwcdataset url="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/sv-ident">SV-Ident</pwcdataset>
    </paper>
    <paper id="2">
      <title>Finding Scientific Topics in Continuously Growing Text Corpora</title>
      <author><first>André</first><last>Bittermann</last></author>
      <author><first>Jonas</first><last>Rieger</last></author>
      <pages>7–18</pages>
      <abstract>The ever growing amount of research publications demands computational assistance for everyone trying to keep track with scientific processes. Topic modeling has become a popular approach for finding scientific topics in static collections of research papers. However, the reality of continuously growing corpora of scholarly documents poses a major challenge for traditional approaches. We introduce RollingLDA for an ongoing monitoring of research topics, which offers the possibility of sequential modeling of dynamically growing corpora with time consistency of time series resulting from the modeled texts. We evaluate its capability to detect research topics and present a Shiny App as an easy-to-use interface. In addition, we illustrate usage scenarios for different user groups such as researchers, students, journalists, or policy-makers.</abstract>
      <url hash="0a2ebb9f">2022.sdp-1.2</url>
      <bibkey>bittermann-rieger-2022-finding</bibkey>
      <pwccode url="https://github.com/leibniz-psychology/psychtopics" additional="true">leibniz-psychology/psychtopics</pwccode>
    </paper>
    <paper id="3">
      <title>Large-scale Evaluation of Transformer-based Article Encoders on the Task of Citation Recommendation</title>
      <author><first>Zoran</first><last>Medić</last></author>
      <author><first>Jan</first><last>Snajder</last></author>
      <pages>19–31</pages>
      <abstract>Recently introduced transformer-based article encoders (TAEs) designed to produce similar vector representations for mutually related scientific articles have demonstrated strong performance on benchmark datasets for scientific article recommendation. However, the existing benchmark datasets are predominantly focused on single domains and, in some cases, contain easy negatives in small candidate pools. Evaluating representations on such benchmarks might obscure the realistic performance of TAEs in setups with thousands of articles in candidate pools. In this work, we evaluate TAEs on large benchmarks with more challenging candidate pools. We compare the performance of TAEs with a lexical retrieval baseline model BM25 on the task of citation recommendation, where the model produces a list of recommendations for citing in a given input article. We find out that BM25 is still very competitive with the state-of-the-art neural retrievers, a finding which is surprising given the strong performance of TAEs on small benchmarks. As a remedy for the limitations of the existing benchmarks, we propose a new benchmark dataset for evaluating scientific article representations: Multi-Domain Citation Recommendation dataset (MDCR), which covers different scientific fields and contains challenging candidate pools.</abstract>
      <url hash="da57a23c">2022.sdp-1.3</url>
      <bibkey>medic-snajder-2022-large</bibkey>
      <pwccode url="https://github.com/zoranmedic/mdcr" additional="false">zoranmedic/mdcr</pwccode>
      <pwcdataset url="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/s2orc">S2ORC</pwcdataset>
      <pwcdataset url="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/trec-covid">TREC-COVID</pwcdataset>
    </paper>
    <paper id="4">
      <title>Investigating the detection of Tortured Phrases in Scientific Literature</title>
      <author><first>Puthineath</first><last>Lay</last></author>
      <author><first>Martin</first><last>Lentschat</last></author>
      <author><first>Cyril</first><last>Labbe</last></author>
      <pages>32–36</pages>
      <abstract>With the help of online tools, unscrupulous authors can today generate a pseudo-scientific article and attempt to publish it. Some of these tools work by replacing or paraphrasing existing texts to produce new content, but they have a tendency to generate nonsensical expressions. A recent study introduced the concept of “tortured phrase”, an unexpected odd phrase that appears instead of the fixed expression. E.g. counterfeit consciousness instead of artificial intelligence. The present study aims at investigating how tortured phrases, that are not yet listed, can be detected automatically. We conducted several experiments, including non-neural binary classification, neural binary classification and cosine similarity comparison of the phrase tokens, yielding noticeable results.</abstract>
      <url hash="3e0ac66d">2022.sdp-1.4</url>
      <bibkey>lay-etal-2022-investigating</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="5">
      <title>Lightweight Contextual Logical Structure Recovery</title>
      <author><first>Po-Wei</first><last>Huang</last></author>
      <author><first>Abhinav</first><last>Ramesh Kashyap</last></author>
      <author><first>Yanxia</first><last>Qin</last></author>
      <author><first>Yajing</first><last>Yang</last></author>
      <author><first>Min-Yen</first><last>Kan</last></author>
      <pages>37–48</pages>
      <abstract>Logical structure recovery in scientific articles associates text with a semantic section of the article. Although previous work has disregarded the surrounding context of a line, we model this important information by employing line-level attention on top of a transformer-based scientific document processing pipeline. With the addition of loss function engineering and data augmentation techniques with semi-supervised learning, our method improves classification performance by 10% compared to a recent state-of-the-art model. Our parsimonious, text-only method achieves a performance comparable to that of other works that use rich document features such as font and spatial position, using less data without sacrificing performance, resulting in a lightweight training pipeline.</abstract>
      <url hash="f4bb4377">2022.sdp-1.5</url>
      <bibkey>huang-etal-2022-lightweight</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="6">
      <title>Citation Context Classification: Critical vs Non-critical</title>
      <author><first>Sonita</first><last>Te</last></author>
      <author><first>Amira</first><last>Barhoumi</last></author>
      <author><first>Martin</first><last>Lentschat</last></author>
      <author><first>Frédérique</first><last>Bordignon</last></author>
      <author><first>Cyril</first><last>Labbé</last></author>
      <author><first>François</first><last>Portet</last></author>
      <pages>49–53</pages>
      <abstract>Recently, there have been numerous research in Natural Language Processing on citation analysis in scientific literature. Studies of citation behavior aim at finding how researchers cited a paper in their work. In this paper, we are interested in identifying cited papers that are criticized. Recent research introduces the concept of Critical citations which provides a useful theoretical framework, making criticism an important part of scientific progress. Indeed, identifying critics could be a way to spot errors and thus encourage self-correction of science. In this work, we investigate how to automatically classify the critical citation contexts using Natural Language Processing (NLP). Our classification task consists of predicting critical or non-critical labels for citation contexts. For this, we experiment and compare different methods, including rule-based and machine learning methods, to classify critical vs. non-critical citation contexts. Our experiments show that fine-tuning pretrained transformer model RoBERTa achieved the highest performance among all systems.</abstract>
      <url hash="b9e24c81">2022.sdp-1.6</url>
      <bibkey>te-etal-2022-citation</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="7">
      <title>Incorporating the Rhetoric of Scientific Language into Sentence Embeddings using Phrase-guided Distant Supervision and Metric Learning</title>
      <author><first>Kaito</first><last>Sugimoto</last></author>
      <author><first>Akiko</first><last>Aizawa</last></author>
      <pages>54–68</pages>
      <abstract>Communicative functions are an important rhetorical feature of scientific writing. Sentence embeddings that contain such features are highly valuable for the argumentative analysis of scientific documents, with applications in document alignment, recommendation, and academic writing assistance. Moreover, embeddings can provide a possible solution to the open-set problem, where models need to generalize to new communicative functions unseen at training time. However, existing sentence representation models are not suited for detecting functional similarity since they only consider lexical or semantic similarities. To remedy this, we propose a combined approach of distant supervision and metric learning to make a representation model more aware of the functional part of a sentence. We first leverage an existing academic phrase database to label sentences automatically with their functions. Then, we train an embedding model to capture similarities and dissimilarities from a rhetorical perspective. The experimental results demonstrate that the embeddings obtained from our model are more advantageous than existing models when retrieving functionally similar sentences. We also provide an extensive analysis of the performance differences between five metric learning objectives, revealing that traditional methods (e.g., softmax cross-entropy loss and triplet loss) outperform state-of-the-art techniques.</abstract>
      <url hash="556766b5">2022.sdp-1.7</url>
      <bibkey>sugimoto-aizawa-2022-incorporating</bibkey>
      <pwccode url="https://github.com/kaisugi/rhetorical_aspect_embeddings" additional="false">kaisugi/rhetorical_aspect_embeddings</pwccode>
      <pwcdataset url="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/pubmed-rct">PubMed RCT</pwcdataset>
      <pwcdataset url="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/s2orc">S2ORC</pwcdataset>
    </paper>
    <paper id="8">
      <title>Identifying Medical Paraphrases in Scientific versus Popularization Texts in <fixed-case>F</fixed-case>rench for Laypeople Understanding</title>
      <author><first>Ioana</first><last>Buhnila</last></author>
      <pages>69–79</pages>
      <abstract>Scientific medical terms are difficult to understand for laypeople due to their technical formulas and etymology. Understanding medical concepts is important for laypeople as personal and public health is a lifelong concern. In this study, we present our methodology for building a French lexical resource annotated with paraphrases for the simplification of monolexical and multiword medical terms. In order to find medical paraphrases, we automatically searched for medical terms and specific lexical markers that help to paraphrase them. We annotated the medical terms, the paraphrase markers, and the paraphrase. We analysed the lexical relations and semantico-pragmatic functions that exists between the term and its paraphrase. We computed statistics for the medical paraphrase corpus, and we evaluated the readability of the medical paraphrases for a non-specialist coder. Our results show that medical paraphrases from popularization texts are easier to understand (62.66%) than paraphrases extracted from scientific texts (50%).</abstract>
      <url hash="7fe2198a">2022.sdp-1.8</url>
      <bibkey>buhnila-2022-identifying</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="9">
      <title>Multi-objective Representation Learning for Scientific Document Retrieval</title>
      <author><first>Mathias</first><last>Parisot</last></author>
      <author><first>Jakub</first><last>Zavrel</last></author>
      <pages>80–88</pages>
      <abstract>Existing dense retrieval models for scientific documents have been optimized for either retrieval by short queries, or for document similarity, but usually not for both. In this paper, we explore the space of combining multiple objectives to achieve a single representation model that presents a good balance between both modes of dense retrieval, combining the relevance judgements from MS MARCO with the citation similarity of SPECTER, and the self-supervised objective of independent cropping. We also consider the addition of training data from document co-citation in a sentence context and domain-specific synthetic data. We show that combining multiple objectives yields models that generalize well across different benchmark tasks, improving up to 73% over models trained on a single objective.</abstract>
      <url hash="a35ac701">2022.sdp-1.9</url>
      <bibkey>parisot-zavrel-2022-multi</bibkey>
      <pwccode url="https://github.com/zetaalphavector/multi-obj-repr-learning" additional="false">zetaalphavector/multi-obj-repr-learning</pwccode>
      <pwcdataset url="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/beir">BEIR</pwcdataset>
      <pwcdataset url="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/ms-marco">MS MARCO</pwcdataset>
      <pwcdataset url="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/scidocs">SciDocs</pwcdataset>
      <pwcdataset url="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/scifact">SciFact</pwcdataset>
    </paper>
    <paper id="10">
      <title>Visualisation Methods for Diachronic Semantic Shift</title>
      <author><first>Raef</first><last>Kazi</last></author>
      <author><first>Alessandra</first><last>Amato</last></author>
      <author><first>Shenghui</first><last>Wang</last></author>
      <author><first>Doina</first><last>Bucur</last></author>
      <pages>89–94</pages>
      <abstract>The meaning and usage of a concept or a word changes over time. These diachronic semantic shifts reflect the change of societal and cultural consensus as well as the evolution of science. The availability of large-scale corpora and recent success in language models have enabled researchers to analyse semantic shifts in great detail. However, current research lacks intuitive ways of presenting diachronic semantic shifts and making them comprehensive. In this paper, we study the PubMed dataset and compute semantic shifts across six decades. We develop three visualisation methods that can show, given a root word: the temporal change in its linguistic context, word re-occurrence, degree of similarity, time continuity, and separate trends per publisher location. We also propose a taxonomy that classifies visualisation methods for diachronic semantic shifts with respect to different purposes.</abstract>
      <url hash="c474ef1f">2022.sdp-1.10</url>
      <bibkey>kazi-etal-2022-visualisation</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="11">
      <title>Unsupervised Partial Sentence Matching for Cited Text Identification</title>
      <author><first>Kathryn</first><last>Ricci</last></author>
      <author><first>Haw-Shiuan</first><last>Chang</last></author>
      <author><first>Purujit</first><last>Goyal</last></author>
      <author><first>Andrew</first><last>McCallum</last></author>
      <pages>95–104</pages>
      <abstract>Given a citation in the body of a research paper, cited text identification aims to find the sentences in the cited paper that are most relevant to the citing sentence. The task is fundamentally one of sentence matching, where affinity is often assessed by a cosine similarity between sentence embeddings. However, (a) sentences may not be well-represented by a single embedding because they contain multiple distinct semantic aspects, and (b) good matches may not require a strong match in all aspects. To overcome these limitations, we propose a simple and efficient unsupervised method for cited text identification that adapts an asymmetric similarity measure to allow partial matches of multiple aspects in both sentences. On the CL-SciSumm dataset we find that our method outperforms a baseline symmetric approach, and, surprisingly, also outperforms all supervised and unsupervised systems submitted to past editions of CL-SciSumm Shared Task 1a.</abstract>
      <url hash="df35e9f6">2022.sdp-1.11</url>
      <bibkey>ricci-etal-2022-unsupervised</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="12">
      <title>Multi-label Classification of Scientific Research Documents Across Domains and Languages</title>
      <author><first>Autumn</first><last>Toney</last></author>
      <author><first>James</first><last>Dunham</last></author>
      <pages>105–114</pages>
      <abstract>Automatically organizing scholarly literature is a necessary and challenging task. By assigning scientific research publications key concepts, researchers, policymakers, and the general public are able to search for and discover relevant research literature. The organization of scientific research evolves with new discoveries and publications, requiring an up-to-date and scalable text classification model. Additionally, scientific research publications benefit from multi-label classification, particularly with more fine-grained sub-domains. Prior work has focused on classifying scientific publications from one research area (e.g., computer science), referencing static concept descriptions, and implementing an English-only classification model. We propose a multi-label classification model that can be implemented in non-English languages, across all of scientific literature, with updatable concept descriptions.</abstract>
      <url hash="feba34f8">2022.sdp-1.12</url>
      <bibkey>toney-dunham-2022-multi</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="13">
      <title>Investigating Metric Diversity for Evaluating Long Document Summarisation</title>
      <author><first>Cai</first><last>Yang</last></author>
      <author><first>Stephen</first><last>Wan</last></author>
      <pages>115–125</pages>
      <abstract>Long document summarisation, a challenging summarisation scenario, is the focus of the recently proposed LongSumm shared task. One of the limitations of this shared task has been its use of a single family of metrics for evaluation (the ROUGE metrics). In contrast, other fields, like text generation, employ multiple metrics. We replicated the LongSumm evaluation using multiple test set samples (vs. the single test set of the official shared task) and investigated how different metrics might complement each other in this evaluation framework. We show that under this more rigorous evaluation, (1) some of the key learnings from Longsumm 2020 and 2021 still hold, but the relative ranking of systems changes, and (2) the use of additional metrics reveals additional high-quality summaries missed by ROUGE, and (3) we show that SPICE is a candidate metric for summarisation evaluation for LongSumm.</abstract>
      <url hash="a1402178">2022.sdp-1.13</url>
      <bibkey>yang-wan-2022-investigating</bibkey>
      <pwccode url="https://github.com/caiyangcy/sdp-longsumm-metric-diversity" additional="false">caiyangcy/sdp-longsumm-metric-diversity</pwccode>
    </paper>
    <paper id="14">
      <title>Exploiting Unary Relations with Stacked Learning for Relation Extraction</title>
      <author><first>Yuan</first><last>Zhuang</last></author>
      <author><first>Ellen</first><last>Riloff</last></author>
      <author><first>Kiri L.</first><last>Wagstaff</last></author>
      <author><first>Raymond</first><last>Francis</last></author>
      <author><first>Matthew P.</first><last>Golombek</last></author>
      <author><first>Leslie K.</first><last>Tamppari</last></author>
      <pages>126–137</pages>
      <abstract>Relation extraction models typically cast the problem of determining whether there is a relation between a pair of entities as a single decision. However, these models can struggle with long or complex language constructions in which two entities are not directly linked, as is often the case in scientific publications. We propose a novel approach that decomposes a binary relation into two unary relations that capture each argument’s role in the relation separately. We create a stacked learning model that incorporates information from unary and binary relation extractors to determine whether a relation holds between two entities. We present experimental results showing that this approach outperforms several competitive relation extractors on a new corpus of planetary science publications as well as a benchmark dataset in the biology domain.</abstract>
      <url hash="5d522a17">2022.sdp-1.14</url>
      <bibkey>zhuang-etal-2022-exploiting</bibkey>
      <pwccode url="https://github.com/yyzhuang1991/stackedlearningwithunarymodels" additional="false">yyzhuang1991/stackedlearningwithunarymodels</pwccode>
      <pwcdataset url="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/lpsc">LPSC</pwcdataset>
    </paper>
    <paper id="15">
      <title>Mitigating Data Shift of Biomedical Research Articles for Information Retrieval and Semantic Indexing</title>
      <author><first>Nima</first><last>Ebadi</last></author>
      <author><first>Anthony</first><last>Rios</last></author>
      <author><first>Peyman</first><last>Najafirad</last></author>
      <pages>138–151</pages>
      <abstract>Researchers have explored novel methods for both semantic indexing and information retrieval of biomedical research articles. Moreover, most solutions treat each task independently. However, both tasks are related. For instance, semantic indexes are generally used to filter results from an information retrieval system. Hence, one task can potentially improve the performance of models trained for the other task. Thus, this study proposes a unified retriever-ranker-based model to tackle the tasks of information retrieval (IR) and semantic indexing (SI). Particularly, our proposed model can adapt to rapid shifts in scientific research. Our results show that the model effectively leverages task similarity to improve the robustness to dataset shift. For SI, the Micro f1 score increases by 8% and the LCA-F score improves by 5%. For IR, the MAP increases by 5% on average.</abstract>
      <url hash="8d12c2e7">2022.sdp-1.15</url>
      <bibkey>ebadi-etal-2022-mitigating</bibkey>
      <pwcdataset url="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/bioasq">BioASQ</pwcdataset>
      <pwcdataset url="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/trec-covid">TREC-COVID</pwcdataset>
    </paper>
    <paper id="16">
      <title>A <fixed-case>J</fixed-case>apanese Masked Language Model for Academic Domain</title>
      <author><first>Hiroki</first><last>Yamauchi</last></author>
      <author><first>Tomoyuki</first><last>Kajiwara</last></author>
      <author><first>Marie</first><last>Katsurai</last></author>
      <author><first>Ikki</first><last>Ohmukai</last></author>
      <author><first>Takashi</first><last>Ninomiya</last></author>
      <pages>152–157</pages>
      <abstract>We release a pretrained Japanese masked language model for an academic domain. Pretrained masked language models have recently improved the performance of various natural language processing applications. In domains such as medical and academic, which include a lot of technical terms, domain-specific pretraining is effective. While domain-specific masked language models for medical and SNS domains are widely used in Japanese, along with domain-independent ones, pretrained models specific to the academic domain are not publicly available. In this study, we pretrained a RoBERTa-based Japanese masked language model on paper abstracts from the academic database CiNii Articles. Experimental results on Japanese text classification in the academic domain revealed the effectiveness of the proposed model over existing pretrained models.</abstract>
      <url hash="c974cf46">2022.sdp-1.16</url>
      <bibkey>yamauchi-etal-2022-japanese</bibkey>
      <pwccode url="https://github.com/hirokiyamauch/academicroberta" additional="false">hirokiyamauch/academicroberta</pwccode>
    </paper>
    <paper id="17">
      <title>Named Entity Inclusion in Abstractive Text Summarization</title>
      <author><first>Sergey</first><last>Berezin</last></author>
      <author><first>Tatiana</first><last>Batura</last></author>
      <pages>158–162</pages>
      <abstract>We address the named entity omission - the drawback of many current abstractive text summarizers. We suggest a custom pretraining objective to enhance the model’s attention on the named entities in a text. At first, the named entity recognition model RoBERTa is trained to determine named entities in the text. After that this model is used to mask named entities in the text and the BART model is trained to reconstruct them. Next, BART model is fine-tuned on the summarization task. Our experiments showed that this pretraining approach drastically improves named entity inclusion precision and recall metrics.</abstract>
      <url hash="f52de4fe">2022.sdp-1.17</url>
      <bibkey>berezin-batura-2022-named</bibkey>
      <pwcdataset url="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/scierc">SciERC</pwcdataset>
    </paper>
    <paper id="18">
      <title>Named Entity Recognition Based Automatic Generation of Research Highlights</title>
      <author><first>Tohida</first><last>Rehman</last></author>
      <author><first>Debarshi Kumar</first><last>Sanyal</last></author>
      <author><first>Prasenjit</first><last>Majumder</last></author>
      <author><first>Samiran</first><last>Chattopadhyay</last></author>
      <pages>163–169</pages>
      <abstract>A scientific paper is traditionally prefaced by an abstract that summarizes the paper. Recently, research highlights that focus on the main findings of the paper have emerged as a complementary summary in addition to an abstract. However, highlights are not yet as common as abstracts, and are absent in many papers. In this paper, we aim to automatically generate research highlights using different sections of a research paper as input. We investigate whether the use of named entity recognition on the input improves the quality of the generated highlights. In particular, we have used two deep learning-based models: the first is a pointer-generator network, and the second augments the first model with coverage mechanism. We then augment each of the above models with named entity recognition features. The proposed method can be used to produce highlights for papers with missing highlights. Our experiments show that adding named entity information improves the performance of the deep learning-based summarizers in terms of ROUGE, METEOR and BERTScore measures.</abstract>
      <url hash="1542d91f">2022.sdp-1.18</url>
      <bibkey>rehman-etal-2022-named</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="19">
      <title>Citation Sentence Generation Leveraging the Content of Cited Papers</title>
      <author><first>Akito</first><last>Arita</last></author>
      <author><first>Hiroaki</first><last>Sugiyama</last></author>
      <author><first>Kohji</first><last>Dohsaka</last></author>
      <author><first>Rikuto</first><last>Tanaka</last></author>
      <author><first>Hirotoshi</first><last>Taira</last></author>
      <pages>170–174</pages>
      <abstract>We address automatic citation sentence generation, which reduces the burden on writing scientific papers. For highly accurate citation senetence generation, appropriate language must be learned using information such as the relationship between the cited source and the cited paper as well as the context in which the paper cited. Although the abstracts of papers have been used for the generation in the past, they often contain extra information in the citation sentence, which might negatively impact the generation of citation sentences. Therefore, this study attempts to learn a highly accurate citation sentence generation model using sentences from cited articles that resemble the previous sentence to the cited location, thereby utilizing information that is more useful for citation sentence generation.</abstract>
      <url hash="f0aaee52">2022.sdp-1.19</url>
      <bibkey>arita-etal-2022-citation</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="20">
      <title>Overview of <fixed-case>MSLR</fixed-case>2022: A Shared Task on Multi-document Summarization for Literature Reviews</title>
      <author><first>Lucy Lu</first><last>Wang</last></author>
      <author><first>Jay</first><last>DeYoung</last></author>
      <author><first>Byron</first><last>Wallace</last></author>
      <pages>175–180</pages>
      <abstract>We provide an overview of the MSLR2022 shared task on multi-document summarization for literature reviews. The shared task was hosted at the Third Scholarly Document Processing (SDP) Workshop at COLING 2022. For this task, we provided data consisting of gold summaries extracted from review papers along with the groups of input abstracts that were synthesized into these summaries, split into two subtasks. In total, six teams participated, making 10 public submissions, 6 to the Cochrane subtask and 4 to the MSˆ2 subtask. The top scoring systems reported over 2 points ROUGE-L improvement on the Cochrane subtask, though performance improvements are not consistently reported across all automated evaluation metrics; qualitative examination of the results also suggests the inadequacy of current evaluation metrics for capturing factuality and consistency on this task. Significant work is needed to improve system performance, and more importantly, to develop better methods for automatically evaluating performance on this task.</abstract>
      <url hash="59399dbf">2022.sdp-1.20</url>
      <bibkey>wang-etal-2022-overview</bibkey>
      <pwccode url="https://github.com/allenai/mslr-shared-task" additional="false">allenai/mslr-shared-task</pwccode>
      <pwcdataset url="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/evidence-inference">Evidence Inference</pwcdataset>
    </paper>
    <paper id="21">
      <title><fixed-case>LED</fixed-case> down the rabbit hole: exploring the potential of global attention for biomedical multi-document summarisation</title>
      <author><first>Yulia</first><last>Otmakhova</last></author>
      <author><first>Thinh Hung</first><last>Truong</last></author>
      <author><first>Timothy</first><last>Baldwin</last></author>
      <author><first>Trevor</first><last>Cohn</last></author>
      <author><first>Karin</first><last>Verspoor</last></author>
      <author><first>Jey Han</first><last>Lau</last></author>
      <pages>181–187</pages>
      <abstract>In this paper we report the experiments performed for the submission to the Multidocument summarisation for Literature Review (MSLR) Shared Task. In particular, we adopt Primera model to the biomedical domain by placing global attention on important biomedical entities in several ways. We analyse the outputs of 23 resulting models and report some patterns related to the presence of additional global attention, number of training steps and the inputs configuration.</abstract>
      <url hash="1529b714">2022.sdp-1.21</url>
      <bibkey>otmakhova-etal-2022-led</bibkey>
      <pwccode url="https://github.com/allenai/mslr-shared-task" additional="true">allenai/mslr-shared-task</pwccode>
      <pwcdataset url="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/ebm-nlp">EBM-NLP</pwcdataset>
    </paper>
    <paper id="22">
      <title>Evaluating Pre-Trained Language Models on Multi-Document Summarization for Literature Reviews</title>
      <author><first>Benjamin</first><last>Yu</last></author>
      <pages>188–192</pages>
      <abstract>Systematic literature reviews in the biomedical space are often expensive to conduct. Automation through machine learning and large language models could improve the accuracy and research outcomes from such reviews. In this study, we evaluate a pre-trained LongT5 model on the MSLR22: Multi-Document Summarization for Literature Reviews Shared Task datasets. We weren’t able to make any improvements on the dataset benchmark, but we do establish some evidence that current summarization metrics are insufficient in measuring summarization accuracy. A multi-document summarization web tool was also built to demonstrate the viability of summarization models for future investigators: <url>https://ben-yu.github.io/summarizer</url></abstract>
      <url hash="2bb0acff">2022.sdp-1.22</url>
      <bibkey>yu-2022-evaluating</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="23">
      <title>Exploring the limits of a base <fixed-case>BART</fixed-case> for multi-document summarization in the medical domain</title>
      <author><first>Ishmael</first><last>Obonyo</last></author>
      <author><first>Silvia</first><last>Casola</last></author>
      <author><first>Horacio</first><last>Saggion</last></author>
      <pages>193–198</pages>
      <abstract>This paper is a description of our participation in the Multi-document Summarization for Literature Review (MSLR) Shared Task, in which we explore summarization models to create an automatic review of scientific results. Rather than maximizing the metrics using expensive computational models, we placed ourselves in a situation of scarce computational resources and explore the limits of a base sequence to sequence models (thus with a limited input length) to the task. Although we explore methods to feed the abstractive model with salient sentences only (using a first extractive step), we find the results still need some improvements.</abstract>
      <url hash="3d2b6fee">2022.sdp-1.23</url>
      <bibkey>obonyo-etal-2022-exploring</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="24">
      <title>Abstractive Approaches To Multidocument Summarization Of Medical Literature Reviews</title>
      <author><first>Rahul</first><last>Tangsali</last></author>
      <author><first>Aditya Jagdish</first><last>Vyawahare</last></author>
      <author><first>Aditya Vyankatesh</first><last>Mandke</last></author>
      <author><first>Onkar Rupesh</first><last>Litake</last></author>
      <author><first>Dipali Dattatray</first><last>Kadam</last></author>
      <pages>199–203</pages>
      <abstract>Text summarization has been a trending domain of research in NLP in the past few decades. The medical domain is no exception to the same. Medical documents often contain a lot of jargon pertaining to certain domains, and performing an abstractive summarization on the same remains a challenge. This paper presents a summary of the findings that we obtained based on the shared task of Multidocument Summarization for Literature Review (MSLR). We stood fourth in the leaderboards for evaluation on the MSˆ2 and Cochrane datasets. We finetuned pre-trained models such as BART-large, DistilBART and T5-base on both these datasets. These models’ accuracy was later tested with a part of the same dataset using ROUGE scores as the evaluation metrics.</abstract>
      <url hash="9f237747">2022.sdp-1.24</url>
      <bibkey>tangsali-etal-2022-abstractive</bibkey>
      <pwcdataset url="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/semantic-scholar">Semantic Scholar</pwcdataset>
    </paper>
    <paper id="25">
      <title>An Extractive-Abstractive Approach for Multi-document Summarization of Scientific Articles for Literature Review</title>
      <author><first>Kartik</first><last>Shinde</last></author>
      <author><first>Trinita</first><last>Roy</last></author>
      <author><first>Tirthankar</first><last>Ghosal</last></author>
      <pages>204–209</pages>
      <abstract>Research in the biomedical domain is con- stantly challenged by its large amount of ever- evolving textual information. Biomedical re- searchers are usually required to conduct a lit- erature review before any medical interven- tion to assess the effectiveness of the con- cerned research. However, the process is time- consuming, and therefore, automation to some extent would help reduce the accompanying information overload. Multi-document sum- marization of scientific articles for literature reviews is one approximation of such automa- tion. Here in this paper, we describe our pipelined approach for the aforementioned task. We design a BERT-based extractive method followed by a BigBird PEGASUS-based ab- stractive pipeline for generating literature re- view summaries from the abstracts of biomedi- cal trial reports as part of the Multi-document Summarization for Literature Review (MSLR) shared task1 in the Scholarly Document Pro- cessing (SDP) workshop 20222. Our proposed model achieves the best performance on the MSLR-Cochrane leaderboard3 on majority of the evaluation metrics. Human scrutiny of our automatically generated summaries indicates that our approach is promising to yield readable multi-article summaries for conducting such lit- erature reviews.</abstract>
      <url hash="b21885ae">2022.sdp-1.25</url>
      <bibkey>shinde-etal-2022-extractive</bibkey>
      <pwccode url="https://github.com/allenai/mslr-shared-task" additional="false">allenai/mslr-shared-task</pwccode>
    </paper>
    <paper id="26">
      <title>Overview of the <fixed-case>DAGP</fixed-case>ap22 Shared Task on Detecting Automatically Generated Scientific Papers</title>
      <author><first>Yury</first><last>Kashnitsky</last></author>
      <author><first>Drahomira</first><last>Herrmannova</last></author>
      <author><first>Anita</first><last>de Waard</last></author>
      <author><first>George</first><last>Tsatsaronis</last></author>
      <author><first>Catriona Catriona</first><last>Fennell</last></author>
      <author><first>Cyril</first><last>Labbe</last></author>
      <pages>210–213</pages>
      <abstract>This paper provides an overview of the DAGPap22 shared task on the detection of automatically generated scientific papers at the Scholarly Document Process workshop colocated with COLING. We frame the detection problem as a binary classification task: given an excerpt of text, label it as either human-written or machine-generated. We shared a dataset containing excerpts from human-written papers as well as artificially generated content and suspicious documents collected by Elsevier publishing and editorial teams. As a test set, the participants are provided with a 5x larger corpus of openly accessible human-written as well as generated papers from the same scientific domains of documents. The shared task saw 180 submissions across 14 participating teams and resulted in two published technical reports. We discuss our findings from the shared task in this overview paper.</abstract>
      <url hash="c79b086d">2022.sdp-1.26</url>
      <bibkey>kashnitsky-etal-2022-overview</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="27">
      <title><fixed-case>S</fixed-case>yn<fixed-case>S</fixed-case>ci<fixed-case>P</fixed-case>ass: detecting appropriate uses of scientific text generation</title>
      <author><first>Domenic</first><last>Rosati</last></author>
      <pages>214–222</pages>
      <abstract>Approaches to machine generated text detection tend to focus on binary classification of human versus machine written text. In the scientific domain where publishers might use these models to examine manuscripts under submission, misclassification has the potential to cause harm to authors. Additionally, authors may appropriately use text generation models such as with the use of assistive technologies like translation tools. In this setting, a binary classification scheme might be used to flag appropriate uses of assistive text generation technology as simply machine generated which is a cause of concern. In our work, we simulate this scenario by presenting a state-of-the-art detector trained on the DAGPap22 with machine translated passages from Scielo and find that the model performs at random. Given this finding, we develop a framework for dataset development that provides a nuanced approach to detecting machine generated text by having labels for the type of technology used such as for translation or paraphrase resulting in the construction of SynSciPass. By training the same model that performed well on DAGPap22 on SynSciPass, we show that not only is the model more robust to domain shifts but also is able to uncover the type of technology used for machine generated text. Despite this, we conclude that current datasets are neither comprehensive nor realistic enough to understand how these models would perform in the wild where manuscript submissions can come from many unknown or novel distributions, how they would perform on scientific full-texts rather than small passages, and what might happen when there is a mix of appropriate and inappropriate uses of natural language generation.</abstract>
      <url hash="259092b6">2022.sdp-1.27</url>
      <bibkey>rosati-2022-synscipass</bibkey>
      <pwccode url="https://github.com/domenicrosati/synscipass" additional="false">domenicrosati/synscipass</pwccode>
    </paper>
    <paper id="28">
      <title>Detecting generated scientific papers using an ensemble of transformer models</title>
      <author><first>Anna</first><last>Glazkova</last></author>
      <author><first>Maksim</first><last>Glazkov</last></author>
      <pages>223–228</pages>
      <abstract>The paper describes neural models developed for the DAGPap22 shared task hosted at the Third Workshop on Scholarly Document Processing. This shared task targets the automatic detection of generated scientific papers. Our work focuses on comparing different transformer-based models as well as using additional datasets and techniques to deal with imbalanced classes. As a final submission, we utilized an ensemble of SciBERT, RoBERTa, and DeBERTa fine-tuned using random oversampling technique. Our model achieved 99.24% in terms of F1-score. The official evaluation results have put our system at the third place.</abstract>
      <url hash="b7f418e4">2022.sdp-1.28</url>
      <bibkey>glazkova-glazkov-2022-detecting</bibkey>
      <pwccode url="https://github.com/oldaandozerskaya/dagpap22" additional="false">oldaandozerskaya/dagpap22</pwccode>
      <pwcdataset url="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/kp20k">KP20k</pwcdataset>
    </paper>
    <paper id="29">
      <title>Overview of the <fixed-case>SV</fixed-case>-Ident 2022 Shared Task on Survey Variable Identification in Social Science Publications</title>
      <author><first>Tornike</first><last>Tsereteli</last></author>
      <author><first>Yavuz Selim</first><last>Kartal</last></author>
      <author><first>Simone Paolo</first><last>Ponzetto</last></author>
      <author><first>Andrea</first><last>Zielinski</last></author>
      <author><first>Kai</first><last>Eckert</last></author>
      <author><first>Philipp</first><last>Mayr</last></author>
      <pages>229–246</pages>
      <abstract>In this paper, we provide an overview of the SV-Ident shared task as part of the 3rd Workshop on Scholarly Document Processing (SDP) at COLING 2022. In the shared task, participants were provided with a sentence and a vocabulary of variables, and asked to identify which variables, if any, are mentioned in individual sentences from scholarly documents in full text. Two teams made a total of 9 submissions to the shared task leaderboard. While none of the teams improve on the baseline systems, we still draw insights from their submissions. Furthermore, we provide a detailed evaluation. Data and baselines for our shared task are freely available at <url>https://github.com/vadis-project/sv-ident</url>.</abstract>
      <url hash="4d7007ac">2022.sdp-1.29</url>
      <bibkey>tsereteli-etal-2022-overview</bibkey>
      <pwccode url="https://github.com/vadis-project/sv-ident" additional="false">vadis-project/sv-ident</pwccode>
      <pwcdataset url="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/sv-ident">SV-Ident</pwcdataset>
    </paper>
    <paper id="30">
      <title>Varanalysis@<fixed-case>SV</fixed-case>-Ident 2022: Variable Detection and Disambiguation Based on Semantic Similarity</title>
      <author><first>Alica</first><last>Hövelmeyer</last></author>
      <author><first>Yavuz Selim</first><last>Kartal</last></author>
      <pages>247–252</pages>
      <abstract>This paper describes an approach to the SV-Ident Shared Task which requires the detection and disambiguation of survey variables in sentences taken from social science publications. It deals with both subtasks as problems of semantic textual similarity (STS) and relies on the use of sentence transformers. Sentences and variables are examined for semantic similarity for both detecting sentences containing variables and disambiguating the respective variables. The focus is placed on analyzing the effects of including different parts of the variables and observing the differences between English and German instances. Additionally, for the variable detection task a bag of words model is used to filter out sentences which are likely to contain a variable mention as a preselection of sentences to perform the semantic similarity comparison on.</abstract>
      <url hash="cfecd85e">2022.sdp-1.30</url>
      <bibkey>hovelmeyer-kartal-2022-varanalysis</bibkey>
      <pwcdataset url="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/sv-ident">SV-Ident</pwcdataset>
    </paper>
    <paper id="31">
      <title>Benchmark for Research Theme Classification of Scholarly Documents</title>
      <author><first>Óscar</first><last>E. Mendoza</last></author>
      <author><first>Wojciech</first><last>Kusa</last></author>
      <author><first>Alaa</first><last>El-Ebshihy</last></author>
      <author><first>Ronin</first><last>Wu</last></author>
      <author><first>David</first><last>Pride</last></author>
      <author><first>Petr</first><last>Knoth</last></author>
      <author><first>Drahomira</first><last>Herrmannova</last></author>
      <author><first>Florina</first><last>Piroi</last></author>
      <author><first>Gabriella</first><last>Pasi</last></author>
      <author><first>Allan</first><last>Hanbury</last></author>
      <pages>253–262</pages>
      <abstract>We present a new gold-standard dataset and a benchmark for the Research Theme Identification task, a sub-task of the Scholarly Knowledge Graph Generation shared task, at the 3rd Workshop on Scholarly Document Processing. The objective of the shared task was to label given research papers with research themes from a total of 36 themes. The benchmark was compiled using data drawn from the largest overall assessment of university research output ever undertaken globally (the Research Excellence Framework - 2014). We provide a performance comparison of a transformer-based ensemble, which obtains multiple predictions for a research paper, given its multiple textual fields (e.g. title, abstract, reference), with traditional machine learning models. The ensemble involves enriching the initial data with additional information from open-access digital libraries and Argumentative Zoning techniques (CITATION). It uses a weighted sum aggregation for the multiple predictions to obtain a final single prediction for the given research paper. Both data and the ensemble are publicly available on <url>https://www.kaggle.com/competitions/sdp2022-scholarly-knowledge-graph-generation/data?select=task1_test_no_label.csv</url> and <url>https://github.com/ProjectDoSSIER/sdp2022</url>, respectively.</abstract>
      <url hash="6e2af96e">2022.sdp-1.31</url>
      <bibkey>e-mendoza-etal-2022-benchmark</bibkey>
      <pwccode url="https://github.com/projectdossier/sdp2022" additional="false">projectdossier/sdp2022</pwccode>
    </paper>
    <paper id="32">
      <title>Overview of the First Shared Task on Multi Perspective Scientific Document Summarization (<fixed-case>M</fixed-case>u<fixed-case>P</fixed-case>)</title>
      <author><first>Arman</first><last>Cohan</last></author>
      <author><first>Guy</first><last>Feigenblat</last></author>
      <author><first>Tirthankar</first><last>Ghosal</last></author>
      <author><first>Michal</first><last>Shmueli-Scheuer</last></author>
      <pages>263–267</pages>
      <abstract>We present the main findings of MuP 2022 shared task, the first shared task on multi-perspective scientific document summarization. The task provides a testbed representing challenges for summarization of scientific documents, and facilitates development of better models to leverage summaries generated from multiple perspectives. We received 139 total submissions from 9 teams. We evaluated submissions both by automated metrics (i.e., Rouge) and human judgments on faithfulness, coverage, and readability which provided a more nuanced view of the differences between the systems. While we observe encouraging results from the participating teams, we conclude that there is still significant room left for improving summarization leveraging multiple references. Our dataset is available at <url>https://github.com/allenai/mup</url>.</abstract>
      <url hash="7a96d442">2022.sdp-1.32</url>
      <bibkey>cohan-etal-2022-overview-first</bibkey>
      <pwccode url="https://github.com/allenai/mup" additional="false">allenai/mup</pwccode>
    </paper>
    <paper id="33">
      <title>Multi Perspective Scientific Document Summarization With Graph Attention Networks (<fixed-case>GATS</fixed-case>)</title>
      <author><first>Abbas</first><last>Akkasi</last></author>
      <pages>268–272</pages>
      <abstract>It is well recognized that creating summaries of scientific texts can be difficult. For each given document, the majority of summarizing research believes there is only one best gold summary. Having just one gold summary limits our capacity to assess the effectiveness of summarizing algorithms because creating summaries is an art. Likewise, because it takes subject-matter experts a lot of time to read and comprehend lengthy scientific publications, annotating several gold summaries for scientific documents can be very expensive. The shared task known as the Multi perspective Scientific Document Summarization (Mup) is an exploration of various methods to produce multi perspective scientific summaries. Utilizing Graph Attention Networks (GATs), we take an extractive text summarization approach to the issue as a kind of sentence ranking task. Although the results produced by the suggested model are not particularly impressive, comparing them to the state-of-the-arts demonstrates the model’s potential for improvement.</abstract>
      <url hash="1e4a4a2d">2022.sdp-1.33</url>
      <bibkey>akkasi-2022-multi</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="34">
      <title><fixed-case>GUIR</fixed-case> @ <fixed-case>M</fixed-case>u<fixed-case>P</fixed-case> 2022: Towards Generating Topic-aware Multi-perspective Summaries for Scientific Documents</title>
      <author><first>Sajad</first><last>Sotudeh</last></author>
      <author><first>Nazli</first><last>Goharian</last></author>
      <pages>273–278</pages>
      <abstract>This paper presents our approach for the MuP 2022 shared task —-Multi-Perspective Scientific Document Summarization, where the objective is to enable summarization models to explore methods for generating multi-perspective summaries for scientific papers. We explore two orthogonal ways to cope with this task. The first approach involves incorporating a neural topic model (i.e., NTM) into the state-of-the-art abstractive summarizer (LED); the second approach involves adding a two-step summarizer that extracts the salient sentences from the document and then writes abstractive summaries from those sentences. Our latter model outperformed our other submissions on the official test set. Specifically, among 10 participants (including organizers’ baseline) who made their results public with 163 total runs. Our best system ranks first in Rouge-1 (F), and second in Rouge-1 (R), Rouge-2 (F) and Average Rouge (F) scores.</abstract>
      <url hash="31354515">2022.sdp-1.34</url>
      <bibkey>sotudeh-goharian-2022-guir</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="35">
      <title><fixed-case>LTRC</fixed-case> @<fixed-case>M</fixed-case>u<fixed-case>P</fixed-case> 2022: Multi-Perspective Scientific Document Summarization Using Pre-trained Generation Models</title>
      <author><first>Ashok</first><last>Urlana</last></author>
      <author><first>Nirmal</first><last>Surange</last></author>
      <author><first>Manish</first><last>Shrivastava</last></author>
      <pages>279–284</pages>
      <abstract>The MuP-2022 shared task focuses on multiperspective scientific document summarization. Given a scientific document, with multiple reference summaries, our goal was to develop a model that can produce a generic summary covering as many aspects of the document as covered by all of its reference summaries. This paper describes our best official model, a finetuned BART-large, along with a discussion on the challenges of this task and some of our unofficial models including SOTA generation models. Our submitted model out performedthe given, MuP 2022 shared task, baselines on ROUGE-2, ROUGE-L and average ROUGE F1-scores. Code of our submission can be ac- cessed here.</abstract>
      <url hash="1d0b794c">2022.sdp-1.35</url>
      <bibkey>urlana-etal-2022-ltrc</bibkey>
      <pwccode url="https://github.com/ashokurlana/ltrc-mup-coling-2022" additional="false">ashokurlana/ltrc-mup-coling-2022</pwccode>
      <pwcdataset url="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/scitldr">SciTLDR</pwcdataset>
    </paper>
    <paper id="36">
      <title>Team <fixed-case>AINLPML</fixed-case> @ <fixed-case>M</fixed-case>u<fixed-case>P</fixed-case> in <fixed-case>SDP</fixed-case> 2021: Scientific Document Summarization by End-to-End Extractive and Abstractive Approach</title>
      <author><first>Sandeep</first><last>Kumar</last></author>
      <author><first>Guneet Singh</first><last>Kohli</last></author>
      <author><first>Kartik</first><last>Shinde</last></author>
      <author><first>Asif</first><last>Ekbal</last></author>
      <pages>285–290</pages>
      <abstract>This paper introduces the proposed summarization system of the AINLPML team for the First Shared Task on Multi-Perspective Scientific Document Summarization at SDP 2022. We present a method to produce abstractive summaries of scientific documents. First, we perform an extractive summarization step to identify the essential part of the paper. The extraction step includes utilizing a contributing sentence identification model to determine the contributing sentences in selected sections and portions of the text. In the next step, the extracted relevant information is used to condition the transformer language model to generate an abstractive summary. In particular, we fine-tuned the pre-trained BART model on the extracted summary from the previous step. Our proposed model successfully outperformed the baseline provided by the organizers by a significant margin. Our approach achieves the best average Rouge F1 Score, Rouge-2 F1 Score, and Rouge-L F1 Score among all submissions.</abstract>
      <url hash="6e3b4719">2022.sdp-1.36</url>
      <bibkey>kumar-etal-2022-team</bibkey>
    </paper>
  </volume>
</collection>
