<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<collection id="2022.nalm">
  <volume id="1" ingest-date="2023-02-10" type="proceedings">
    <meta>
      <booktitle>Proceedings of the First Workshop on NLP in Agriculture and Livestock Management</booktitle>
      <editor><first>Manjira</first><last>Sinha</last></editor>
      <editor><first>Tirthankar</first><last>Dasgupta</last></editor>
      <editor><first>Sanjay</first><last>Chatterjee</last></editor>
      <publisher>Association for Computational Linguistics</publisher>
      <address>IIIT Delhi, New Delhi, India</address>
      <month>December</month>
      <year>2022</year>
      <url hash="52ab4099">2022.nalm-1</url>
      <venue>nalm</venue>
    </meta>
    <frontmatter>
      <url hash="1dd68923">2022.nalm-1.0</url>
      <bibkey>nalm-2022-nlp</bibkey>
    </frontmatter>
    <paper id="1">
      <title>Rice Cultivation in <fixed-case>I</fixed-case>ndia – Challenges and Environmental Effects</title>
      <author><first>Ushasi</first><last>Bhattacharya</last></author>
      <pages>1-4</pages>
      <abstract>Rice is one of the most cultivated grain crops in India as well as in Asian countries. It is a staple food in India. India is the second largest producer of Rice next to China. This crop is grown mainly in tropical and rain fed areas. In this paper, major types of Rice crops cultivated in India, the major challenges of cultivating Rice in India and its adverse effect in the environment are discussed. We have also discussed how the Computer Vision, Natural Language Processing, Mobile Applications and other technologies and research works can help to overcome these issues.</abstract>
      <url hash="4943c617">2022.nalm-1.1</url>
      <bibkey>bhattacharya-2022-rice</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="2">
      <title>A custom <fixed-case>CNN</fixed-case> model for detection of rice disease under complex environment</title>
      <author><first>Chiranjit</first><last>Pal</last></author>
      <author><first>Sanjoy</first><last>Pratihar</last></author>
      <author><first>Imon</first><last>Mukherjee</last></author>
      <pages>5-8</pages>
      <abstract>The work in this paper designs an image-based rice disease detection framework that takes rice plant image as input and identifies the presence of BrownSpot disease in the image fed into the system. A CNN-based disease detection scheme performs the binary classification task on our custom dataset containing 2223 images of healthy and unhealthy classes under complex environments. Experimental results show that our system is able to achieve consistently satisfactory results in performing disease detection tasks. Furthermore, the CNN disease detection model compares with state-of-the-art works and procures an accuracy of 96.8%.</abstract>
      <url hash="e2beece6">2022.nalm-1.2</url>
      <bibkey>pal-etal-2022-custom</bibkey>
    </paper>
  </volume>
</collection>
