<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<collection id="2022.wiesp">
  <volume id="1" ingest-date="2023-01-09" type="proceedings">
    <meta>
      <booktitle>Proceedings of the first Workshop on Information Extraction from Scientific Publications</booktitle>
      <editor><first>Tirthankar</first><last>Ghosal</last></editor>
      <editor><first>Sergi</first><last>Blanco-Cuaresma</last></editor>
      <editor><first>Alberto</first><last>Accomazzi</last></editor>
      <editor><first>Robert M.</first><last>Patton</last></editor>
      <editor><first>Felix</first><last>Grezes</last></editor>
      <editor><first>Thomas</first><last>Allen</last></editor>
      <publisher>Association for Computational Linguistics</publisher>
      <address>Online</address>
      <month>November</month>
      <year>2022</year>
      <url hash="4f1413bc">2022.wiesp-1</url>
      <venue>wiesp</venue>
    </meta>
    <frontmatter>
      <url hash="8565c285">2022.wiesp-1.0</url>
      <bibkey>wiesp-2022-information</bibkey>
    </frontmatter>
    <paper id="1">
      <title>Overview of the First Shared Task on Detecting Entities in the Astrophysics Literature (<fixed-case>DEAL</fixed-case>)</title>
      <author><first>Felix</first><last>Grezes</last></author>
      <author><first>Sergi</first><last>Blanco-Cuaresma</last></author>
      <author><first>Thomas</first><last>Allen</last></author>
      <author><first>Tirthankar</first><last>Ghosal</last></author>
      <pages>1–7</pages>
      <abstract>In this article, we describe the overview of our shared task: Detecting Entities in the Astrophysics Literature (DEAL). The DEAL shared task was part of the Workshop on Information Extraction from Scientific Publications (WIESP) in AACL-IJCNLP 2022. Information extraction from scientific publications is critical in several downstream tasks such as identification of critical entities, article summarization, citation classification, etc. The motivation of this shared task was to develop a community-wide effort for entity extraction from astrophysics literature. Automated entity extraction would help to build knowledge bases, high-quality meta-data for indexing and search, and several other use-cases of interests. Thirty-three teams registered for DEAL, twelve of them participated in the system runs, and finally four teams submitted their system descriptions. We analyze their system and performance and finally discuss the findings of DEAL.</abstract>
      <url hash="76371ca3">2022.wiesp-1.1</url>
      <bibkey>grezes-etal-2022-overview</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="2">
      <title>Classification of <fixed-case>URL</fixed-case> Citations in Scholarly Papers for Promoting Utilization of Research Artifacts</title>
      <author><first>Masaya</first><last>Tsunokake</last></author>
      <author><first>Shigeki</first><last>Matsubara</last></author>
      <pages>8–19</pages>
      <abstract>Utilizing citations for research artifacts (e.g., dataset, software) in scholarly papers contributes to efficient expansion of research artifact repositories and various applications e.g., the search, recommendation, and evaluation of such artifacts. This study focuses on citations using URLs (URL citations) and aims to identify and analyze research artifact citations automatically. This paper addresses the classification task for each URL citation to identify (1) the role that the referenced resources play in research activities, (2) the type of referenced resources, and (3) the reason why the author cited the resources. This paper proposes the classification method using section titles and footnote texts as new input features. We extracted URL citations from international conference papers as experimental data. We performed 5-fold cross-validation using the data and computed the classification performance of our method. The results demonstrate that our method is effective in all tasks. An additional experiment demonstrates that using cited URLs as input features is also effective.</abstract>
      <url hash="2f4d9d9a">2022.wiesp-1.2</url>
      <bibkey>tsunokake-matsubara-2022-classification</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="3">
      <title><fixed-case>TELIN</fixed-case>: Table Entity <fixed-case>LIN</fixed-case>ker for Extracting Leaderboards from Machine Learning Publications</title>
      <author><first>Sean</first><last>Yang</last></author>
      <author><first>Chris</first><last>Tensmeyer</last></author>
      <author><first>Curtis</first><last>Wigington</last></author>
      <pages>20–25</pages>
      <abstract>Tracking state-of-the-art (SOTA) results in machine learning studies is challenging due to high publication volume. Existing methods for creating leaderboards in scientific documents require significant human supervision or rely on scarcely available LaTeX source files. We propose Table Entity LINker (TELIN), a framework which extracts (task, model, dataset, metric) quadruples from collections of scientific publications in PDF format. TELIN identifies scientific named entities, constructs a knowledge base, and leverages human feedback to iteratively refine automatic extractions. TELIN identifies and prioritizes uncertain and impactful entities for human review to create a cascade effect for leaderboard completion. We show that TELIN is competitive with the SOTA but requires much less human annotation.</abstract>
      <url hash="8db2ce0d">2022.wiesp-1.3</url>
      <bibkey>yang-etal-2022-telin</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="4">
      <title><fixed-case>PICO</fixed-case> Corpus: A Publicly Available Corpus to Support Automatic Data Extraction from Biomedical Literature</title>
      <author><first>Faith</first><last>Mutinda</last></author>
      <author><first>Kongmeng</first><last>Liew</last></author>
      <author><first>Shuntaro</first><last>Yada</last></author>
      <author><first>Shoko</first><last>Wakamiya</last></author>
      <author><first>Eiji</first><last>Aramaki</last></author>
      <pages>26–31</pages>
      <abstract>We present a publicly available corpus with detailed annotations describing the core elements of clinical trials: Participants, Intervention, Control, and Outcomes. The corpus consists of 1011 abstracts of breast cancer randomized controlled trials extracted from the PubMed database. The corpus improves previous corpora by providing detailed annotations for outcomes to identify numeric texts that report the number of participants that experience specific outcomes. The corpus will be helpful for the development of systems for automatic extraction of data from randomized controlled trial literature to support evidence-based medicine. Additionally, we demonstrate the feasibility of the corpus by using two strong baselines for named entity recognition task. Most of the entities achieve F1 scores greater than 0.80 demonstrating the quality of the dataset.</abstract>
      <url hash="1923bbd7">2022.wiesp-1.4</url>
      <bibkey>mutinda-etal-2022-pico</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="5">
      <title>Linking a Hypothesis Network From the Domain of Invasion Biology to a Corpus of Scientific Abstracts: The <fixed-case>INAS</fixed-case> Dataset</title>
      <author><first>Marc</first><last>Brinner</last></author>
      <author><first>Tina</first><last>Heger</last></author>
      <author><first>Sina</first><last>Zarriess</last></author>
      <pages>32–42</pages>
      <abstract>We investigate the problem of identifying the major hypothesis that is addressed in a scientific paper. To this end, we present a dataset from the domain of invasion biology that organizes a set of 954 papers into a network of fine-grained domain-specific categories of hypotheses. We carry out experiments on classifying abstracts according to these categories and present a pilot study on annotating hypothesis statements within the text. We find that hypothesis statements in our dataset are complex, varied and more or less explicit, and, importantly, spread over the whole abstract. Experiments with BERT-based classifiers show that these models are able to classify complex hypothesis statements to some extent, without being trained on sentence-level text span annotations.</abstract>
      <url hash="c285ccf9">2022.wiesp-1.5</url>
      <bibkey>brinner-etal-2022-linking</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="6">
      <title>Leveraging knowledge graphs to update scientific word embeddings using latent semantic imputation</title>
      <author><first>Jason</first><last>Hoelscher-Obermaier</last></author>
      <author><first>Edward</first><last>Stevinson</last></author>
      <author><first>Valentin</first><last>Stauber</last></author>
      <author><first>Ivaylo</first><last>Zhelev</last></author>
      <author><first>Viktor</first><last>Botev</last></author>
      <author><first>Ronin</first><last>Wu</last></author>
      <author><first>Jeremy</first><last>Minton</last></author>
      <pages>43–53</pages>
      <abstract>The most interesting words in scientific texts will often be novel or rare. This presents a challenge for scientific word embedding models to determine quality embedding vectors for useful terms that are infrequent or newly emerging. We demonstrate how Latent Semantic Imputation (LSI) can address this problem by imputing embeddings for domain-specific words from up-to-date knowledge graphs while otherwise preserving the original word embedding model. We use the MeSH knowledge graph to impute embedding vectors for biomedical terminology without retraining and evaluate the resulting embedding model on a domain-specific word-pair similarity task. We show that LSI can produce reliable embedding vectors for rare and out-of-vocabulary terms in the biomedical domain.</abstract>
      <url hash="61840d42">2022.wiesp-1.6</url>
      <bibkey>hoelscher-obermaier-etal-2022-leveraging</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="7">
      <title>Full-Text Argumentation Mining on Scientific Publications</title>
      <author><first>Arne</first><last>Binder</last></author>
      <author><first>Leonhard</first><last>Hennig</last></author>
      <author><first>Bhuvanesh</first><last>Verma</last></author>
      <pages>54–66</pages>
      <abstract>Scholarly Argumentation Mining (SAM) has recently gained attention due to its potential to help scholars with the rapid growth of published scientific literature. It comprises two subtasks: argumentative discourse unit recognition (ADUR) and argumentative relation extraction (ARE), both of which are challenging since they require e.g. the integration of domain knowledge, the detection of implicit statements, and the disambiguation of argument structure. While previous work focused on dataset construction and baseline methods for specific document sections, such as abstract or results, full-text scholarly argumentation mining has seen little progress. In this work, we introduce a sequential pipeline model combining ADUR and ARE for full-text SAM, and provide a first analysis of the performance of pretrained language models (PLMs) on both subtasks. We establish a new SotA for ADUR on the Sci-Arg corpus, outperforming the previous best reported result by a large margin (+7% F1). We also present the first results for ARE, and thus for the full AM pipeline, on this benchmark dataset. Our detailed error analysis reveals that non-contiguous ADUs as well as the interpretation of discourse connectors pose major challenges and that data annotation needs to be more consistent.</abstract>
      <url hash="fe19e326">2022.wiesp-1.7</url>
      <attachment type="Software" hash="4d13c2f3">2022.wiesp-1.7.Software.zip</attachment>
      <bibkey>binder-etal-2022-full</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="8">
      <title>On the portability of extractive Question-Answering systems on scientific papers to real-life application scenarios</title>
      <author><first>Chyrine</first><last>Tahri</last></author>
      <author><first>Xavier</first><last>Tannier</last></author>
      <author><first>Patrick</first><last>Haouat</last></author>
      <pages>67–77</pages>
      <abstract>There are still hurdles standing in the way of faster and more efficient knowledge consumption in industrial environments seeking to foster innovation. In this work, we address the portability of extractive Question Answering systems from academic spheres to industries basing their decisions on thorough scientific papers analysis. Keeping in mind that such industrial contexts often lack high-quality data to develop their own QA systems, we illustrate the misalignment between application requirements and cost sensitivity of such industries and some widespread practices tackling the domain-adaptation problem in the academic world. Through a series of extractive QA experiments on QASPER, we adopt the pipeline-based retriever-ranker-reader architecture for answering a question on a scientific paper and show the impact of modeling choices in different stages on the quality of answer prediction. We thus provide a characterization of practical aspects of real-life application scenarios and notice that appropriate trade-offs can be efficient and add value in those industrial environments.</abstract>
      <url hash="129ffe51">2022.wiesp-1.8</url>
      <bibkey>tahri-etal-2022-portability</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="9">
      <title>Detecting Entities in the Astrophysics Literature: A Comparison of Word-based and Span-based Entity Recognition Methods</title>
      <author><first>Xiang</first><last>Dai</last></author>
      <author><first>Sarvnaz</first><last>Karimi</last></author>
      <pages>78–83</pages>
      <abstract>Information Extraction from scientific literature can be challenging due to the highly specialised nature of such text. We describe our entity recognition methods developed as part of the DEAL (Detecting Entities in the Astrophysics Literature) shared task. The aim of the task is to build a system that can identify Named Entities in a dataset composed by scholarly articles from astrophysics literature. We planned our participation such that it enables us to conduct an empirical comparison between word-based tagging and span-based classification methods. When evaluated on two hidden test sets provided by the organizer, our best-performing submission achieved F1 scores of 0.8307 (validation phase) and 0.7990 (testing phase).</abstract>
      <url hash="b24242f1">2022.wiesp-1.9</url>
      <bibkey>dai-karimi-2022-detecting</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="10">
      <title>Domain Specific Augmentations as Low Cost Teachers for Large Students</title>
      <author><first>Po-Wei</first><last>Huang</last></author>
      <pages>84–90</pages>
      <abstract>Current neural network solutions in scientific document processing employ models pretrained on domain-specific corpi, which are usually limited in model size, as pretraining can be costly and limited by training resources. We introduce a framework that uses data augmentation from such domain-specific pretrained models to transfer domain specific knowledge to larger general pretrained models and improve performance on downstream tasks. Our method improves the performance of Named Entity Recognition in the astrophysical domain by more than 20% compared to domain-specific pretrained models finetuned to the target dataset.</abstract>
      <url hash="cc5554a1">2022.wiesp-1.10</url>
      <bibkey>huang-2022-domain</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="11">
      <title>Moving beyond word lists: towards abstractive topic labels for human-like topics of scientific documents</title>
      <author><first>Domenic</first><last>Rosati</last></author>
      <pages>91–99</pages>
      <abstract>Topic models represent groups of documents as a list of words (the topic labels). This work asks whether an alternative approach to topic labeling can be developed that is closer to a natural language description of a topic than a word list. To this end, we present an approach to generating human-like topic labels using abstractive multi-document summarization (MDS). We investigate our approach with an exploratory case study. We model topics in citation sentences in order to understand what further research needs to be done to fully operationalize MDS for topic labeling. Our case study shows that in addition to more human-like topics there are additional advantages to evaluation by using clustering and summarization measures instead of topic model measures. However, we find that there are several developments needed before we can design a well-powered study to evaluate MDS for topic modeling fully. Namely, improving cluster cohesion, improving the factuality and faithfulness of MDS, and increasing the number of documents that might be supported by MDS. We present a number of ideas on how these can be tackled and conclude with some thoughts on how topic modeling can also be used to improve MDS in general.</abstract>
      <url hash="3779bb62">2022.wiesp-1.11</url>
      <bibkey>rosati-2022-moving</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="12">
      <title>Astro-m<fixed-case>T</fixed-case>5: Entity Extraction from Astrophysics Literature using m<fixed-case>T</fixed-case>5 Language Model</title>
      <author><first>Madhusudan</first><last>Ghosh</last></author>
      <author><first>Payel</first><last>Santra</last></author>
      <author><first>Sk Asif</first><last>Iqbal</last></author>
      <author><first>Partha</first><last>Basuchowdhuri</last></author>
      <pages>100–104</pages>
      <abstract>Scientific research requires reading and extracting relevant information from existing scientific literature in an effective way. To gain insights over a collection of such scientific documents, extraction of entities and recognizing their types is considered to be one of the important tasks. Numerous studies have been conducted in this area of research. In our study, we introduce a framework for entity recognition and identification of NASA astrophysics dataset, which was published as a part of the DEAL SharedTask. We use a pre-trained multilingual model, based on a natural language processing framework for the given sequence labeling tasks. Experiments show that our model, Astro-mT5, out-performs the existing baseline in astrophysics related information extraction.</abstract>
      <url hash="63356456">2022.wiesp-1.12</url>
      <bibkey>ghosh-etal-2022-astro</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="13">
      <title><fixed-case>NLPS</fixed-case>hared<fixed-case>T</fixed-case>asks: A Corpus of Shared Task Overview Papers in Natural Language Processing Domains</title>
      <author><first>Anna</first><last>Martin</last></author>
      <author><first>Ted</first><last>Pedersen</last></author>
      <author><first>Jennifer</first><last>D’Souza</last></author>
      <pages>105–120</pages>
      <abstract>As the rate of scientific output continues to grow, it is increasingly important to develop systems to improve interfaces between researchers and scholarly papers. Training models to extract scientific information from the full texts of scholarly documents is important for improving how we structure and access scientific information. However, there are few annotated corpora that provide full paper texts. This paper presents the NLPSharedTasks corpus, a new resource of 254 full text Shared Task Overview papers in NLP domains with annotated task descriptions. We calculated strict and relaxed inter-annotator agreement scores, achieving Cohen’s kappa coefficients of 0.44 and 0.95, respectively. Lastly, we performed a sentence classification task over the dataset, in order to generate a neural baseline for future research and to provide an example of how to preprocess unbalanced datasets of full scientific texts. We achieved an F1 score of 0.75 using SciBERT, fine-tuned and tested on a rebalanced version of the dataset.</abstract>
      <url hash="288066ae">2022.wiesp-1.13</url>
      <bibkey>martin-etal-2022-nlpsharedtasks</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="14">
      <title>Parsing Electronic Theses and Dissertations Using Object Detection</title>
      <author><first>Aman</first><last>Ahuja</last></author>
      <author><first>Alan</first><last>Devera</last></author>
      <author><first>Edward Alan</first><last>Fox</last></author>
      <pages>121–130</pages>
      <abstract>Electronic theses and dissertations (ETDs) contain valuable knowledge that can be useful for a wide range of purposes. To effectively utilize the knowledge contained in ETDs for downstream tasks such as search and retrieval, question-answering, and summarization, the data first needs to be parsed and stored in a format such as XML. However, since most of the ETDs available on the web are PDF documents, parsing them to make their data useful for downstream tasks is a challenge. In this work, we propose a dataset and a framework to help with parsing long scholarly documents such as ETDs. We take the Object Detection approach for document parsing. We first introduce a set of objects that are important elements of an ETD, along with a new dataset ETD-OD that consists of over 25K page images originating from 200 ETDs with bounding boxes around each of the objects. We also propose a framework that utilizes this dataset for converting ETDs to XML, which can further be used for ETD-related downstream tasks. Our code and pre-trained models are available at: <url>https://github.com/Opening-ETDs/ETD-OD</url>.</abstract>
      <url hash="e3ff24f6">2022.wiesp-1.14</url>
      <bibkey>ahuja-etal-2022-parsing</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="15">
      <title><fixed-case>TDAC</fixed-case>, The First Corpus in Time-Domain Astrophysics: Analysis and First Experiments on Named Entity Recognition</title>
      <author><first>Atilla Kaan</first><last>Alkan</last></author>
      <author><first>Cyril</first><last>Grouin</last></author>
      <author><first>Fabian</first><last>Schussler</last></author>
      <author><first>Pierre</first><last>Zweigenbaum</last></author>
      <pages>131–139</pages>
      <abstract>The increased interest in time-domain astronomy over the last decades has resulted in a substantial increase in observation reports publication leading to a saturation of how astrophysicists read, analyze and classify information. Due to the short life span of the detected astronomical events, the information related to the characterization of new phenomena has to be communicated and analyzed very rapidly to allow other observatories to react and conduct their follow-up observations. This paper introduces TDAC: the first Corpus in Time-Domain Astrophysics, based on observation reports. We also present the NLP experiments we made for named entity recognition based on annotations we made and annotations from the WIESP NLP Challenge.</abstract>
      <url hash="7f959f7d">2022.wiesp-1.15</url>
      <bibkey>alkan-etal-2022-tdac</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="16">
      <title>Reproducibility Signals in Science: A preliminary analysis</title>
      <author><first>Akhil Pandey</first><last>Akella</last></author>
      <author><first>Hamed</first><last>Alhoori</last></author>
      <author><first>David</first><last>Koop</last></author>
      <pages>140–144</pages>
      <abstract>Reproducibility is an important feature of science; experiments are retested, and analyses are repeated. Trust in the findings increases when consistent results are achieved. Despite the importance of reproducibility, significant work is often involved in these efforts, and some published findings may not be reproducible due to oversights or errors. In this paper, we examine a myriad of features in scholarly articles published in computer science conferences and journals and test how they correlate with reproducibility. We collected data from three different sources that labeled publications as either reproducible or irreproducible and employed statistical significance tests to identify features of those publications that hold clues about reproducibility. We found the readability of the scholarly article and accessibility of the software artifacts through hyperlinks to be strong signals noticeable amongst reproducible scholarly articles.</abstract>
      <url hash="2d7eccf6">2022.wiesp-1.16</url>
      <bibkey>akella-etal-2022-reproducibility</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="17">
      <title>A Majority Voting Strategy of a <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>ci<fixed-case>BERT</fixed-case>-based Ensemble Models for Detecting Entities in the Astrophysics Literature (Shared Task)</title>
      <author><first>Atilla Kaan</first><last>Alkan</last></author>
      <author><first>Cyril</first><last>Grouin</last></author>
      <author><first>Fabian</first><last>Schussler</last></author>
      <author><first>Pierre</first><last>Zweigenbaum</last></author>
      <pages>145–150</pages>
      <abstract>Detecting Entities in the Astrophysics Literature (DEAL) is a proposed shared task in the scope of the first Workshop on Information Extraction from Scientific Publications (WIESP) at AACL-IJCNLP 2022. It aims to propose systems identifying astrophysical named entities. This article presents our system based on a majority voting strategy of an ensemble composed of multiple SciBERT models. The system we propose is ranked second and outperforms the baseline provided by the organisers by achieving an F1 score of 0.7993 and a Matthews Correlation Coefficient (MCC) score of 0.8978 in the testing phase.</abstract>
      <url hash="c78ed364">2022.wiesp-1.17</url>
      <bibkey>alkan-etal-2022-majority</bibkey>
    </paper>
  </volume>
</collection>
