<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<collection id="2023.case">
  <volume id="1" ingest-date="2023-10-31" type="proceedings">
    <meta>
      <booktitle>Proceedings of the 6th Workshop on Challenges and Applications of Automated Extraction of Socio-political Events from Text</booktitle>
      <editor><first>Ali</first><last>Hürriyetoğlu</last></editor>
      <editor><first>Hristo</first><last>Tanev</last></editor>
      <editor><first>Vanni</first><last>Zavarella</last></editor>
      <editor><first>Reyyan</first><last>Yeniterzi</last></editor>
      <editor><first>Erdem</first><last>Yörük</last></editor>
      <editor><first>Milena</first><last>Slavcheva</last></editor>
      <publisher>INCOMA Ltd., Shoumen, Bulgaria</publisher>
      <address>Varna, Bulgaria</address>
      <month>sEPTEMBER</month>
      <year>2023</year>
      <url hash="8b04dd21">2023.case-1</url>
      <venue>case</venue>
      <venue>ws</venue>
    </meta>
    <frontmatter>
      <url hash="21f77465">2023.case-1.0</url>
      <bibkey>case-2023-challenges</bibkey>
    </frontmatter>
    <paper id="1">
      <title>Classifying Organized Criminal Violence in <fixed-case>M</fixed-case>exico using <fixed-case>ML</fixed-case> and <fixed-case>LLM</fixed-case>s</title>
      <author><first>Javier</first><last>Osorio</last></author>
      <author><first>Juan</first><last>Vasquez</last></author>
      <pages>1–10</pages>
      <abstract>Natural Language Processing (NLP) tools have been rapidly adopted in political science for the study of conflict and violence. In this paper, we present an application to analyze various lethal and non-lethal events conducted by organized criminal groups and state forces in Mexico. Based on a large corpus of news articles in Spanish and a set of high-quality annotations, the application evaluates different Machine Learning (ML) algorithms and Large Language Models (LLMs) to classify documents and individual sentences, and to identify specific behaviors related to organized criminal violence and law enforcement efforts. Our experiments support the growing evidence that BERT-like models achieve outstanding classification performance for the study of organized crime. This application amplifies the capacity of conflict scholars to provide valuable information related to important security challenges in the developing world.</abstract>
      <url hash="69d26bed">2023.case-1.1</url>
      <bibkey>osorio-vasquez-2023-classifying</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="2">
      <title>Where “where” Matters : Event Location Disambiguation with a <fixed-case>BERT</fixed-case> Language Model</title>
      <author><first>Hristo</first><last>Tanev</last></author>
      <author><first>Bertrand</first><last>De Longueville</last></author>
      <pages>11–17</pages>
      <abstract>The method method presented in this paper uses a BERT model for classifying location mentions in event reporting news texts into two classes: a place of an event, called main location, or another location mention, called here secondary location. Our evaluation on articles, reporting protests, shows promising results and demonstrates the feasibility of our approach and the event geolocation task in general. We evaluate our method against a simple baseline and state of the art ML models and we achieve a significant improvement in all cases by using the BERT model. In contrast to other location classification approaches, we completelly avoid lingusitic pre processing and feature engineering, which is a pre-requisite for all multi-domain and multilingual applications.</abstract>
      <url hash="f5822794">2023.case-1.2</url>
      <bibkey>tanev-de-longueville-2023-matters</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="3">
      <title>A Multi-instance Learning Approach to Civil Unrest Event Detection on <fixed-case>T</fixed-case>witter</title>
      <author><first>Alexandra</first><last>DeLucia</last></author>
      <author><first>Mark</first><last>Dredze</last></author>
      <author><first>Anna L.</first><last>Buczak</last></author>
      <pages>18–33</pages>
      <abstract>Social media has become an established platform for people to organize and take offline actions, often in the form of civil unrest. Understanding these events can help support pro-democratic movements. The primary method to detect these events on Twitter relies on aggregating many tweets, but this includes many that are not relevant to the task. We propose a multi-instance learning (MIL) approach, which jointly identifies relevant tweets and detects civil unrest events. We demonstrate that MIL improves civil unrest detection over methods based on simple aggregation. Our best model achieves a 0.73 F1 on the Global Civil Unrest on Twitter (G-CUT) dataset.</abstract>
      <url hash="4e749496">2023.case-1.3</url>
      <bibkey>delucia-etal-2023-multi</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="4">
      <title><fixed-case>MLM</fixed-case>odeler5 @ Causal News Corpus 2023: Using <fixed-case>R</fixed-case>o<fixed-case>BERT</fixed-case>a for Casual Event Classification</title>
      <author><first>Amrita</first><last>Bhatia</last></author>
      <author><first>Ananya</first><last>Thomas</last></author>
      <author><first>Nitansh</first><last>Jain</last></author>
      <author><first>Jatin</first><last>Bedi</last></author>
      <pages>34–37</pages>
      <abstract>Identifying cause-effect relations plays an integral role in the understanding and interpretation of natural languages. Furthermore, automated mining of causal relations from news and text about socio-political events is a stepping stone in gaining critical insights, including analyzing the scale, frequency and trends across timelines of events, as well as anticipating future ones. The Shared Task 3, part of the 6th Workshop on Challenges and Applications of Automated Extraction of Socio-political Events from Text (CASE @ RANLP 2023), involved the task of Event Causality Identification with Causal News Corpus. We describe our approach to Subtask 1, dealing with causal event classification, a supervised binary classification problem to annotate given event sentences with whether they contained any cause-effect relations. To help achieve this task, a BERT based architecture - RoBERTa was implemented. The results of this model are validated on the dataset provided by the organizers of this task.</abstract>
      <url hash="f82c2288">2023.case-1.4</url>
      <bibkey>bhatia-etal-2023-mlmodeler5</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="5">
      <title><fixed-case>B</fixed-case>osch<fixed-case>AI</fixed-case> @ Causal News Corpus 2023: Robust Cause-Effect Span Extraction using Multi-Layer Sequence Tagging and Data Augmentation</title>
      <author><first>Timo Pierre</first><last>Schrader</last></author>
      <author><first>Simon</first><last>Razniewski</last></author>
      <author><first>Lukas</first><last>Lange</last></author>
      <author><first>Annemarie</first><last>Friedrich</last></author>
      <pages>38–43</pages>
      <abstract>Understanding causality is a core aspect of intelligence. The Event Causality Identification with Causal News Corpus Shared Task addresses two aspects of this challenge: Subtask 1 aims at detecting causal relationships in texts, and Subtask 2 requires identifying signal words and the spans that refer to the cause or effect, respectively. Our system, which is based on pre-trained transformers, stacked sequence tagging, and synthetic data augmentation, ranks third in Subtask 1 and wins Subtask 2 with an F1 score of 72.8, corresponding to a margin of 13 pp. to the second-best system.</abstract>
      <url hash="65efa3cd">2023.case-1.5</url>
      <bibkey>schrader-etal-2023-boschai</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="6">
      <title>An Evaluation Framework for Mapping News Headlines to Event Classes in a Knowledge Graph</title>
      <author><first>Steve Fonin</first><last>Mbouadeu</last></author>
      <author><first>Martin</first><last>Lorenzo</last></author>
      <author><first>Ken</first><last>Barker</last></author>
      <author><first>Oktie</first><last>Hassanzadeh</last></author>
      <pages>44–52</pages>
      <abstract>Mapping ongoing news headlines to event-related classes in a rich knowledge base can be an important component in a knowledge-based event analysis and forecasting solution. In this paper, we present a methodology for creating a benchmark dataset of news headlines mapped to event classes in Wikidata, and resources for the evaluation of methods that perform the mapping. We use the dataset to study two classes of unsupervised methods for this task: 1) adaptations of classic entity linking methods, and 2) methods that treat the problem as a zero-shot text classification problem. For the first approach, we evaluate off-the-shelf entity linking systems. For the second approach, we explore a) pre-trained natural language inference (NLI) models, and b) pre-trained large generative language models. We present the results of our evaluation, lessons learned, and directions for future work. The dataset and scripts for evaluation are made publicly available.</abstract>
      <url hash="6d3407ee">2023.case-1.6</url>
      <bibkey>mbouadeu-etal-2023-evaluation</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="7">
      <title>Ometeotl@Multimodal Hate Speech Event Detection 2023: Hate Speech and Text-Image Correlation Detection in Real Life Memes Using Pre-Trained <fixed-case>BERT</fixed-case> Models over Text</title>
      <author><first>Jesus</first><last>Armenta-Segura</last></author>
      <author><first>César Jesús</first><last>Núñez-Prado</last></author>
      <author><first>Grigori Olegovich</first><last>Sidorov</last></author>
      <author><first>Alexander</first><last>Gelbukh</last></author>
      <author><first>Rodrigo Francisco</first><last>Román-Godínez</last></author>
      <pages>53–59</pages>
      <abstract>Hate speech detection during times of war has become crucial in recent years, as evident with the recent Russo-Ukrainian war. In this paper, we present our submissions for both subtasks from the Multimodal Hate Speech Event Detec- tion contest at CASE 2023, RANLP 2023. We used pre-trained BERT models in both submis- sion, achieving a F1 score of 0.809 in subtask A, and F1 score of 0.567 in subtask B. In the first subtask, our result was not far from the first place, which led us to realize the lower impact of images in real-life memes about feel- ings, when compared with the impact of text. However, we observed a higher importance of images when targeting hateful feelings towards a specific entity. The source code to reproduce our results can be found at the github repository https://github.com/JesusASmx/OmeteotlAtCASE2023</abstract>
      <url hash="4c3d5e4e">2023.case-1.7</url>
      <bibkey>armenta-segura-etal-2023-ometeotl</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="8">
      <title><fixed-case>I</fixed-case>nteros<fixed-case>ML</fixed-case>@Causal News Corpus 2023: Understanding Causal Relationships: Supervised Contrastive Learning for Event Classification</title>
      <author><first>Rajat</first><last>Patel</last></author>
      <pages>60–65</pages>
      <abstract>Causal events play a crucial role in explaining the intricate relationships between the causes and effects of events. However, comprehending causal events within discourse, text, or speech poses significant semantic challenges. We propose a contrastive learning-based method in this submission to the Causal News Corpus - Event Causality Shared Task 2023, with a specific focus on SubTask1 centered on causal event classification. In our approach we pre-train our base model using Supervised Contrastive (SuperCon) learning. Subsequently, we fine-tune the pre-trained model for the specific task of causal event classification. Our experimentation demonstrates the effectiveness of our method, achieving a competitive performance, and securing the 2nd position on the leaderboard with an F1-Score of 84.36.</abstract>
      <url hash="984b09d3">2023.case-1.8</url>
      <bibkey>patel-2023-interosml</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="9">
      <title><fixed-case>SSN</fixed-case>-<fixed-case>NLP</fixed-case>-<fixed-case>ACE</fixed-case>@Multimodal Hate Speech Event Detection 2023: Detection of Hate Speech and Targets using Logistic Regression and <fixed-case>SVM</fixed-case></title>
      <author><first>Avanthika</first><last>K</last></author>
      <author><first>Mrithula</first><last>Kl</last></author>
      <author><first>Thenmozhi</first><last>D</last></author>
      <pages>66–70</pages>
      <abstract>In this research paper, we propose a multimodal approach to hate speech detection, directed towards the identification of hate speech and its related targets. Our method uses logistic regression and support vector machines (SVMs) to analyse textual content extracted from social media platforms. We exploit natural language processing techniques to preprocess and extract relevant features from textual content, capturing linguistic patterns, sentiment, and contextual information.</abstract>
      <url hash="60ce80cd">2023.case-1.9</url>
      <bibkey>k-etal-2023-ssn</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="10">
      <title><fixed-case>ARC</fixed-case>-<fixed-case>NLP</fixed-case> at Multimodal Hate Speech Event Detection 2023: Multimodal Methods Boosted by Ensemble Learning, Syntactical and Entity Features</title>
      <author><first>Umitcan</first><last>Sahin</last></author>
      <author><first>Izzet Emre</first><last>Kucukkaya</last></author>
      <author><first>Oguzhan</first><last>Ozcelik</last></author>
      <author><first>Cagri</first><last>Toraman</last></author>
      <pages>71–78</pages>
      <abstract>Text-embedded images can serve as a means of spreading hate speech, propaganda, and extremist beliefs. Throughout the Russia-Ukraine war, both opposing factions heavily relied on text-embedded images as a vehicle for spreading propaganda and hate speech. Ensuring the effective detection of hate speech and propaganda is of utmost importance to mitigate the negative effect of hate speech dissemination. In this paper, we outline our methodologies for two subtasks of Multimodal Hate Speech Event Detection 2023. For the first subtask, hate speech detection, we utilize multimodal deep learning models boosted by ensemble learning and syntactical text attributes. For the second subtask, target detection, we employ multimodal deep learning models boosted by named entity features. Through experimentation, we demonstrate the superior performance of our models compared to all textual, visual, and text-visual baselines employed in multimodal hate speech detection. Furthermore, our models achieve the first place in both subtasks on the final leaderboard of the shared task.</abstract>
      <url hash="edd9eaee">2023.case-1.10</url>
      <bibkey>sahin-etal-2023-arc</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="11">
      <title><fixed-case>V</fixed-case>erba<fixed-case>V</fixed-case>isor@Multimodal Hate Speech Event Detection 2023: Hate Speech Detection using Transformer Model</title>
      <author><first>Sarika</first><last>Esackimuthu</last></author>
      <author><first>Prabavathy</first><last>Balasundaram</last></author>
      <pages>79–83</pages>
      <abstract>Hate speech detection has emerged as a critical research area in recent years due to the rise of online social platforms and the proliferation of harmful content targeting individuals or specific groups.This task highlights the importance of detecting hate speech in text-embedded images.By leveraging deep learning models,this research aims to uncover the connection between hate speech and the entities it targets.</abstract>
      <url hash="4fac8593">2023.case-1.11</url>
      <bibkey>esackimuthu-balasundaram-2023-verbavisor</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="12">
      <title>Lexical Squad@Multimodal Hate Speech Event Detection 2023: Multimodal Hate Speech Detection using Fused Ensemble Approach</title>
      <author><first>Mohammad</first><last>Kashif</last></author>
      <author><first>Mohammad</first><last>Zohair</last></author>
      <author><first>Saquib</first><last>Ali</last></author>
      <pages>84–91</pages>
      <abstract>With a surge in the usage of social media postings to express opinions, emotions, and ideologies, there has been a significant shift towards the calibration of social media as a rapid medium of conveying viewpoints and outlooks over the globe. Concurrently, the emergence of a multitude of conflicts between two entities has given rise to a stream of social media content containing propaganda, hate speech, and inconsiderate views. Thus, the issue of monitoring social media postings is rising swiftly, attracting major attention from those willing to solve such problems. One such problem is Hate Speech detection. To mitigate this problem, we present our novel ensemble learning approach for detecting hate speech, by classifying text-embedded images into two labels, namely “Hate Speech” and “No Hate Speech” . We have incorporated state-of-art models including InceptionV3, BERT, and XLNet. Our proposed ensemble model yielded promising results with 75.21 and 74.96 as accuracy and F-1 score (respectively). We also present an empirical evaluation of the text-embedded images to elaborate on how well the model was able to predict and classify.</abstract>
      <url hash="a6ae8dd9">2023.case-1.12</url>
      <bibkey>kashif-etal-2023-lexical</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="13">
      <title>On the Road to a Protest Event Ontology for <fixed-case>B</fixed-case>ulgarian: Conceptual Structures and Representation Design</title>
      <author><first>Milena</first><last>Slavcheva</last></author>
      <author><first>Hristo</first><last>Tanev</last></author>
      <author><first>Onur</first><last>Uca</last></author>
      <pages>92–100</pages>
      <abstract>The paper presents a semantic model of protest events, called Semantic Interpretations of Protest Events (SemInPE). The analytical framework used for building the semantic representations is inspired by the object-oriented paradigm in computer science and a cognitive approach to the linguistic analysis. The model is a practical application of the Unified Eventity Representation (UER) formalism, which is based on the Unified Modeling Language (UML). The multi-layered architecture of the model provides flexible means for building the semantic representations of the language objects along a scale of generality and specificity. Thus, it is a suitable environment for creating the elements of ontologies on various topics and for different languages.</abstract>
      <url hash="8fe7c0ed">2023.case-1.13</url>
      <bibkey>slavcheva-etal-2023-road</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="14">
      <title><fixed-case>CSECU</fixed-case>-<fixed-case>DSG</fixed-case>@Multimodal Hate Speech Event Detection 2023: Transformer-based Multimodal Hierarchical Fusion Model For Multimodal Hate Speech Detection</title>
      <author><first>Abdul</first><last>Aziz</last></author>
      <author><first>MD. Akram</first><last>Hossain</last></author>
      <author><first>Abu Nowshed</first><last>Chy</last></author>
      <pages>101–107</pages>
      <abstract>The emergence of social media and e-commerce platforms enabled the perpetrator to spread negativity and abuse individuals or organisations worldwide rapidly. It is critical to detect hate speech in both visual and textual content so that it may be moderated or excluded from online platforms to keep it sound and safe for users. However, multimodal hate speech detection is a complex and challenging task as people sarcastically present hate speech and different modalities i.e., image and text are involved in their content. This paper describes our participation in the CASE 2023 multimodal hate speech event detection task. In this task, the objective is to automatically detect hate speech and its target from the given text-embedded image. We proposed a transformer-based multimodal hierarchical fusion model to detect hate speech present in the visual content. We jointly fine-tune a language and a vision pre-trained transformer models to extract the visual-contextualized features representation of the text-embedded image. We concatenate these features and fed them to the multi-sample dropout strategy. Moreover, the contextual feature vector is fed into the BiLSTM module and the output of the BiLSTM module also passes into the multi-sample dropout. We employed arithmetic mean fusion to fuse all sample dropout outputs that predict the final label of our proposed method. Experimental results demonstrate that our model obtains competitive performance and ranked 5th among the participants</abstract>
      <url hash="562b841f">2023.case-1.14</url>
      <bibkey>aziz-etal-2023-csecu-dsg</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="15">
      <title><fixed-case>CSECU</fixed-case>-<fixed-case>DSG</fixed-case> @ Causal News Corpus 2023: Leveraging <fixed-case>R</fixed-case>o<fixed-case>BERT</fixed-case>a and <fixed-case>D</fixed-case>e<fixed-case>BERT</fixed-case>a Transformer Model with Contrastive Learning for Causal Event Classification</title>
      <author><first>MD. Akram</first><last>Hossain</last></author>
      <author><first>Abdul</first><last>Aziz</last></author>
      <author><first>Abu Nowshed</first><last>Chy</last></author>
      <pages>108–112</pages>
      <abstract>Cause-effect relationships play a crucial role in human cognition, and distilling cause-effect relations from text helps in ameliorating causal networks for predictive tasks. There are many NLP applications that can benefit from this task, including natural language-based financial forecasting, text summarization, and question-answering. However, due to the lack of syntactic clues, the ambivalent semantic meaning of words, complex sentence structure, and implicit meaning of numerical entities in the text make it one of the challenging tasks in NLP. To address these challenges, CASE-2023 introduced a shared task 3 task focusing on event causality identification with causal news corpus. In this paper, we demonstrate our participant systems for this task. We leverage two transformers models including DeBERTa and Twitter-RoBERTa along with the weighted average fusion technique to tackle the challenges of subtask 1 where we need to identify whether a text belongs to either causal or not. For subtask 2 where we need to identify the cause, effect, and signal tokens from the text, we proposed a unified neural network of DeBERTa and DistilRoBERTa transformer variants with contrastive learning techniques. The experimental results showed that our proposed method achieved competitive performance among the participants’ systems.</abstract>
      <url hash="f6aeb115">2023.case-1.15</url>
      <bibkey>hossain-etal-2023-csecu</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="16">
      <title><fixed-case>NEXT</fixed-case>: An Event Schema Extension Approach for Closed-Domain Event Extraction Models</title>
      <author><first>Elena</first><last>Tuparova</last></author>
      <author><first>Petar</first><last>Ivanov</last></author>
      <author><first>Andrey</first><last>Tagarev</last></author>
      <author><first>Svetla</first><last>Boytcheva</last></author>
      <author><first>Ivan</first><last>Koychev</last></author>
      <pages>113–123</pages>
      <abstract>Event extraction from textual data is a NLP research task relevant to a plethora of domains. Most approaches aim to recognize events from a predefined event schema, consisting of event types and their corresponding arguments. For domains, such as disinformation, where new event types emerge frequently, there is a need to adapt such fixed event schemas to accommodate for new event types. We present NEXT (New Event eXTraction) - a resource-sparse approach to extending a close-domain model to novel event types, that requires a very small number of annotated samples for fine-tuning performed on a single GPU. Furthermore, our results suggest that this approach is suitable not only for extraction of new event types, but also for recognition of existing event types, as the use of this approach on a new dataset leads to improved recall for all existing events while retaining precision.</abstract>
      <url hash="88e2a08f">2023.case-1.16</url>
      <bibkey>tuparova-etal-2023-next</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="17">
      <title>Negative documents are positive: Improving event extraction performance using overlooked negative data</title>
      <author><first>Osman</first><last>Mutlu</last></author>
      <author><first>Ali</first><last>Hürriyetoğlu</last></author>
      <pages>124–135</pages>
      <abstract>The scarcity of data poses a significant challenge in closed-domain event extraction, as is common in complex NLP tasks. This limitation primarily arises from the intricate nature of the annotation process. To address this issue, we present a multi-task model structure and training approach that leverages the additional data, which is found as not having any event information at document and sentence levels, generated during the event annotation process. By incorporating this supplementary data, our proposed framework demonstrates enhanced robustness and, in some scenarios, improved performance. A particularly noteworthy observation is that including only negative documents in addition to the original data contributes to performance enhancement. Our findings offer promising insights into leveraging extra data to mitigate data scarcity challenges in closed-domain event extraction.</abstract>
      <url hash="80416953">2023.case-1.17</url>
      <bibkey>mutlu-hurriyetoglu-2023-negative</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="18">
      <title><fixed-case>IIC</fixed-case>_<fixed-case>T</fixed-case>eam@Multimodal Hate Speech Event Detection 2023: Detection of Hate Speech and Targets using Xlm-Roberta-base</title>
      <author><first>Karanpreet</first><last>Singh</last></author>
      <author><first>Vajratiya</first><last>Vajrobol</last></author>
      <author><first>Nitisha</first><last>Aggarwal</last></author>
      <pages>136–143</pages>
      <abstract>Hate speech has emerged as a pressing issue on social media platforms, fueled by the increasing availability of multimodal data and easy internet access. Addressing this problem requires collaborative efforts from researchers, policymakers, and online platforms. In this study, we investigate the detection of hate speech in multimodal data, comprising text-embedded images, by employing advanced deep learning models. The main objective is to identify effective strategies for hate speech detection and content moderation. We conducted experiments using four state-of-the-art classifiers: XLM-Roberta-base, BiLSTM, XLNet base cased, and ALBERT, on the CrisisHateMM[4] dataset, consisting of over 4700 text-embedded images related to the Russia-Ukraine conflict. The best findings reveal that XLM-Roberta-base exhibits superior performance, outperforming other classifiers across all evaluation metrics, including an impressive F1 score of 84.62 for sub-task 1 and 69.73 for sub-task 2. The future scope of this study lies in exploring multimodal approaches to enhance hate speech detection accuracy, integrating ethical considerations to address potential biases, promoting fairness, and safeguarding user rights. Additionally, leveraging larger and more diverse datasets will contribute to developing more robust and generalised hate speech detection solutions.</abstract>
      <url hash="f20f4e72">2023.case-1.18</url>
      <bibkey>singh-etal-2023-iic</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="19">
      <title>Event Causality Identification - Shared Task 3, <fixed-case>CASE</fixed-case> 2023</title>
      <author><first>Fiona Anting</first><last>Tan</last></author>
      <author><first>Hansi</first><last>Hettiarachchi</last></author>
      <author><first>Ali</first><last>Hürriyetoğlu</last></author>
      <author><first>Nelleke</first><last>Oostdijk</last></author>
      <author><first>Onur</first><last>Uca</last></author>
      <author><first>Surendrabikram</first><last>Thapa</last></author>
      <author><first>Farhana Ferdousi</first><last>Liza</last></author>
      <pages>144–150</pages>
      <abstract>The Event Causality Identification Shared Task of CASE 2023 is the second iteration of a shared task centered around the Causal News Corpus. Two subtasks were involved: In Subtask 1, participants were challenged to predict if a sentence contains a causal relation or not. In Subtask 2, participants were challenged to identify the Cause, Effect, and Signal spans given an input causal sentence. For both subtasks, participants uploaded their predictions for a held-out test set, and ranking was done based on binary F1 and macro F1 scores for Subtask 1 and 2, respectively. This paper includes an overview of the work of the ten teams that submitted their results to our competition and the six system description papers that were received. The highest F1 scores achieved for Subtask 1 and 2 were 84.66% and 72.79%, respectively.</abstract>
      <url hash="644f1c65">2023.case-1.19</url>
      <bibkey>tan-etal-2023-event-causality</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="20">
      <title>Multimodal Hate Speech Event Detection - Shared Task 4, <fixed-case>CASE</fixed-case> 2023</title>
      <author><first>Surendrabikram</first><last>Thapa</last></author>
      <author><first>Farhan</first><last>Jafri</last></author>
      <author><first>Ali</first><last>Hürriyetoğlu</last></author>
      <author><first>Francielle</first><last>Vargas</last></author>
      <author><first>Roy Ka-Wei</first><last>Lee</last></author>
      <author><first>Usman</first><last>Naseem</last></author>
      <pages>151–159</pages>
      <abstract>Ensuring the moderation of hate speech and its targets emerges as a critical imperative within contemporary digital discourse. To facilitate this imperative, the shared task Multimodal Hate Speech Event Detection was organized in the sixth CASE workshop co-located at RANLP 2023. The shared task has two subtasks. The sub-task A required participants to pose hate speech detection as a binary problem i.e. they had to detect if the given text-embedded image had hate or not. Similarly, sub-task B required participants to identify the targets of the hate speech namely individual, community, and organization targets in text-embedded images. For both sub-tasks, the participants were ranked on the basis of the F1-score. The best F1-score in sub-task A and sub-task B were 85.65 and 76.34 respectively. This paper provides a comprehensive overview of the performance of 13 teams that submitted the results in Subtask A and 10 teams in Subtask B.</abstract>
      <url hash="79ff19c3">2023.case-1.20</url>
      <bibkey>thapa-etal-2023-multimodal</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="21">
      <title>Detecting and Geocoding Battle Events from Social Media Messages on the Russo-<fixed-case>U</fixed-case>krainian War: Shared Task 2, <fixed-case>CASE</fixed-case> 2023</title>
      <author><first>Hristo</first><last>Tanev</last></author>
      <author><first>Nicolas</first><last>Stefanovitch</last></author>
      <author><first>Andrew</first><last>Halterman</last></author>
      <author><first>Onur</first><last>Uca</last></author>
      <author><first>Vanni</first><last>Zavarella</last></author>
      <author><first>Ali</first><last>Hurriyetoglu</last></author>
      <author><first>Bertrand</first><last>De Longueville</last></author>
      <author><first>Leonida</first><last>Della Rocca</last></author>
      <pages>160–166</pages>
      <abstract>The purpose of the shared task 2 at the Challenges and Applications of Automated Extraction of Socio-political Events from Text (CASE) 2023 workshop was to test the abilities of the participating models and systems to detect and geocode armed conflicts events in social media messages from Telegram channels reporting on the Russo Ukrainian war. The evaluation followed an approach which was introduced in CASE 2021 (Giorgi et al., 2021): For each system we consider the correlation of the spatio-temporal distribution of its detected events and the events identified for the same period in the ACLED (Armed Conflict Location and Event Data Project) database (Raleigh et al., 2010). We use ACLED for the ground truth, since it is a well established standard in the field of event extraction and political trend analysis, which relies on human annotators for the encoding of security events using a fine grained taxonomy. Two systems participated in this shared task, we report in this paper on both the shared task and the participating systems.</abstract>
      <url hash="6d7e5b74">2023.case-1.21</url>
      <bibkey>tanev-etal-2023-detecting</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="22">
      <title>Challenges and Applications of Automated Extraction of Socio-political Events from Text (<fixed-case>CASE</fixed-case> 2023): Workshop and Shared Task Report</title>
      <author><first>Ali</first><last>Hürriyetoğlu</last></author>
      <author><first>Hristo</first><last>Tanev</last></author>
      <author><first>Osman</first><last>Mutlu</last></author>
      <author><first>Surendrabikram</first><last>Thapa</last></author>
      <author><first>Fiona Anting</first><last>Tan</last></author>
      <author><first>Erdem</first><last>Yörük</last></author>
      <pages>167–175</pages>
      <abstract>We provide a summary of the sixth edition of the CASE workshop that is held in the scope of RANLP 2023. The workshop consists of regular papers, three keynotes, working papers of shared task participants, and shared task overview papers. This workshop series has been bringing together all aspects of event information collection across technical and social science fields. In addition to contributing to the progress in text based event extraction, the workshop provides a space for the organization of a multimodal event information collection task.</abstract>
      <url hash="4d8b2e53">2023.case-1.22</url>
      <bibkey>hurriyetoglu-etal-2023-challenges</bibkey>
    </paper>
  </volume>
</collection>
