<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<collection id="2024.tsar">
  <volume id="1" ingest-date="2024-11-05" type="proceedings">
    <meta>
      <booktitle>Proceedings of the Third Workshop on Text Simplification, Accessibility and Readability (TSAR 2024)</booktitle>
      <editor><first>Matthew</first><last>Shardlow</last><affiliation>Manchester Metropolitan University, UK</affiliation></editor>
      <editor><first>Horacio</first><last>Saggion</last><affiliation>Universitat Pompeu Fabra, Spain</affiliation></editor>
      <editor><first>Fernando</first><last>Alva-Manchego</last><affiliation>Cardiff University, UK</affiliation></editor>
      <editor><first>Marcos</first><last>Zampieri</last><affiliation>George Mason University, USA</affiliation></editor>
      <editor><first>Kai</first><last>North</last><affiliation>Cambium Assessment, USA</affiliation></editor>
      <editor><first>Sanja</first><last>Štajner</last><affiliation>Karlsruhe, Germany</affiliation></editor>
      <editor><first>Regina</first><last>Stodden</last><affiliation>Heinrich Heine University Dusseldorf, Germany</affiliation></editor>
      <publisher>Association for Computational Linguistics</publisher>
      <address>Miami, Florida, USA</address>
      <month>November</month>
      <year>2024</year>
      <url hash="f06e8db2">2024.tsar-1</url>
      <venue>tsar</venue>
    </meta>
    <frontmatter>
      <url hash="bf3f39e5">2024.tsar-1.0</url>
      <bibkey>tsar-2024-1</bibkey>
    </frontmatter>
    <paper id="1">
      <title><fixed-case>M</fixed-case>ulti<fixed-case>LS</fixed-case>: An End-to-End Lexical Simplification Framework</title>
      <author><first>Kai</first><last>North</last><affiliation>George Mason University</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Tharindu</first><last>Ranasinghe</last><affiliation>Lancaster University</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Matthew</first><last>Shardlow</last><affiliation>Manchester Metropolitan University</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Marcos</first><last>Zampieri</last><affiliation>George Mason University</affiliation></author>
      <pages>1-11</pages>
      <abstract>Lexical Simplification (LS) automatically replaces difficult to read words for easier alternatives while preserving a sentence’s original meaning. Several datasets exist for LS and each of them specialize in one or two sub-tasks within the LS pipeline. However, as of this moment, no single LS dataset has been developed that covers all LS sub-tasks. We present MultiLS, the first LS framework that allows for the creation of a multi-task LS dataset. We also present MultiLS-PT, the first dataset created using the MultiLS framework. We demonstrate the potential of MultiLS-PT by carrying out all LS sub-tasks of (1) lexical complexity prediction (LCP), (2) substitute generation, and (3) substitute ranking for Portuguese.</abstract>
      <url hash="1c7a58c4">2024.tsar-1.1</url>
      <bibkey>north-etal-2024-multils</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="2">
      <title><fixed-case>O</fixed-case>to<fixed-case>BERT</fixed-case>: Identifying Suffixed Verbal Forms in <fixed-case>M</fixed-case>odern <fixed-case>H</fixed-case>ebrew Literature</title>
      <author><first>Avi</first><last>Shmidman</last><affiliation>Bar Ilan University and DICTA</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Shaltiel</first><last>Shmidman</last><affiliation>Dicta</affiliation></author>
      <pages>12-19</pages>
      <abstract>We provide a solution for a specific morphological obstacle which often makes Hebrew literature difficult to parse for the younger generation. The morphologically-rich nature of the Hebrew language allows pronominal direct objects to be realized as bound morphemes, suffixed to the verb. Although such suffixes are often utilized in Biblical Hebrew, their use has all but disappeared in modern Hebrew. Nevertheless, authors of modern Hebrew literature, in their search for literary flair, do make use of such forms. These unusual forms are notorious for alienating young readers from Hebrew literature, especially because these rare suffixed forms are often orthographically identical to common Hebrew words with different meanings. Upon encountering such words, readers naturally select the usual analysis of the word; yet, upon completing the sentence, they find themselves confounded. Young readers end up feeling “tricked”, and this in turn contributes to their alienation from the text. In order to address this challenge, we pretrained a new BERT model specifically geared to identify such forms, so that they may be automatically simplified and/or flagged. We release this new BERT model to the public for unrestricted use.</abstract>
      <url hash="e6c1dc7d">2024.tsar-1.2</url>
      <bibkey>shmidman-shmidman-2024-otobert</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="3">
      <title><fixed-case>C</fixed-case>omp<fixed-case>L</fixed-case>ex-<fixed-case>ZH</fixed-case>: A New Dataset for Lexical Complexity Prediction in <fixed-case>M</fixed-case>andarin and <fixed-case>C</fixed-case>antonese</title>
      <author><first>Le</first><last>Qiu</last><affiliation>The Hong Kong Polytechnic University</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Shanyue</first><last>Guo</last><affiliation>The Hong Kong Polytechnic University</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Tak-Sum</first><last>Wong</last><affiliation>Department of Chinese and Bilingual Studies</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Emmanuele</first><last>Chersoni</last><affiliation>Hong Kong Polytechnic University</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>John</first><last>Lee</last><affiliation>City University of Hong Kong</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Chu-Ren</first><last>Huang</last><affiliation>The Hong Kong Polytechnic Universiy</affiliation></author>
      <pages>20-26</pages>
      <abstract>The prediction of lexical complexity in context is assuming an increasing relevance in Natural Language Processing research, since identifying complex words is often the first step of text simplification pipelines. To the best of our knowledge, though, datasets annotated with complex words are available only for English and for a limited number of Western languages.In our paper, we introduce CompLex-ZH, a dataset including words annotated with complexity scores in sentential contexts for Chinese. Our data include sentences in Mandarin and Cantonese, which were selected from a variety of sources and textual genres. We provide a first evaluation with baselines combining hand-crafted and language models-based features.</abstract>
      <url hash="14e7f4f4">2024.tsar-1.3</url>
      <bibkey>qiu-etal-2024-complex</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="4">
      <title>Images Speak Volumes: User-Centric Assessment of Image Generation for Accessible Communication</title>
      <author><first>Miriam</first><last>Anschütz</last><affiliation>Technical University of Munich</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Tringa</first><last>Sylaj</last><affiliation>Technical University of Munich</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Georg</first><last>Groh</last><affiliation>TUM</affiliation></author>
      <pages>27-40</pages>
      <abstract>Explanatory images play a pivotal role in accessible and easy-to-read (E2R) texts. However, the images available in online databases are not tailored toward the respective texts, and the creation of customized images is expensive. In this large-scale study, we investigated whether text-to-image generation models can close this gap by providing customizable images quickly and easily. We benchmarked seven, four open- and three closed-source, image generation models and provide an extensive evaluation of the resulting images. In addition, we performed a user study with people from the E2R target group to examine whether the images met their requirements. We find that some of the models show remarkable performance, but none of the models are ready to be used at a larger scale without human supervision. Our research is an important step toward facilitating the creation of accessible information for E2R creators and tailoring accessible images to the target group’s needs.</abstract>
      <url hash="e9776d0c">2024.tsar-1.4</url>
      <bibkey>anschutz-etal-2024-images</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="5">
      <title>Cochrane-auto: An Aligned Dataset for the Simplification of Biomedical Abstracts</title>
      <author><first>Jan</first><last>Bakker</last><affiliation>University of Amsterdam</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Jaap</first><last>Kamps</last><affiliation>University of Amsterdam</affiliation></author>
      <pages>41-51</pages>
      <abstract>The most reliable and up-to-date information on health questions is in the biomedical literature, but inaccessible due to the complex language full of jargon. Domain specific scientific text simplification holds the promise to make this literature accessible to a lay audience. Therefore, we create Cochrane-auto: a large corpus of pairs of aligned sentences, paragraphs, and abstracts from biomedical abstracts and lay summaries. Experiments demonstrate that a plan-guided simplification system trained on Cochrane-auto is able to outperform a strong baseline trained on unaligned abstracts and lay summaries. More generally, our freely available corpus complementing Newsela-auto and Wiki-auto facilitates text simplification research beyond the sentence-level and direct lexical and grammatical revisions.</abstract>
      <url hash="c60c9c44">2024.tsar-1.5</url>
      <bibkey>bakker-kamps-2024-cochrane</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="6">
      <title>Considering Human Interaction and Variability in Automatic Text Simplification</title>
      <author><first>Jenia</first><last>Kim</last><affiliation>HU University of Applied Sciences Utrecht</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Stefan</first><last>Leijnen</last><affiliation>HU University of Applied Sciences Utrecht</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Lisa</first><last>Beinborn</last><affiliation>Unviersity of Goettingen</affiliation></author>
      <pages>52-60</pages>
      <abstract>Research into automatic text simplification aims to promote access to information for all members of society. To facilitate generalizability, simplification research often abstracts away from specific use cases, and targets a prototypical reader and an underspecified content creator. In this paper, we consider a real-world use case – simplification technology for use in Dutch municipalities – and identify the needs of the content creators and the target audiences in this use case. The stakeholders envision a system that (a) assists the human writer without taking over the task; (b) can provide diverse alternative outputs, tailored for specific target audiences; and (c) can explain and motivate the suggestions that it outputs. These requirements call for technology that is characterized by modularity, explainability, and variability. We believe that these are important research directions that require further exploration.</abstract>
      <url hash="1a42cf44">2024.tsar-1.6</url>
      <bibkey>kim-etal-2024-considering</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="7">
      <title>Society of Medical Simplifiers</title>
      <author><first>Chen</first><last>Lyu</last><affiliation>University of Warwick</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Gabriele</first><last>Pergola</last><affiliation>University of Warwick</affiliation></author>
      <pages>61-68</pages>
      <abstract>Medical text simplification is crucial for making complex biomedical literature more accessible to non-experts. Traditional methods struggle with the specialized terms and jargon of medical texts, lacking the flexibility to adapt the simplification process dynamically. In contrast, recent advancements in large language models (LLMs) present unique opportunities by offering enhanced control over text simplification through iterative refinement and collaboration between specialized agents. In this work, we introduce the Society of Medical Simplifiers, a novel LLM-based framework inspired by the “Society of Mind” (SOM) philosophy. Our approach leverages the strengths of LLMs by assigning five distinct roles, i.e., Layperson, Simplifier, Medical Expert, Language Clarifier, and Redundancy Checker, organized into interaction loops. This structure allows the agents to progressively improve text simplification while maintaining the complexity and accuracy of the original content. Evaluations on the Cochrane text simplification dataset demonstrate that our framework is on par with or outperforms state-of-the-art methods, achieving superior readability and content preservation through controlled simplification processes.</abstract>
      <url hash="49283047">2024.tsar-1.7</url>
      <bibkey>lyu-pergola-2024-society</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="8">
      <title>Difficult for Whom? A Study of <fixed-case>J</fixed-case>apanese Lexical Complexity</title>
      <author><first>Adam</first><last>Nohejl</last><affiliation>Nara Institute of Science and Technology</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Akio</first><last>Hayakawa</last><affiliation>Universitat Pompeu Fabra</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Yusuke</first><last>Ide</last><affiliation>Nara Institute of Science and Technology</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Taro</first><last>Watanabe</last><affiliation>Nara Institute of Science and Technology</affiliation></author>
      <pages>69-81</pages>
      <abstract>The tasks of lexical complexity prediction (LCP) and complex word identification (CWI) commonly presuppose that difficult-to-understand words are shared by the target population. Meanwhile, personalization methods have also been proposed to adapt models to individual needs. We verify that a recent Japanese LCP dataset is representative of its target population by partially replicating the annotation. By another reannotation we show that native Chinese speakers perceive the complexity differently due to Sino-Japanese vocabulary. To explore the possibilities of personalization, we compare competitive baselines trained on the group mean ratings and individual ratings in terms of performance for an individual. We show that the model trained on a group mean performs similarly to an individual model in the CWI task, while achieving good LCP performance for an individual is difficult. We also experiment with adapting a finetuned BERT model, which results only in marginal improvements across all settings.</abstract>
      <url hash="c54b4ed2">2024.tsar-1.8</url>
      <bibkey>nohejl-etal-2024-difficult</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="9">
      <title>Lexical Complexity Prediction and Lexical Simplification for <fixed-case>C</fixed-case>atalan and <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>panish: Resource Creation, Quality Assessment, and Ethical Considerations</title>
      <author><first>Horacio</first><last>Saggion</last><affiliation>Universitat Pompeu Fabra</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Stefan</first><last>Bott</last><affiliation>Universitat Pompeu Fabra</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Sandra</first><last>Szasz</last><affiliation>Universitat Pompeu Fabra</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Nelson</first><last>Pérez</last><affiliation>Instituto Tecnológico de Costa Rica</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Saúl</first><last>Calderón</last><affiliation>Intituto Tecnológico de Costa Rica</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Martín</first><last>Solís</last><affiliation>Instituto Tecnológico de Costa Rica</affiliation></author>
      <pages>82-94</pages>
      <abstract>Automatic lexical simplification is a task to substitute lexical items that may be unfamiliar and difficult to understand with easier and more common words. This paper presents the description and analysis of two novel datasets for lexical simplification in Spanish and Catalan. This dataset represents the first of its kind in Catalan and a substantial addition to the sparse data on automatic lexical simplification which is available for Spanish. Specifically, it is the first dataset for Spanish which includes scalar ratings of the understanding difficulty of lexical items. In addition, we present a detailed analysis aiming at assessing the appropriateness and ethical dimensions of the data for the lexical simplification task.</abstract>
      <url hash="ac03e771">2024.tsar-1.9</url>
      <bibkey>saggion-etal-2024-lexical</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="10">
      <title><fixed-case>S</fixed-case>ci<fixed-case>G</fixed-case>is<fixed-case>P</fixed-case>y: a Novel Metric for Biomedical Text Simplification via Gist Inference Score</title>
      <author><first>Chen</first><last>Lyu</last><affiliation>University of Warwick</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Gabriele</first><last>Pergola</last><affiliation>University of Warwick</affiliation></author>
      <pages>95-106</pages>
      <abstract>Biomedical literature is often written in highly specialized language, posing significant comprehension challenges for non-experts. Automatic text simplification (ATS) offers a solution by making such texts more accessible while preserving critical information. However, evaluating ATS for biomedical texts is still challenging due to the limitations of existing evaluation metrics. General-domain metrics like SARI, BLEU, and ROUGE focus on surface-level text features, and readability metrics like FKGL and ARI fail to account for domain-specific terminology or assess how well the simplified text conveys core meanings (gist). To address this, we introduce SciGisPy, a novel evaluation metric inspired by Gist Inference Score (GIS) from Fuzzy-Trace Theory (FTT). SciGisPy measures how well a simplified text facilitates the formation of abstract inferences (gist) necessary for comprehension, especially in the biomedical domain. We revise GIS for this purpose by introducing domain-specific enhancements, including semantic chunking, Information Content (IC) theory, and specialized embeddings, while removing unsuitable indexes. Our experimental evaluation on the Cochrane biomedical text simplification dataset demonstrates that SciGisPy outperforms the original GIS formulation, with a significant increase in correctly identified simplified texts (84% versus 44.8%). The results and a thorough ablation study confirm that SciGisPy better captures the essential meaning of biomedical content, outperforming existing approaches.</abstract>
      <url hash="c17a419b">2024.tsar-1.10</url>
      <bibkey>lyu-pergola-2024-scigispy</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="11">
      <title><fixed-case>EASSE</fixed-case>-<fixed-case>DE</fixed-case> &amp; <fixed-case>EASSE</fixed-case>-multi: Easier Automatic Sentence Simplification Evaluation for <fixed-case>G</fixed-case>erman &amp; Multiple Languages</title>
      <author><first>Regina</first><last>Stodden</last><affiliation>Computational Linguistics Department, Heinrich Heine University Düsseldorf</affiliation></author>
      <pages>107-116</pages>
      <abstract>In this work, we propose EASSE-multi, a framework for easier automatic sentence evaluation for languages other than English. Compared to the original EASSE framework, EASSE-multi does not focus only on English.It contains tokenizers and versions of text simplification evaluation metrics which are suitable for multiple languages. In this paper, we exemplify the usage of EASSE-multi for German TS resulting in EASSE-DE. Further, we compare text simplification results when evaluating with different language or tokenization settings of the metrics. Based on this, we formulate recommendations on how to make the evaluation of (German) TS models more transparent and better comparable. Additionally, we present a benchmark on German TS evaluated with EASSE-DE and make its resources (i.e., test sets, system outputs, and evaluation reports) available. The code of EASSE-multi and its German specialisation (EASSE-DE) can be found at https://github.com/rstodden/easse-multi and https://github.com/rstodden/easse-de.</abstract>
      <url hash="51045588">2024.tsar-1.11</url>
      <bibkey>stodden-2024-easse</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="12">
      <title>Evaluating the Simplification of <fixed-case>B</fixed-case>razilian Legal Rulings in <fixed-case>LLM</fixed-case>s Using Readability Scores as a Target</title>
      <author><first>Antonio Flavio</first><last>Paula</last><affiliation>Universidade Federal de Goiás</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Celso</first><last>Camilo-Junior</last><affiliation>Institute of Informatics, Federal University of Goiás</affiliation></author>
      <pages>117-125</pages>
      <abstract>Legal documents are often characterized by complex language, including jargon and technical terms, making them challenging for Natural Language Processing (NLP) applications. We apply the readability-controlled text modification task with an emphasis on legal texts simplification. Additionally, our work explores an evaluation based on the comparison of word complexity in the documents using Zipf scale, demonstrating the models’ ability to simplify text according to the target readability scores, while also identifying a limit to this capability. Our results with Llama-3 and Sabiá-2 show that while the complexity score decreases with higher readability targets, there is a trade-off with reduced semantic similarity.</abstract>
      <url hash="d201556f">2024.tsar-1.12</url>
      <bibkey>paula-camilo-junior-2024-evaluating</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="13">
      <title>Measuring and Modifying the Readability of <fixed-case>E</fixed-case>nglish Texts with <fixed-case>GPT</fixed-case>-4</title>
      <author><first>Sean</first><last>Trott</last><affiliation>UC San Diego</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Pamela</first><last>Rivière</last><affiliation>UC San Diego</affiliation></author>
      <pages>126-134</pages>
      <abstract>The success of Large Language Models (LLMs) in other domains has raised the question of whether LLMs can reliably assess and manipulate the readability of text. We approach this question empirically. First, using a published corpus of 4,724 English text excerpts, we find that readability estimates produced “zero-shot” from GPT-4 Turbo and GPT-4o mini exhibit relatively high correlation with human judgments (r = 0.76 and r = 0.74, respectively), out-performing estimates derived from traditional readability formulas and various psycholinguistic indices. Then, in a pre-registered human experiment (N = 59), we ask whether Turbo can reliably make text easier or harder to read. We find evidence to support this hypothesis, though considerable variance in human judgments remains unexplained. We conclude by discussing the limitations of this approach, including limited scope, as well as the validity of the “readability” construct and its dependence on context, audience, and goal.</abstract>
      <url hash="e80c1741">2024.tsar-1.13</url>
      <bibkey>trott-riviere-2024-measuring</bibkey>
    </paper>
  </volume>
</collection>
