<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<collection id="2025.wasp">
  <volume id="main" ingest-date="2026-01-13" type="proceedings">
    <meta>
      <booktitle>Proceedings of the Third Workshop for Artificial Intelligence for Scientific Publications</booktitle>
      <editor><first>Alberto</first><last>Accomazzi</last></editor>
      <editor><first>Tirthankar</first><last>Ghosal</last></editor>
      <editor><first>Felix</first><last>Grezes</last></editor>
      <editor><first>Kelly</first><last>Lockhart</last></editor>
      <publisher>Association for Computational Linguistics</publisher>
      <address>Mumbai, India and virtual</address>
      <month>December</month>
      <year>2025</year>
      <url hash="f6eaca89">2025.wasp-main</url>
      <venue>wasp</venue>
      <venue>ws</venue>
      <isbn>979-8-89176-310-4</isbn>
    </meta>
    <frontmatter>
      <url hash="92d0fddd">2025.wasp-main.0</url>
      <bibkey>wasp-ws-2025-main</bibkey>
    </frontmatter>
    <paper id="1">
      <title>Overview of the Third Workshop for Artificial Intelligence for Scientific Publications</title>
      <author><first>Kelly</first><last>Lockhart</last><affiliation>Harvard-Smithsonian Center for Astrophysics</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Alberto</first><last>Accomazzi</last><affiliation>Harvard-Smithsonian Center for Astrophysics</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Felix</first><last>Grezes</last><affiliation>Harvard-Smithsonian Center for Astrophysics</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Tirthankar</first><last>Ghosal</last><affiliation>Oak Ridge National Laboratory</affiliation></author>
      <pages>1-4</pages>
      <abstract>The Workshop for Artificial Intelligence for Scientific Publications (WASP), formerly Workshop on Information Extraction from Scientific Publications (WIESP), started in 2022 to provide a platform for researchers to discuss research on information extraction, mining, generation, and knowledge discovery from scientific publications using Natural Language Processing and Machine Learning techniques. The third WASP workshop was held at the 14th International Joint Conference on Natural Language Processing and 4th Asia-Pacific Chapter of the Association for Computational Linguistics in Mumbai, India on December 23rd, 2025, as a hybrid event. The WASP workshop saw great interest, with 29 submissions, of which 16 were accepted. The program consisted of the contributed research talks, 2 keynote talks, a panel discussion, and one shared task, Telescope Reference and Astronomy Categorization Shared task (TRACS).</abstract>
      <url hash="ef69dfa2">2025.wasp-main.1</url>
      <bibkey>lockhart-etal-2025-overview</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="2">
      <title>Overview of <fixed-case>TRACS</fixed-case>: the Telescope Reference and Astronomy Categorization Dataset &amp; Shared Task</title>
      <author><first>Felix</first><last>Grezes</last><affiliation>Harvard-Smithsonian Center for Astrophysics</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Jennifer Lynn</first><last>Bartlett</last><affiliation>Harvard-Smithsonian Center for Astrophysics</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Kelly</first><last>Lockhart</last><affiliation>Harvard-Smithsonian Center for Astrophysics</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Alberto</first><last>Accomazzi</last><affiliation>Harvard-Smithsonian Center for Astrophysics</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Ethan</first><last>Seefried</last><affiliation>Oak Ridge National Laboratory</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Anjali</first><last>Pandiri</last><affiliation>Florida State University</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Tirthankar</first><last>Ghosal</last><affiliation>Oak Ridge National Laboratory</affiliation></author>
      <pages>5-15</pages>
      <abstract>To evaluate the scientific influence of observational facilities, astronomers examine the body of publications that have utilized data from those facilities. This depends on curated bibliographies that annotate and connect data products to the corresponding literature, enabling bibliometric analyses to quantify data impact. Compiling such bibliographies is a demanding process that requires expert curators to scan the literature for relevant names, acronyms, and identifiers, and then to determine whether and how specific observations contributed to each publication. These bibliographies have value beyond impact assessment: for research scientists, explicit links between data and literature form an essential pathway for discovering and accessing data. Accordingly, by building on the work of librarians and archivists, telescope bibliographies can be repurposed to directly support scientific inquiry. In this context, we present the Telescope Reference and Astronomy Categorization Shared task (TRACS) and its accompanying dataset, which comprises more than 89,000 publicly available English-language texts drawn from space telescope bibliographies. These texts are labeled according to a new, compact taxonomy developed in consultation with experienced bibliographers.</abstract>
      <url hash="da54d39d">2025.wasp-main.2</url>
      <bibkey>grezes-etal-2025-overview</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="3">
      <title>Exploring Health Misinformation Detection with Multi-Agent Debate</title>
      <author><first>Chih-Han</first><last>Chen</last><affiliation>National Taiwan University</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Chen-Han</first><last>Tsai</last><affiliation>HTC DeepQ</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Yu-Shao</first><last>Peng</last><affiliation>HTC DeepQ</affiliation></author>
      <pages>16-21</pages>
      <abstract>Fact-checking health-related claims has become increasingly critical as misinformation proliferates online. Effective verification requires both the retrieval of high-quality evidence and rigorous reasoning processes. In this paper, we propose a two-stage framework for health misinformation detection: Agreement Score Prediction followed by Multi-Agent Debate. In the first stage, we employ large language models (LLMs) to independently evaluate retrieved articles and compute an aggregated agreement score that reflects the overall evidence stance. When this score indicates insufficient consensus—falling below a predefined threshold—the system proceeds to a second stage. Multiple agents engage in structured debate to synthesize conflicting evidence and generate well-reasoned verdicts with explicit justifications. Experimental results demonstrate that our two-stage approach achieves superior performance compared to baseline methods, highlighting the value of combining automated scoring with collaborative reasoning for complex verification tasks.</abstract>
      <url hash="86b4767d">2025.wasp-main.3</url>
      <bibkey>chen-etal-2025-exploring-health</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="4">
      <title>Zero-Shot Cross-Sentential Scientific Relation Extraction via Entity-Guided Summarization</title>
      <author><first>Vani</first><last>Kanjirangat</last><affiliation>SUPSI, IDSIA, Switzerland</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Fabio</first><last>Rinaldi</last><affiliation>SUPSI, IDSIA, Switzerland</affiliation></author>
      <pages>22-33</pages>
      <abstract>Structured information extraction (IE) from scientific abstracts is increasingly leveraging large language models (LLMs). A crucial step in IE is relation extraction (RE), which becomes challenging when entity relations span sentences. Traditional path-based methods, such as shortest dependency paths, are often unable to handle cross-sentential relations effectively. Although LLMs have been utilized as zero-shot learners for IE tasks, they continue to struggle with capturing long-range dependencies and multi-hop reasoning. In this work, we propose using GPT as a zero-shot entity-guided summarizer to encapsulate cross-sentential context into a single-sentence summary for relation extraction. We perform intrinsic evaluations, comparing our approach against direct zero-shot prompting on biomedical scientific abstracts. On the Chemical-Disease Relation (CDR) dataset, our method achieves a 7-point improvement in overall F-score and 6 points for cross-sentential relations. On the Gene-Disease Association (GDA) dataset, we observe an 8-point gain for inter-sentential relations. These results demonstrate that entity-guided summarization with GPT can enhance zero-shot biomedical RE, supporting more effective structured information extraction from scientific texts.</abstract>
      <url hash="6a0f5004">2025.wasp-main.4</url>
      <bibkey>kanjirangat-rinaldi-2025-zero</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="5">
      <title>Finding the Paper Behind the Data: Automatic Identification of Research Articles related to Data Publications</title>
      <author><first>Barbara</first><last>McGillivray</last><affiliation>King’s College London</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Kaveh</first><last>Aryan</last><affiliation>King’s College London</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Viola</first><last>Harperath</last><affiliation>King’s College London</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Marton</first><last>Ribary</last><affiliation>Royal Holloway, University of London</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Mandy</first><last>Wigdorowitz</last><affiliation>University of Alabama</affiliation></author>
      <pages>34-43</pages>
      <abstract>Data papers are scholarly publications that describe datasets in detail, including their structure, collection methods, and potential for reuse, typically without presenting new analyses. As data sharing becomes increasingly central to research workflows, linking data papers to relevant research papers is essential for improving transparency, reproducibility, and scholarly credit. However, these links are rarely made explicit in metadata and are often difficult to identify manually at scale. In this study, we present a comprehensive approach to automating the linking process using natural language processing (NLP) techniques. We evaluate both set-based and vector-based methods, including Jaccard similarity, TF-IDF, SBERT, and reranking with large language models. Our experiments on a curated benchmark dataset reveal that no single method consistently outperforms others across all metrics, in line with the multifaceted nature of the task. Set-based methods using frequent words (N=50) achieve the highest top-10% accuracy, closely followed by TF-IDF, which also leads in MRR and top-1% and top-5% accuracy. SBERT-based reranking with LLMs yields the best results in top-N accuracy. This dispersion suggests that different approaches capture complementary aspects of similarity (lexical, semantic, and contextual), showing the value of hybrid strategies for robust matching between data papers and research articles. For several methods, we find no statistically significant difference between using abstracts and full texts, suggesting that abstracts may be sufficient for effective matching. Our findings demonstrate the feasibility of scalable, automated linking between data papers and research articles, enabling more accurate bibliometric analyses, improved tracking of data reuse, and fairer credit assignment for data sharing. This contributes to a more transparent, interconnected, and accessible research ecosystem.</abstract>
      <url hash="1646f84f">2025.wasp-main.5</url>
      <bibkey>mcgillivray-etal-2025-finding</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="6">
      <title>A benchmark for end-to-end zero-shot biomedical relation extraction with <fixed-case>LLM</fixed-case>s: experiments with <fixed-case>O</fixed-case>pen<fixed-case>AI</fixed-case> models</title>
      <author><first>Aviv</first><last>Brokman</last><affiliation>University of Kentucky, USA</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Xuguang</first><last>Ai</last><affiliation>University of Kentucky, USA</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Yuhang</first><last>Jiang</last><affiliation>University of Kentucky, USA</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Shashank</first><last>Gupta</last><affiliation>University of Kentucky, USA</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Ramakanth</first><last>Kavuluru</last><affiliation>University of Kentucky, USA</affiliation></author>
      <pages>44-55</pages>
      <abstract>Extracting relations from scientific literature is a fundamental task in biomedical NLP because entities and relations among them drive hypothesis generation and knowledge discovery. As literature grows rapidly, relation extraction (RE) is indispensable to curate knowledge graphs to be used as computable structured and symbolic representations. With the rise of LLMs, it is pertinent to examine if it is better to skip tailoring supervised RE methods, save annotation burden, and just use zero shot RE (ZSRE) via LLM API calls. In this paper, we propose a benchmark with seven biomedical RE datasets with interesting characteristics and evaluate three Open AI models (GPT-4, o1, and GPT-OSS-120B) for end-to-end ZSRE. We show that LLM-based ZSRE is inching closer to supervised methods in performances on some datasets but still struggles on complex inputs expressing multiple relations with different predicates. Our error analysis reveals scope for improvements.</abstract>
      <url hash="0d9fbfa2">2025.wasp-main.6</url>
      <bibkey>brokman-etal-2025-benchmark</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="7">
      <title>Bridging the Gap: Instruction-Tuned <fixed-case>LLM</fixed-case>s for Scientific Named Entity Recognition</title>
      <author><first>Necva</first><last>Bölücü</last><affiliation>CSIRO Data61, Sydney, Australia</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Maciej</first><last>Rybinski</last><affiliation>ITIS, University of Málaga, Málaga, Spain</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Stephen</first><last>Wan</last><affiliation>CSIRO Data61, Sydney, Australia</affiliation></author>
      <pages>56-71</pages>
      <abstract>Information extraction (IE) from scientific literature plays an important role in many information-seeking pipelines. Large Language Models (LLMs) have demonstrated strong zero-shot and few-shot performance on IE tasks. However, there are challenges in practical deployment, especially in scenarios that involve sensitive information, such as industrial research or limited budgets. A key question is whether there is a need for a fine-tuned model for optimal domain adaptation (i.e., whether in-domain labelled training data is needed, or zero-shot to few-shot effectiveness is enough). In this paper, we explore this question in the context of IE on scientific literature. We further consider methodological questions, such as alternatives to cloud-based proprietary LLMs (e.g., GPT and Claude) when these are unsuitable due to data privacy, data sensitivity, or cost reasons. This paper outlines empirical results to recommend which locally hosted open-source LLM approach to adopt and illustrates the trade-offs in domain adaptation.</abstract>
      <url hash="8d94cce3">2025.wasp-main.7</url>
      <bibkey>bolucu-etal-2025-bridging</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="8">
      <title>Metadata Generation for Research Data from <fixed-case>URL</fixed-case> Citation Contexts in Scholarly Papers: Task Definition and Dataset Construction</title>
      <author><first>Yu</first><last>Watanabe</last><affiliation>Graduate School of Informatics, Nagoya University</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Koichiro</first><last>Ito</last><affiliation>Graduate School of Informatics, Nagoya University</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Shigeki</first><last>Matsubara</last><affiliation>Information Technology Center, Nagoya University</affiliation></author>
      <pages>72-79</pages>
      <abstract>This paper proposes a new research task aimed at automatically generating metadata for research data, such as datasets and code, to accelerate open science. From the perspective of ‘Findable’ in the FAIR data principles, research data is required to be assigned a global unique identifier and described with rich metadata. The proposed task is defined as extracting information about research data (specifically, name, generic mention, and in-text citation) from texts surrounding URLs that serve as identifiers for research data references in scholarly papers. To support this task, we constructed a dataset containing approximately 600 manually annotated citation contexts with URLs of research data from conference papers. To evaluate the task, we conducted a preliminary experiment using the constructed dataset, employing the In-Context Learning method with LLMs as a baseline. The results showed that the performance of LLMs matched that of humans in some cases, demonstrating the feasibility of the task.</abstract>
      <url hash="27222cc4">2025.wasp-main.8</url>
      <bibkey>watanabe-etal-2025-metadata</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="9">
      <title>Dynamic Reference Extraction and Linking across Multiple Scholarly Knowledge Graphs</title>
      <author><first>Nicolau</first><last>Duran-Silva</last><affiliation>SIRIS Lab, Research Division of SIRIS Academic, Barcelona, Spain</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Pablo</first><last>Accuosto</last><affiliation>LaSTUS Lab, TALN Group, Universitat Pompeu Fabra, Barcelona, Spain</affiliation></author>
      <pages>80-86</pages>
      <abstract>References are an important feature of scientific literature; however, they are unstructured, heterogeneous, noisy, and often multilingual. We present a modular pipeline that leverages fine-tuned transformer models for reference location, classification, parsing, retrieval, and re-ranking across multiple scholarly knowledge graphs, with a focus on multilingual and non-traditional sources such as patents and policy documents. Our main contributions are: a unified pipeline for reference extraction and linking across diverse document types, openly released annotated datasets, fine-tuned models for each subtask, and evaluations across multiple scholarly knowledge graphs, enabling richer, more inclusive infrastructures for open research information.</abstract>
      <url hash="a084c323">2025.wasp-main.9</url>
      <bibkey>duran-silva-accuosto-2025-dynamic</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="10">
      <title><fixed-case>AI</fixed-case> for Data Ingestion into <fixed-case>IPAC</fixed-case> Archives</title>
      <author><first>Nicholas</first><last>Susemiehl</last><affiliation>PAC, California Institute of Technology</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Joseph</first><last>Mazzarella</last><affiliation>PAC, California Institute of Technology</affiliation></author>
      <pages>87-93</pages>
      <abstract>The astronomical data archives at IPAC, including the NASA Extragalactic Database (NED) and NASA Exoplanet Archive (NEA), have served as repositories for data published in the literature for decades. Throughout this time, extracting data from journal articles has remained a challenging task and future large data releases will exasperate this problem. We seek to accelerate the rate at which data can be extracted from journal articles and reformatted into database load files by leveraging recent advances in natural language processing enabled by AI. We are developing a new suite of tools to semi-automate information retrieval from scientific journal articles. Manual methods to extract and prepare data, which can take hours for some articles, are being replaced with AI-powered tools that can compress the task to minutes. A combination of AI and non-AI methods, along with human supervision, can substantially accelerate archive data ingestion. Challenges remain for improving accuracy, capturing data in external files, and flagging issues such as mislabeled object names and missing metadata.</abstract>
      <url hash="84d4342b">2025.wasp-main.10</url>
      <bibkey>susemiehl-mazzarella-2025-ai</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="11">
      <title>A Hybrid <fixed-case>LLM</fixed-case> and Supervised Model Pipeline for Polymer Property Extraction from Tables in Scientific Literature</title>
      <author><first>Van-Thuy</first><last>Phi</last><affiliation>RIKEN Center for Advanced Intelligence Project</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Dinh-Truong</first><last>Do</last><affiliation>RIKEN Center for Advanced Intelligence Project</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Hoang-An</first><last>Trieu</last><affiliation>RIKEN Center for Advanced Intelligence Project</affiliation></author>
      <author id="yuji-matsumoto"><first>Yuji</first><last>Matsumoto</last><affiliation>RIKEN Center for Advanced Intelligence Project</affiliation></author>
      <pages>94-102</pages>
      <abstract>Extracting structured information from tables in scientific literature is a critical yet challenging task for building domain-specific knowledge bases. This paper addresses extraction of 5-ary polymer property tuples: (POLYMER, PROP_NAME, PROP_VALUE, CONDITION, CHAR_METHOD). We introduce and systematically compare two distinct methodologies: (1) a novel two-stage Hybrid Pipeline that first utilizes Large Language Models (LLMs) for table-to-text conversion, which is then processed by specialized text-based extraction models; and (2) an end-to-end Direct LLM Extraction approach. To evaluate these methods, we employ a systematic, domain-aligned evaluation setup based on the expert-curated PoLyInfo database. Our results demonstrate the clear superiority of the hybrid pipeline. When using Claude Sonnet 4.5 for the linearization stage, the pipeline achieves a score of 67.92% F1@PoLyInfo, significantly outperforming the best direct LLM extraction approach (Claude Sonnet 4.5 at 56.66%). This work establishes the effectiveness of a hybrid architecture that combines the generative strengths of LLMs with the precision of specialized supervised models for structured data extraction.</abstract>
      <url hash="3f6fef4c">2025.wasp-main.11</url>
      <bibkey>phi-etal-2025-hybrid</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="12">
      <title><fixed-case>T</fixed-case>e<fixed-case>G</fixed-case>-<fixed-case>DR</fixed-case>ec: Inductive Text-Graph Learning for Unseen Node Scientific Dataset Recommendation</title>
      <author><first>Ammar</first><last>Qayyum</last><affiliation>Integrated Graduate School of Medicine, Engineering, and Agricultural Sciences, University of Yamanashi</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Bassamtiano</first><last>Irnawan</last><affiliation>Integrated Graduate School of Medicine, Engineering, and Agricultural Sciences, University of Yamanashi</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Fumiyo</first><last>Fukumoto</last><affiliation>Graduate Faculty of Interdisciplinary Research, University of Yamanashi</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Latifah</first><last>Kamarudin</last><affiliation>Centre of Excellence for Advanced Sensor Technology Universiti Malaysia Perlis</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Kentaro</first><last>Go</last><affiliation>Graduate Faculty of Interdisciplinary Research, University of Yamanashi</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Yoshimi</first><last>Suzuki</last><affiliation>Graduate Faculty of Interdisciplinary Research, University of Yamanashi</affiliation></author>
      <pages>103-114</pages>
      <abstract>Scientific datasets are crucial for evaluating scientific research, and their number is increasing rapidly. Most scientific dataset recommendation systems use Information Retrieval (IR) methods that model semantics while overlooking interactions. Graph Neural Networks (GNNs) excel at handling interactions between entities but often overlook textual content, limiting their ability to generalise to unseen nodes. We propose TeG-DRec, a framework for scientific dataset recommendation that integrates GNNs and textual content via a subgraph generation module to ensure correct propagation throughout the model, enabling handling of unseen data. Experimental results on the dataset recommendation’s dataset show that our method outperformed the baselines for text-based IR and graph-based recommendation systems. Our source code is available at https://github.com/Maqif14/TeG-DRec.git</abstract>
      <url hash="c0e9883f">2025.wasp-main.12</url>
      <bibkey>qayyum-etal-2025-teg</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="13">
      <title>Structured Outputs in Prompt Engineering: Enhancing <fixed-case>LLM</fixed-case> Adaptability on Counterintuitive Instructions</title>
      <author><first>Jingjing</first><last>Ye</last><affiliation>Independent Researcher</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Song</first><last>Bai</last><affiliation>Independent Researcher</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Zhenyang</first><last>Li</last><affiliation>Independent Researcher</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Zheqi</first><last>Zone</last><affiliation>Independent Researcher</affiliation></author>
      <pages>115-120</pages>
      <abstract>Large Language Models (LLMs) have demonstrated remarkable capabilities in natural language processing tasks, yet they often exhibit cognitive inertia, rigidly adhering to ingrained training conventions even when prompted to deviate. This paper investigates the efficacy of structured output techniques in prompt engineering to mitigate such inertia and improve instruction-following on counterintuitive tasks. We argue that using the structured input and output with our framework yields significant performance gains, studied on the Inversed IFEval dataset across varying prompts and domains. This work contributes to the growing field of prompt engineering research by demonstrating structured outputs as a robust method for enhancing LLM logical reasoning.</abstract>
      <url hash="5b33327e">2025.wasp-main.13</url>
      <bibkey>ye-etal-2025-structured</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="14">
      <title>Atlas: Customizing Large Language Models for Reliable Bibliographic Retrieval and Verification</title>
      <author><first>Akash</first><last>Kodali</last><affiliation>California State University, Long Beach</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Hailu</first><last>Xu</last><affiliation>California State University, Long Beach</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Wenlu</first><last>Zhang</last><affiliation>California State University, Long Beach</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Xin</first><last>Qin</last><affiliation>California State University, Long Beach</affiliation></author>
      <pages>121-126</pages>
      <abstract>Large Language Models (LLMs) are increasingly used for citation retrieval, yet their bibliographic outputs often contain hallucinated or inconsistent metadata. This paper examines whether structured prompting improves citation reliability compared with traditional API-based retrieval. We implement a three-stage BibTeX-fetching pipeline: a baseline Crossref resolver, a standard GPT prompting method, and a customized verification-guided GPT configuration. Across heterogeneous reference inputs, we evaluate retrieval coverage, field completeness, and metadata accuracy against Crossref ground truth. Results show that prompting improves coverage and completeness. Our findings highlight the importance of prompt design for building reliable, LLM-driven bibliographic retrieval systems.</abstract>
      <url hash="e4b0bd8f">2025.wasp-main.14</url>
      <bibkey>kodali-etal-2025-atlas</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="15">
      <title>Automated Telescope-Paper Linkage via Multi-Model Ensemble Learning</title>
      <author><first>Ojaswa</first><last>Ojaswa Varshney</last><affiliation>IIIT, Surat, India</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Prashasti</first><last>Vyas</last><affiliation>IIIT, Surat, India</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Priyanka</first><last>Goyal</last><affiliation>IIIT, Surat, India</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Tarpita</first><last>Singh</last><affiliation>IIIT, Surat, India</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Ritesh</first><last>Kumar</last><affiliation>IIIT, Surat, India</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Mayank</first><last>Singh</last><affiliation>IIT Gandhinagar, India</affiliation></author>
      <pages>127-135</pages>
      <abstract>Automated linkage between scientific publications and telescope datasets is a cornerstone for scalable bibliometric analyses and ensuring scientific reproducibility in astrophysics. We propose a multi-model ensemble architecture integrating transformer models DeBERTa, RoBERTa, and TF-IDF logistic regression, tailored to the WASP-2025 shared task on telescope-paper classification. Our approach achieves a macro F1 score approaching 0.78 after extensive multi-seed ensembling and per-label threshold tuning, significantly outperforming baseline models. This paper presents comprehensive methodology, ablation studies, and an in-depth discussion of challenges, establishing a robust benchmark for scientific bibliometric task automation.</abstract>
      <url hash="f26caa7b">2025.wasp-main.15</url>
      <bibkey>ojaswa-varshney-etal-2025-automated</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="16">
      <title>Systematic Evaluation of Machine Learning and Transformer-Based Methods for Scientific Telescope Literature Classification</title>
      <author><first>Huynh Trung</first><last>Kiet</last><affiliation>University of Science, VNU-HCM</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Dao Sy Duy</first><last>Minh</last><affiliation>University of Science, VNU-HCM</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Tran Chi</first><last>Nguyen</last><affiliation>University of Science, VNU-HCM</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Nguyen Lam Phu</first><last>Quy</last><affiliation>University of Science, VNU-HCM</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Pham Phu</first><last>Hoa</last><affiliation>University of Science, VNU-HCM</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Nguyen Dinh Ha</first><last>Duong</last><affiliation>University of Science, VNU-HCM</affiliation></author>
      <author id="dinh-dien"><first>Dinh</first><last>Dien</last><affiliation>University of Science, VNU-HCM</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Nguyen Hong Buu</first><last>Long</last><affiliation>University of Science, VNU-HCM</affiliation></author>
      <pages>136-145</pages>
      <abstract>Recent space missions such as Hubble, Chandra, and JWST have produced a rapidly growing body of scientific literature. Maintaining telescope bibliographies is essential for mission assessment and research traceability, yet current curation processes rely heavily on manual annotation and do not scale. To facilitate progress in this direction, the TRACS @ WASP 2025 shared task provides a benchmark for automatic telescope bibliographic classification based on scientific publications. In this work, we conduct a comparative study of modeling strategies for this task. We first explore traditional machine learning methods such as multinomial Naive Bayes with TF–IDF and CountVectorizer representations. We then evaluate transformer-based multi-label classification using BERT-based scientific language models. Finally, we investigate a task-wise classification approach, where we decompose the problem into separate prediction tasks and train a dedicated model for each. In addition, we experiment with a limited-resource LLM-based approach, showing that even without full fine-tuning and using only a partial subset of the training data, LLMs exhibit promising potential for telescope classification. Our best system achieves a macro F1 of 0.72 with BERT-based models on the test evaluation, substantially outperforming the official openai-gpt-oss-20b baseline (0.31 macro F1).</abstract>
      <url hash="65da4ac0">2025.wasp-main.16</url>
      <bibkey>kiet-etal-2025-systematic</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="17">
      <title>“Clutch or Cry” Team at <fixed-case>TRACS</fixed-case> @ <fixed-case>WASP</fixed-case>2025: A Hybrid Stacking Ensemble for Astrophysical Document Classification</title>
      <author><first>Arshad</first><last>Khatib</last><affiliation>Department of Artificial Intelligence, SVNIT Surat</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Aayush</first><last>Prasad</last><affiliation>Department of Artificial Intelligence, SVNIT Surat</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Rudra</first><last>Trivedi</last><affiliation>Department of Artificial Intelligence, SVNIT Surat</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Shrikant</first><last>Malviya</last><affiliation>Department of Computer Science and Engineering, SVNIT Surat</affiliation></author>
      <pages>146-156</pages>
      <abstract>Automatically identifying telescopes and their roles within astrophysical literature is crucial for large-scale scientific analysis and tracking instrument usage patterns. This paper describes the system developed by the “Clutch or Cry” team for the Telescope Reference and Astronomy Categorization Shared task (TRACS) at WASP 2025. The task involved two distinct challenges: multi-class telescope identification (Task 1) and multi-label role classification (Task 2). For Task 1, we employed a feature-centric approach combining document identifiers, metadata, and textual features to achieve high accuracy. For the more complex Task 2, we utilized a carefully designed two-level stacking ensemble. This hybrid model effectively fused symbolic information from a rule-based classifier with deep semantic understanding from a domain-adapted transformer. A subsequent meta-learning stage then performed targeted optimization for each role. These architectures were designed to address the primary challenges of handling long documents and managing severe class imbalance. A systematic optimization strategy focused on mitigating this imbalance significantly improved performance for minority classes. This work validates the effectiveness of using tailored, hybrid approaches and targeted optimization for complex classification tasks in specialized scientific domains.</abstract>
      <url hash="7031bab2">2025.wasp-main.17</url>
      <bibkey>khatib-etal-2025-clutch</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="18">
      <title>amc: The Automated Mission Classifier for Telescope Bibliographies</title>
      <author><first>John F.</first><last>Wu</last><affiliation>Space Telescope Science Institute</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Joshua E.G.</first><last>Peek</last><affiliation>Space Telescope Science Institute</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Sophie J.</first><last>Miller</last><affiliation>Space Telescope Science Institute</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Jenny</first><last>Novacescu</last><affiliation>Space Telescope Science Institute</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Achu J.</first><last>Usha</last><affiliation>Space Telescope Science Institute</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Christopher A.</first><last>Wilkinson</last><affiliation>Space Telescope Science Institute</affiliation></author>
      <pages>157-169</pages>
      <abstract>Telescope bibliographies record the pulse of astronomy research by capturing publication statistics and citation metrics for telescope facilities. Robust and scalable bibliographies ensure that we can measure the scientific impact of our facilities and archives. However, the growing rate of publications threatens to outpace our ability to manually label astronomical literature. We therefore present the Automated Mission Classifier (amc), a tool that uses large language models (LLMs) to identify and categorize telescope references by processing large quantities of paper text. A modified version of amc performs well on the TRACS Kaggle challenge, achieving a macro F1 score of 0.84 on the held-out test set. amc is valuable for other telescopes beyond TRACS; we developed the initial software for identifying papers that featured scientific results by NASA missions. Additionally, we investigate how amc can also be used to interrogate historical datasets and surface potential label errors. Our work demonstrates that LLM-based applications offer powerful and scalable assistance for library sciences.</abstract>
      <url hash="d267d7ac">2025.wasp-main.18</url>
      <bibkey>wu-etal-2025-amc</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="19">
      <title><fixed-case>A</fixed-case>stro<fixed-case>ML</fixed-case>ab 5: Structured Summaries and Concept Extraction for 400,000 Astrophysics Papers</title>
      <author><first>Yuan-Sen</first><last>Ting</last><affiliation>The Ohio State University</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Alberto</first><last>Accomazzi</last><affiliation>Harvard-Smithsonian Center for Astrophysics</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Tirthankar</first><last>Ghosal</last><affiliation>Oak Ridge National Laboratory</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Tuan Dung</first><last>Nguyen</last><affiliation>University of Pennsylvania</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Rui</first><last>Pan</last><affiliation>University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Zechang</first><last>Sun</last><affiliation>Tsinghua University</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Tijmen</first><last>de Haan</last><affiliation>KEK</affiliation></author>
      <pages>170-185</pages>
      <abstract>We present a dataset of 408,590 astrophysics papers from arXiv (astro-ph), spanning 1992 through July 2025. Each paper has been processed through a multi-stage pipeline to produce: (1) structured summaries organized into six semantic sections (Background, Motivation, Methodology, Results, Interpretation, Implication), and (2) concept extraction yielding 9,999 unique concepts with detailed descriptions. The dataset contains 3.8 million paper-concept associations and includes semantic embeddings for all concepts. Comparison with traditional ADS keywords reveals that the concepts provide denser coverage and more uniform distribution, while analysis of embedding space structure demonstrates that concepts are semantically dispersed within papers—enabling discovery through multiple diverse entry points. Concept vocabulary and embeddings are publicly released at https://github.com/tingyuansen/astro-ph_knowledge_graph.</abstract>
      <url hash="a70468bb">2025.wasp-main.19</url>
      <bibkey>ting-etal-2025-astromlab</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="20">
      <title>Citation Drift: Measuring Reference Stability in Multi-Turn <fixed-case>LLM</fixed-case> Conversations</title>
      <author><first>Gokul Srinath Seetha</first><last>Ram</last><affiliation>California State Polytechnic University, Pomona</affiliation></author>
      <pages>186-191</pages>
      <abstract>Large Language Models (LLMs) are increasingly used for scientific writing and research assistance, yet their ability to maintain consistent citations across multi-turn conversations remains unexplored. This paper introduces the concept of citation drift—the phenomenon where references mutate, disappear, or get fabricated during extended LLM interactions. We analyze 240 conversations across four LLaMA models using 36 authentic scientific papers from six domains and find significant citation instability. LLaMA-4-Maverick-17B achieves the highest stability (0.481) and lowest fabrication entropy, while LLaMA-4-Scout-17B fabricates up to 85.6% of citations. We introduce five new metrics—stability, fabrication rate, drift rate, drift entropy, and willingness-to-cite—providing a standardized framework for evaluating factual reliability in scientific dialogue systems. Our benchmark offers reproducible, model-agnostic evaluation tools for assessing citation reliability in AI-assisted research workflows.</abstract>
      <url hash="0261eb35">2025.wasp-main.20</url>
      <bibkey>ram-2025-citation</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="21">
      <title>Efficient Context-Limited Telescope Bibliography Classification for the <fixed-case>WASP</fixed-case>-2025 Shared Task Using <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>ci<fixed-case>BERT</fixed-case></title>
      <author><first>Madhusudhan</first><last>Naidu</last><affiliation>Independent Researcher</affiliation></author>
      <pages>192-194</pages>
      <abstract>The creation of telescope bibliographies is a crucial part of assessing the scientific impact of observatories and ensuring reproducibility in astronomy. This task involves identifying, categorizing, and linking scientific publications that reference or use specific telescopes. However, this process remains largely manual and resource intensive. In this work, we present an efficient SciBERT-based approach for automatic classification of scientific papers into four categories — science, instrumentation, mention, and not telescope. Despite strict context-length constraints (maximum 512 tokens) and limited compute resources, our approach achieved a macro F1 score of 0.89, ranking at the top of the WASP-2025 leaderboard. We analyze the effect of truncation and show that even with half the samples exceeding the token limit, SciBERT’s domain alignment enables robust classification. We discuss trade-offs between truncation, chunking, and long-context models, providing insights into the efficiency frontier for scientific text curation.</abstract>
      <url hash="668bd63c">2025.wasp-main.21</url>
      <bibkey>naidu-2025-efficient</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="22">
      <title>Encoder Fine-tuning with Stochastic Sampling Outperforms Open-weight <fixed-case>GPT</fixed-case> in Astronomy Knowledge Extraction</title>
      <author><first>Shivam</first><last>Rawat</last><affiliation>Bonn-Aachen International Center for Information Technology</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Lucie</first><last>Flek</last><affiliation>Bonn-Aachen International Center for Information Technology</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Akbar</first><last>Karimi</last><affiliation>Lamarr Institute for Machine Learning and Artificial Intelligence, Germany</affiliation></author>
      <pages>195-200</pages>
      <abstract>Scientific literature in astronomy is rapidly expanding, making it increasingly important to automate the extraction of key entities and contextual information from research papers. In this paper, we present an encoder-based system for extracting knowledge from astronomy articles. Our objective is to develop models capable of classifying telescope references, detecting auxiliary semantic attributes, and recognizing instrument mentions from textual content. To this end, we implement a multi-task transformer-based system built upon the SciBERT model and fine-tuned for astronomy corpora classification. To carry out the fine-tuning, we stochastically sample segments from the training data and use majority voting over the test segments at inference time. Our system, despite its simplicity and low-cost implementation, significantly outperforms the open-weight GPT baseline.</abstract>
      <url hash="7ac23beb">2025.wasp-main.22</url>
      <bibkey>rawat-etal-2025-encoder</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="23">
      <title>Enhanced Table Structure Recognition with Multi-Modal Approach</title>
      <author><first>Huichen</first><last>Yang</last><affiliation>CSIRO Data61</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Andrew D.</first><last>Hellicar</last><affiliation>CSIRO Data61</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Maciej</first><last>Rybinski</last><affiliation>ITIS, University of Málaga, Spain</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Sarvnaz</first><last>Karimi</last><affiliation>CSIRO Data61</affiliation></author>
      <pages>201-207</pages>
      <abstract>Tables are fundamental for presenting information in research articles, technical documents, manuals, and reports. One key challenge is accessing the information in tables that are embedded in Portable Document Format (PDF) files or scanned images. It requires accurately recognising table structures in diverse table layouts and complex tables. The Table Structure Recognition (TSR) task aims to recognise the internal structure of table images and convert them into a machine-readable format. We propose a flexible multi-modal framework for image-based TSR. Our approach employs two-stream transformer encoders alongside task-specific decoders for table structure extraction and cell bounding box detection. Experiments on benchmark datasets demonstrate that our model achieves highly competitive results compared to strong baselines, gaining 5.4% over single-modality approaches on the FinTabNetd dataset.</abstract>
      <url hash="51178dca">2025.wasp-main.23</url>
      <bibkey>yang-etal-2025-enhanced</bibkey>
    </paper>
  </volume>
</collection>
