<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<collection id="2025.isa">
  <volume id="1" ingest-date="2025-09-08" type="proceedings">
    <meta>
      <booktitle>Proceedings of the 21st Joint ACL - ISO Workshop on Interoperable Semantic Annotation (ISA-21)</booktitle>
      <editor><first>Bunt</first><last>Harry</last></editor>
      <publisher>Association for Computational Linguistics</publisher>
      <address>Düsseldorf, Germany</address>
      <month>September</month>
      <year>2025</year>
      <url hash="d1679c3e">2025.isa-1</url>
      <venue>isa</venue>
      <venue>ws</venue>
      <isbn>979-8-89176-319-7</isbn>
    </meta>
    <frontmatter>
      <url hash="b3a537b8">2025.isa-1.0</url>
      <bibkey>isa-ws-2025-1</bibkey>
    </frontmatter>
    <paper id="1">
      <title>Engagement and Non-Engagement: Two Notions at the Core of an Annotation Schema of Enunciative Strategies</title>
      <author><first>Cyril</first><last>Bruneau</last></author>
      <author><first>Delphine</first><last>Battistelli</last></author>
      <pages>1-11</pages>
      <abstract>This study provides an annotation schema of a wide range of enunciative strategies underlying every enunciation process by which an enunciator actualizes a predicative content. We show that most of these enunciative strategies involve the enunciator in a relationship of <i>Engagement</i> (concerned with the notions of truth value and axiological/appreciative value) or <i>Non-Engagement</i> toward a stated predicative content. Our approach takes place in the French enunciative framework rooted in the work of Bally (1932). We explicitly compare our approach with that of Appraisal theory (Martin and White, 2003). We also illustrate the applications of our schema with a manual annotation experiment conducted on a corpus of French history textbooks. This experiment reveals interesting diachronic variations in the enunciator’s modes of <i>Engagement</i> and <i>Non-Engagement</i>.</abstract>
      <url hash="9e8d5efe">2025.isa-1.1</url>
      <bibkey>bruneau-battistelli-2025-engagement</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="2">
      <title>Revisiting the <fixed-case>ISO</fixed-case>-<fixed-case>T</fixed-case>ime<fixed-case>ML</fixed-case> abstract syntax</title>
      <author id="harry-bunt"><first>Harry</first><last>Bunt</last></author>
      <author><first>Alex</first><last>Fang</last></author>
      <author><first>Kiyong</first><last>Lee</last></author>
      <author><first>Volha</first><last>Petukhova</last></author>
      <author><first>Purificação</first><last>Silvano</last></author>
      <author id="james-pustejovsky"><first>James</first><last>Pustejovsky</last></author>
      <pages>12-20</pages>
      <abstract>This paper describes some of the ongoing work within the ISO preliminary work item PWI 254617-17, ‘Interlinking of annotations’. This PWI investigates the possibilities and problems of combining annotations made with different annotation schemes. using the ‘interlinking’ approach (Bunt, 2024) applied to different parts of the multi-part standard ISO 24617, ‘Semantic annotation framework’. This paper focuses on the combination of ISO-TimeML and QuantML at the level of abstract syntax. A new version is defined for the ISO-TimeML abstract syntax specification and how it relates to the concrete (XML-based) syntax as a basis for this combination. As a side-effect, some issues in the use of ISO-TimeML come to light that could be relevant for a possible future second edition of this standard.</abstract>
      <url hash="f89dc3fb">2025.isa-1.2</url>
      <bibkey>bunt-etal-2025-revisiting</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="3">
      <title>The representation of <fixed-case>Q</fixed-case>uant<fixed-case>ML</fixed-case> annotations in <fixed-case>UMR</fixed-case> - an exploration</title>
      <author id="harry-bunt"><first>Harry</first><last>Bunt</last></author>
      <author><first>Kiyong</first><last>Lee</last></author>
      <pages>21-30</pages>
      <abstract>This paper explores the possibilities and the problems in using Unified Meaning Representations (UMRs) for representing annotations of quantification phenomena, according to the ISO standard scheme QuantML (ISO 24617-12:2025). We show that the semantic information in QuantML annotations can we expressed in UMR, provided that some powerful semantic concepts are introduced and a slightly more general approach is adopted for the representation of multiple scope relations. Conversion functions are defined that transform the XML-based representations of QuantML into UMR structures and vice versa. The consequences are discussed that can be drawn from this regarding the possible role of UMR and the semantics of UMR representations of quantification.</abstract>
      <url hash="be35c14e">2025.isa-1.3</url>
      <bibkey>bunt-lee-2025-representation</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="4">
      <title>Cococorpus: a corpus of copredication</title>
      <author><first>Long</first><last>Chen</last></author>
      <author><first>Deniz Ekin</first><last>Yavaş</last></author>
      <author><first>Laura</first><last>Kallmeyer</last></author>
      <author><first>Rainer</first><last>Osswald</last></author>
      <pages>31-40</pages>
      <abstract>While copredication has been widely investigated as a linguistic phenomenon, there is a notable lack of systematically annotated data to support empirical and quantitative research. This paper gives an overview of the ongoing construction of Cococorpus, a corpus of copredication, describes the annotation methodology and guidelines, and presents preliminary findings from the annotated data. Currently, the corpus contains 1500 gold-standard manual annotations including about 200 sentences with copredications. The annotated data not only supports the empirical validation for existing theories of copredication, but also reveals regularities that may inform theoretical development.</abstract>
      <url hash="a7224da0">2025.isa-1.4</url>
      <bibkey>chen-etal-2025-cococorpus</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="5">
      <title>Can <fixed-case>ISO</fixed-case> 24617-1 go clinical? Extending a General-Domain Scheme to Medical Narratives</title>
      <author><first>Ana Luísa</first><last>Fernandes</last></author>
      <author><first>Purificação</first><last>Silvano</last></author>
      <author><first>António</first><last>Leal</last></author>
      <author><first>Nuno</first><last>Guimarães</last></author>
      <author><first>Evelin</first><last>Amorim</last></author>
      <pages>41-52</pages>
      <abstract>The definition of rigorous and well-structured annotation schemes is a key element in the advancement of Natural Language Processing (NLP). This paper aims to compare the performance of a general-purpose annotation scheme — Text2Story, based on the ISO 24617-1 standard — with that of a domain-specific scheme — i2b2 — in the context of clinical narrative annotation; and to assess the feasibility of harmonizing ISO 24617-1, originally designed for general-domain applications, with a specialized extension tailored to the medical domain. Based on the results of this comparative analysis, we present Med2Story, a medical-specific extension of ISO 24617-1 developed to address the particularities of clinical text annotation.</abstract>
      <url hash="08661bea">2025.isa-1.5</url>
      <bibkey>fernandes-etal-2025-iso</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="6">
      <title>Enhancing <fixed-case>ISO</fixed-case> 24617-2: Formalizing Apology and Thanking Acts for Spoken <fixed-case>R</fixed-case>ussian Dialogue Annotation</title>
      <author><first>Ksenia</first><last>Klokova</last></author>
      <author><first>Anton</first><last>Bankov</last></author>
      <author><first>Nikolay</first><last>Ignatiev</last></author>
      <pages>53-62</pages>
      <abstract>This paper refines ISO 24617-2’s Social Obligations Management dimension by formalizing apology and thanking acts for Russian dialogue annotation. Addressing gaps in formal definitions and limited response strategies, we propose culture-neutral semantic cores using Wierzbicka’s universal primes and update semantics. We introduce three response functions: address (minimal acknowledgment), downplay (mitigation), and decline (reinforcement). Validated through qualitative analysis, this framework captures empirical strategies—including non-response, formulaic minimization, and strategic obligation maintenance—unaddressed in the current standard. Our approach maintains ISO compatibility while eliminating unsubstantiated elements like obligatory response pressure, enhancing annotation accuracy for Russian dialogue.</abstract>
      <url hash="48491a55">2025.isa-1.6</url>
      <bibkey>klokova-etal-2025-enhancing</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="7">
      <title>An annotation scheme for financial news in <fixed-case>P</fixed-case>ortuguese</title>
      <author><first>António</first><last>Leal</last></author>
      <author><first>Purificação</first><last>Silvano</last></author>
      <author><first>Zuo</first><last>Qinren</last></author>
      <author><first>Evelin</first><last>Amorim</last></author>
      <author id="alipio-jorge"><first>Alípio</first><last>Jorge</last></author>
      <pages>63-75</pages>
      <abstract>We present an annotation scheme designed to capture information related to the maintenance or change in the price of some goods (fuels, water, and vehicles) in news articles in Portuguese. The methodology we used involved adapting an existing annotation scheme, the Text2Story scheme (Silvano et al., 2021; Leal et al., 2022), which is based on different parts of ISO 24617 to capture the essential information for this project. Adaptations were needed to accommodate specific information, namely, information related to quantitative data and comparative relations that are abundant in this type of news. In this paper, we provide an overview of the annotation scheme, highlighting attributes and values of the entity and link structures specifically designed to capture financial information, as well as some problems we had to overcome in the process of building it and the rationale of some decisions behind its overall architecture.</abstract>
      <url hash="02a4a39b">2025.isa-1.7</url>
      <bibkey>leal-etal-2025-annotation</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="8">
      <title>Enhanced Evaluative Language Annotation through Refined Theoretical Framework and Workflow</title>
      <author><first>Jiamei</first><last>Zeng</last></author>
      <author><first>Haitao</first><last>Wang</last></author>
      <author id="harry-bunt"><first>Harry</first><last>Bunt</last></author>
      <author><first>Xinyu</first><last>Cao</last></author>
      <author><first>Sylviane</first><last>Cardey</last></author>
      <author><first>Min</first><last>Dong</last></author>
      <author><first>Tianyong</first><last>Hao</last></author>
      <author><first>Yangli</first><last>Jia</last></author>
      <author><first>Kiyong</first><last>Lee</last></author>
      <author><first>Shengqing</first><last>Liao</last></author>
      <author id="james-pustejovsky"><first>James</first><last>Pustejovsky</last></author>
      <author><first>François Claude</first><last>Rey</last></author>
      <author id="laurent-romary"><first>Laurent</first><last>Romary</last></author>
      <author><first>Jianfang</first><last>Zong</last></author>
      <author id="alex-chengyu-fang"><first>Alex C.</first><last>Fang</last></author>
      <pages>76-84</pages>
      <abstract>As precursor work in preparation for an international standard <i>ISO/PWI 24617-16 Language resource management – Semantic annotation – Part 16: Evaluative language</i>, we aim to test and enhance the reliability of the annotation of subjective evaluation based on Appraisal Theory. We describe a comprehensive three-phase workflow tested on COVID-19 media reports to achieve reliable agreement through progressive training and quality control. Our methodology addresses some of the key challenges through the refinement of targeted guideline refinements and the development of interactive clarification tools, alongside a custom platform that enables the pre-classification of six evaluative categories, systematic annotation review, and organized documentation. We report empirical results that demonstrate substantial improvements from the initial moderate agreement to a strong final consensus. Our research offers both theoretical refinements addressing persistent classification challenges in evaluation and practical solutions for the implementation of the annotation workflow, proposing a replicable methodology for the achievement of reliable annotation consistency in the annotation of evaluative language.</abstract>
      <url hash="3bad652c">2025.isa-1.8</url>
      <bibkey>zeng-etal-2025-enhanced</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="9">
      <title>Multimodal Common Ground Annotation for Partial Information Collaborative Problem Solving</title>
      <author><first>Yifan</first><last>Zhu</last></author>
      <author><first>Changsoo</first><last>Jung</last></author>
      <author><first>Kenneth</first><last>Lai</last></author>
      <author><first>Videep</first><last>Venkatesha</last></author>
      <author><first>Mariah</first><last>Bradford</last></author>
      <author><first>Jack</first><last>Fitzgerald</last></author>
      <author><first>Huma</first><last>Jamil</last></author>
      <author><first>Carine</first><last>Graff</last></author>
      <author><first>Sai Kiran Ganesh</first><last>Kumar</last></author>
      <author><first>Bruce</first><last>Draper</last></author>
      <author><first>Nathaniel</first><last>Blanchard</last></author>
      <author id="james-pustejovsky"><first>James</first><last>Pustejovsky</last></author>
      <author><first>Nikhil</first><last>Krishnaswamy</last></author>
      <pages>85-91</pages>
      <abstract>This project note describes challenges and procedures undertaken in annotating an audiovisual dataset capturing a multimodal situated collaborative construction task. In the task, all participants begin with different partial information, and must collaborate using speech, gesture, and action to arrive a solution that satisfies all individual pieces of private information. This rich data poses a number of annotation challenges, from small objects in a close space, to the implicit and multimodal fashion in which participants express agreement, disagreement, and beliefs. We discuss the data collection procedure, annotation schemas and tools, and future use cases.</abstract>
      <url hash="6ca74d30">2025.isa-1.9</url>
      <bibkey>zhu-etal-2025-multimodal-common</bibkey>
    </paper>
  </volume>
</collection>
