<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<collection id="2025.cl">
  <volume id="1" type="journal">
    <meta>
      <booktitle>Computational Linguistics, Volume 51, Issue 1 - March 2025</booktitle>
      <publisher>MIT Press</publisher>
      <address>Cambridge, MA</address>
      <month>March</month>
      <year>2025</year>
      <venue>cl</venue>
      <journal-volume>51</journal-volume>
      <journal-issue>1</journal-issue>
    </meta>
    <paper id="1">
      <title>Opening a New Chapter for Computational Linguistics</title>
      <author><first>Wei</first><last>Lu</last></author>
      <doi>10.1162/coli_e_00552</doi>
      <abstract>By the end of 2024, the journal Computational Linguistics has reached a significant milestone: It has published exactly 50 volumes over the past half-century. As we launch the first issue of Volume 51, this is an opportune moment to reflect on the journal’s legacy, ongoing evolution, and the exciting changes that lie ahead. Together, we embark on a journey to open a new chapter for this storied publication.</abstract>
      <pages>1–5</pages>
      <url hash="75bed9d3">2025.cl-1.1</url>
      <bibkey>lu-2025-opening</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="2">
      <title><fixed-case>MUC</fixed-case>king In, or Fifty Years in Information Extraction</title>
      <author><first>Ralph</first><last>Grishman</last></author>
      <doi>10.1162/coli_a_00547</doi>
      <abstract>I want to thank the ACL for this Lifetime Achievement Award. I am deeply honored to be receiving it. I would also like to thank the students, faculty, and researchers who were members of the Proteus Project during most of my professional lifetime. It was an honor to serve that group.</abstract>
      <pages>7–22</pages>
      <url hash="eab7a061">2025.cl-1.2</url>
      <bibkey>grishman-2025-mucking</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="3">
      <title>e<fixed-case>RST</fixed-case>: A Signaled Graph Theory of Discourse Relations and Organization</title>
      <author><first>Amir</first><last>Zeldes</last></author>
      <author><first>Tatsuya</first><last>Aoyama</last></author>
      <author><first>Yang Janet</first><last>Liu</last></author>
      <author><first>Siyao</first><last>Peng</last></author>
      <author><first>Debopam</first><last>Das</last></author>
      <author><first>Luke</first><last>Gessler</last></author>
      <doi>10.1162/coli_a_00538</doi>
      <abstract>In this article we present Enhanced Rhetorical Structure Theory (eRST), a new theoretical framework for computational discourse analysis, based on an expansion of Rhetorical Structure Theory (RST). The framework encompasses discourse relation graphs with tree-breaking, non-projective and concurrent relations, as well as implicit and explicit signals which give explainable rationales to our analyses. We survey shortcomings of RST and other existing frameworks, such as Segmented Discourse Representation Theory, the Penn Discourse Treebank, and Discourse Dependencies, and address these using constructs in the proposed theory. We provide annotation, search, and visualization tools for data, and present and evaluate a freely available corpus of English annotated according to our framework, encompassing 12 spoken and written genres with over 200K tokens. Finally, we discuss automatic parsing, evaluation metrics, and applications for data in our framework.</abstract>
      <pages>23–72</pages>
      <url hash="e1ebaaf8">2025.cl-1.3</url>
      <bibkey>zeldes-etal-2025-erst</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="4">
      <title>Machine Translation Meta Evaluation through Translation Accuracy Challenge Sets</title>
      <author><first>Nikita</first><last>Moghe</last></author>
      <author><first>Arnisa</first><last>Fazla</last></author>
      <author><first>Chantal</first><last>Amrhein</last></author>
      <author><first>Tom</first><last>Kocmi</last></author>
      <author><first>Mark</first><last>Steedman</last></author>
      <author><first>Alexandra</first><last>Birch</last></author>
      <author><first>Rico</first><last>Sennrich</last></author>
      <author><first>Liane</first><last>Guillou</last></author>
      <doi>10.1162/coli_a_00537</doi>
      <abstract>Recent machine translation (MT) metrics calibrate their effectiveness by correlating with human judgment. However, these results are often obtained by averaging predictions across large test sets without any insights into the strengths and weaknesses of these metrics across different error types. Challenge sets are used to probe specific dimensions of metric behavior but there are very few such datasets and they either focus on a limited number of phenomena or a limited number of language pairs. We introduce ACES, a contrastive challenge set spanning 146 language pairs, aimed at discovering whether metrics can identify 68 translation accuracy errors. These phenomena range from basic alterations at the word/character level to more intricate errors based on discourse and real-world knowledge. We conducted a large-scale study by benchmarking ACES on 47 metrics submitted to the WMT 2022 and WMT 2023 metrics shared tasks. We also measure their sensitivity to a range of linguistic phenomena. We further investigate claims that large language models (LLMs) are effective as MT evaluators, addressing the limitations of previous studies by using a dataset that covers a range of linguistic phenomena and language pairs and includes both low- and medium-resource languages. Our results demonstrate that different metric families struggle with different phenomena and that LLM-based methods are unreliable. We expose a number of major flaws with existing methods: Most metrics ignore the source sentence; metrics tend to prefer surface level overlap; and over-reliance on language-agnostic representations leads to confusion when the target language is similar to the source language. To further encourage detailed evaluation beyond singular scores, we expand ACES to include error span annotations, denoted as SPAN-ACES, and we use this dataset to evaluate span-based error metrics, showing that these metrics also need considerable improvement. Based on our observations, we provide a set of recommendations for building better MT metrics, including focusing on error labels instead of scores, ensembling, designing metrics to explicitly focus on the source sentence, focusing on semantic content rather than relying on the lexical overlap, and choosing the right pre-trained model for obtaining representations.</abstract>
      <pages>73–137</pages>
      <url hash="62052024">2025.cl-1.4</url>
      <bibkey>moghe-etal-2025-machine</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="5">
      <title>Compositionality and Sentence Meaning: Comparing Semantic Parsing and Transformers on a Challenging Sentence Similarity Dataset</title>
      <author><first>James</first><last>Fodor</last></author>
      <author><first>Simon De</first><last>Deyne</last></author>
      <author><first>Shinsuke</first><last>Suzuki</last></author>
      <doi>10.1162/coli_a_00536</doi>
      <abstract>One of the major outstanding questions in computational semantics is how humans integrate the meaning of individual words into a sentence in a way that enables understanding of complex and novel combinations of words, a phenomenon known as compositionality. Many approaches to modeling the process of compositionality can be classified as either “vector-based” models, in which the meaning of a sentence is represented as a vector of numbers, or “syntax-based” models, in which the meaning of a sentence is represented as a structured tree of labeled components. A major barrier in assessing and comparing these contrasting approaches is the lack of large, relevant datasets for model comparison. This article aims to address this gap by introducing a new dataset, STS3k, which consists of 2,800 pairs of sentences rated for semantic similarity by human participants. The sentence pairs have been selected to systematically vary different combinations of words, providing a rigorous test and enabling a clearer picture of the comparative strengths and weaknesses of vector-based and syntax-based methods. Our results show that when tested on the new STS3k dataset, state-of-the-art transformers poorly capture the pattern of human semantic similarity judgments, while even simple methods for combining syntax- and vector-based components into a novel hybrid model yield substantial improvements. We further show that this improvement is due to the ability of the hybrid model to replicate human sensitivity to specific changes in sentence structure. Our findings provide evidence for the value of integrating multiple methods to better reflect the way in which humans mentally represent compositional meaning.</abstract>
      <pages>139–190</pages>
      <url hash="83fd8b18">2025.cl-1.5</url>
      <bibkey>fodor-etal-2025-compositionality</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="6">
      <title>Evaluating Synthetic Data Generation from User Generated Text</title>
      <author><first>Jenny</first><last>Chim</last></author>
      <author><first>Julia</first><last>Ive</last></author>
      <author><first>Maria</first><last>Liakata</last></author>
      <doi>10.1162/coli_a_00540</doi>
      <abstract>User-generated content provides a rich resource to study social and behavioral phenomena. Although its application potential is currently limited by the paucity of expert labels and the privacy risks inherent in personal data, synthetic data can help mitigate this bottleneck. In this work, we introduce an evaluation framework to facilitate research on synthetic language data generation for user-generated text. We define a set of aspects for assessing data quality, namely, style preservation, meaning preservation, and divergence, as a proxy for privacy. We introduce metrics corresponding to each aspect. Moreover, through a set of generation strategies and representative tasks and baselines across domains, we demonstrate the relation between the quality aspects of synthetic user generated content, generation strategies, metrics, and downstream performance. To our knowledge, our work is the first unified evaluation framework for user-generated text in relation to the specified aspects, offering both intrinsic and extrinsic evaluation. We envisage it will facilitate developments towards shareable, high-quality synthetic language data.</abstract>
      <pages>191–233</pages>
      <url hash="76099fc1">2025.cl-1.6</url>
      <bibkey>chim-etal-2025-evaluating</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="7">
      <title>Neural Semantic Parsing with Extremely Rich Symbolic Meaning Representations</title>
      <author><first>Xiao</first><last>Zhang</last></author>
      <author><first>Gosse</first><last>Bouma</last></author>
      <author><first>Johan</first><last>Bos</last></author>
      <doi>10.1162/coli_a_00542</doi>
      <abstract>Current open-domain neural semantics parsers show impressive performance. However, closer inspection of the symbolic meaning representations they produce reveals significant weaknesses: Sometimes they tend to merely copy character sequences from the source text to form symbolic concepts, defaulting to the most frequent word sense based in the training distribution. By leveraging the hierarchical structure of a lexical ontology, we introduce a novel compositional symbolic representation for concepts based on their position in the taxonomical hierarchy. This representation provides richer semantic information and enhances interpretability. We introduce a neural “taxonomical” semantic parser to utilize this new representation system of predicates, and compare it with a standard neural semantic parser trained on the traditional meaning representation format, employing a novel challenge set and evaluation metric for evaluation. Our experimental findings demonstrate that the taxonomical model, trained on much richer and complex meaning representations, is slightly subordinate in performance to the traditional model using the standard metrics for evaluation, but outperforms it when dealing with out-of-vocabulary concepts. We further show through neural model probing that training on a taxonomic representation enhances the model’s ability to learn the taxonomical hierarchy. This finding is encouraging for research in computational semantics that aims to combine data-driven distributional meanings with knowledge-based symbolic representations.</abstract>
      <pages>235–274</pages>
      <url hash="3fe0fcd7">2025.cl-1.7</url>
      <bibkey>zhang-etal-2025-neural</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="8">
      <title>A Survey on <fixed-case>LLM</fixed-case>-Generated Text Detection: Necessity, Methods, and Future Directions</title>
      <author><first>Junchao</first><last>Wu</last></author>
      <author><first>Shu</first><last>Yang</last></author>
      <author><first>Runzhe</first><last>Zhan</last></author>
      <author><first>Yulin</first><last>Yuan</last></author>
      <author><first>Lidia Sam</first><last>Chao</last></author>
      <author><first>Derek Fai</first><last>Wong</last></author>
      <doi>10.1162/coli_a_00549</doi>
      <abstract>The remarkable ability of large language models (LLMs) to comprehend, interpret, and generate complex language has rapidly integrated LLM-generated text into various aspects of daily life, where users increasingly accept it. However, the growing reliance on LLMs underscores the urgent need for effective detection mechanisms to identify LLM-generated text. Such mechanisms are critical to mitigating misuse and safeguarding domains like artistic expression and social networks from potential negative consequences. LLM-generated text detection, conceptualized as a binary classification task, seeks to determine whether an LLM produced a given text. Recent advances in this field stem from innovations in watermarking techniques, statistics-based detectors, and neural-based detectors. Human-assisted methods also play a crucial role. In this survey, we consolidate recent research breakthroughs in this field, emphasizing the urgent need to strengthen detector research. Additionally, we review existing datasets, highlighting their limitations and developmental requirements. Furthermore, we examine various LLM-generated text detection paradigms, shedding light on challenges like out-of-distribution problems, potential attacks, real-world data issues, and ineffective evaluation frameworks. Finally, we outline intriguing directions for future research in LLM-generated text detection to advance responsible artificial intelligence. This survey aims to provide a clear and comprehensive introduction for newcomers while offering seasoned researchers valuable updates in the field.1</abstract>
      <pages>275–338</pages>
      <url hash="be1eb645">2025.cl-1.8</url>
      <bibkey>wu-etal-2025-survey</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="9">
      <title>Automatic Language Identification in Texts</title>
      <author><first>Tom</first><last>Lippincott</last></author>
      <doi>10.1162/coli_r_00521</doi>
      <pages>339–341</pages>
      <url hash="ece5801a">2025.cl-1.9</url>
      <bibkey>lippincott-2025-automatic</bibkey>
    </paper>
  </volume>
</collection>
