<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<collection id="2025.chipsal">
  <volume id="1" ingest-date="2025-01-24" type="proceedings">
    <meta>
      <booktitle>Proceedings of the First Workshop on Challenges in Processing South Asian Languages (CHiPSAL 2025)</booktitle>
      <editor><first>Kengatharaiyer</first><last>Sarveswaran</last></editor>
      <editor><first>Ashwini</first><last>Vaidya</last></editor>
      <editor><first>Bal</first><last>Krishna Bal</last></editor>
      <editor><first>Sana</first><last>Shams</last></editor>
      <editor><first>Surendrabikram</first><last>Thapa</last></editor>
      <publisher>International Committee on Computational Linguistics</publisher>
      <address>Abu Dhabi, UAE</address>
      <month>January</month>
      <year>2025</year>
      <url hash="05c81aae">2025.chipsal-1</url>
      <venue>chipsal</venue>
      <venue>ws</venue>
    </meta>
    <frontmatter>
      <url hash="ee055ceb">2025.chipsal-1.0</url>
    </frontmatter>
    <paper id="1">
      <title>A Brief Overview of the First Workshop on Challenges in Processing <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>outh <fixed-case>A</fixed-case>sian Languages (<fixed-case>CH</fixed-case>i<fixed-case>PSAL</fixed-case>)</title>
      <author><first>Kengatharaiyer</first><last>Sarveswaran</last></author>
      <author><first>Surendrabikram</first><last>Thapa</last></author>
      <author><first>Sana</first><last>Shams</last></author>
      <author><first>Ashwini</first><last>Vaidya</last></author>
      <author><first>Bal Krishna</first><last>Bal</last></author>
      <pages>1–8</pages>
      <abstract>In this paper, we provide a brief summary of the inaugural workshop on Challenges in Processing South Asian Languages (CHiPSAL) held as part of COLING 2025. The workshop included regular papers, invited keynotes, and shared task papers, fostering a collaborative platform for exploring challenges in processing South Asian languages. The shared task focused on Devanagari-script language understanding, encompassing subtasks on language identification, hate speech detection, and target classification. This workshop series aims to address linguistic and cultural nuances, resource constraints, and orthographic complexities in low-resource South Asian languages while advancing NLP research and promoting multilingual inclusivity.</abstract>
      <url hash="047ccac7">2025.chipsal-1.1</url>
    </paper>
    <paper id="2">
      <title>Development of Pre-Trained Transformer-based Models for the <fixed-case>N</fixed-case>epali Language</title>
      <author><first>Prajwal</first><last>Thapa</last></author>
      <author><first>Jinu</first><last>Nyachhyon</last></author>
      <author><first>Mridul</first><last>Sharma</last></author>
      <author><first>Bal Krishna</first><last>Bal</last></author>
      <pages>9–16</pages>
      <abstract>Transformer-based pre-trained language models have dominated the field of Natural Language Processing (NLP) for quite some time now. However, the Nepali language, spoken by approximately 32 million people worldwide, remains significantly underrepresented in this domain. This underrepresentation is primarily attributed to the scarcity of monolingual data corpora and limited available resources for the Nepali language. While existing efforts have predominantly concentrated on basic encoder-based models, there is a notable gap in the exploration of decoder-based architectures. To address this gap, we have collected 27.5 GB of Nepali text data, approximately 2.4x larger than any previously available Nepali language corpus. Leveraging this data, we pre-trained three different models i.e., BERT, RoBERTa, and GPT-2, exclusively for the Nepali Language. Furthermore, we performed instruction tuning and explored its potential for monolingual Nepali data, providing a foundation for future research. Our models outperformed the existing best model by 2 points on Nep-gLUE benchmark, scoring 95.60 and also outperformed existing models on text generation tasks, demonstrating improvements in both understanding and generating Nepali text.</abstract>
      <url hash="aaadcda4">2025.chipsal-1.2</url>
    </paper>
    <paper id="3">
      <title>Benchmarking the Performance of Pre-trained <fixed-case>LLM</fixed-case>s across <fixed-case>U</fixed-case>rdu <fixed-case>NLP</fixed-case> Tasks</title>
      <author><first>Munief Hassan</first><last>Tahir</last></author>
      <author><first>Sana</first><last>Shams</last></author>
      <author><first>Layba</first><last>Fiaz</last></author>
      <author><first>Farah</first><last>Adeeba</last></author>
      <author><first>Sarmad</first><last>Hussain</last></author>
      <pages>17–34</pages>
      <abstract>Large Language Models (LLMs) pre-trained on multilingual data have revolutionized natural language processing research, by transitioning from languages and task specific model pipelines to a single model adapted on a variety of tasks. However majority of existing multilingual NLP benchmarks for LLMs provide evaluation data in only few languages with little linguistic diversity. In addition these benchmarks lack quality assessment against the respective state-of the art models. This study presents an in-depth examination of 7 prominent LLMs: GPT-3.5-turbo, Llama 2-7B-Chat, Llama 3.1-8B, Bloomz 3B, Bloomz 7B1, Ministral-8B and Whisper (Large, medium and small variant) across 17 tasks using 22 datasets, 13.8 hours of speech, in a zero-shot setting, and their performance against state-of-the-art (SOTA) models, has been compared and analyzed. Our experiments show that SOTA models currently outperform encoder-decoder models in majority of Urdu NLP tasks under zero-shot settings. However, comparing Llama 3.1-8B over prior version Llama 2-7B-Chat, we can deduce that with improved language coverage, LLMs can surpass these SOTA models. Our results emphasize that models with fewer parameters but richer language-specific data, like Llama 3.1-8B, often outperform larger models with lower language diversity, such as GPT-3.5, in several tasks.</abstract>
      <url hash="c02e6d66">2025.chipsal-1.3</url>
    </paper>
    <paper id="4">
      <title><fixed-case>B</fixed-case>engali <fixed-case>C</fixed-case>hart<fixed-case>S</fixed-case>umm: A Benchmark Dataset and study on feasibility of Large Language Models on <fixed-case>B</fixed-case>engali Chart to Text Summarization</title>
      <author><first>Nahida Akter</first><last>Tanjila</last></author>
      <author><first>Afrin Sultana</first><last>Poushi</last></author>
      <author><first>Sazid Abdullah</first><last>Farhan</last></author>
      <author><first>Abu Raihan Mostofa</first><last>Kamal</last></author>
      <author><first>Md. Azam</first><last>Hossain</last></author>
      <author><first>Md. Hamjajul</first><last>Ashmafee</last></author>
      <pages>35–45</pages>
      <abstract>In today’s data-driven world, effectively organizing and presenting data is challenging, particularly for non-experts. While tabular formats structure data, they often lack intuitive insights; charts, however, prefer accessible and impactful visual summaries. Although recent advancements in NLP, powered by large language models (LLMs), have primarily beneʐʒted high-resource languages like English, low-resource languages such as Bengali—spoken by millions globally—still face significant data limitations. This research addresses this gap by introducing “Bengali ChartSumm,” a benchmark dataset with 4,100 Bengali chart images, metadata, and summaries. This dataset facilitates the analysis of LLMs (mT5, BanglaT5, Gemma) in Bengali chart-to-text summarization, offering essential baselines and evaluations that enhance NLP research for low-resource languages.</abstract>
      <url hash="58c93abd">2025.chipsal-1.4</url>
    </paper>
    <paper id="5">
      <title><fixed-case>D</fixed-case>wesh<fixed-case>V</fixed-case>aani: An <fixed-case>LLM</fixed-case> for Detecting Religious Hate Speech in Code-Mixed <fixed-case>H</fixed-case>indi-<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>nglish</title>
      <author><first>Varad</first><last>Srivastava</last></author>
      <pages>46–60</pages>
      <abstract>Traditional language models in NLP have been extensively made use of, in hateful speech detection problems. With the growth of social media, content in regional languages has grown exponentially. However, use of language models as well as LLMs on code-mixed Hindi-English hateful speech detection is under-explored. Our work addresses this gap by investigating both cutting-edge LLMs by Meta, Google, OpenAI, Nvidia as well as Indic-LLMs like Sarvam, Indic-Gemma, and Airavata on hateful speech detection in code-mixed Hindi-English languages in a comprehensive set of few-shot scenarios which include examples selected randomly, as well as with retrieval-augmented generation (RAG) based on MuRIL language model. We observed that Indic-LLMs which are instruction tuned on Indian content fall behind on the task. We also experimented with fine-tuning approaches, where we use knowledge-distillation based-finetuning by using extracted information about rationale behind hate speech, as part of the fine-tuning process. Finally, we also propose Dwesh-Vaani, an LLM based on fine-tuned Gemma-2, that out-performs all other approaches at the task of religious hateful speech detection as well as targeted religion identification in code-mixed Hindi-English languages.</abstract>
      <url hash="b289d069">2025.chipsal-1.5</url>
    </paper>
    <paper id="6">
      <title>Improving Accuracy of Low-resource <fixed-case>ASR</fixed-case> using Rule-Based Character Constituency Loss (<fixed-case>RBCCL</fixed-case>)</title>
      <author><first>Rupak Raj</first><last>Ghimire</last></author>
      <author><first>Prakash</first><last>Poudyal</last></author>
      <author><first>Bal Krishna</first><last>Bal</last></author>
      <pages>61–70</pages>
      <abstract>Modern general-purpose speech recognition systems are more robust in languages with high resources. However, achieving state-of-the-art accuracy for low-resource languages is still challenging. To deal with this challenge, one of the popular practice is fine-tuning the pre-trained model on low-resource settings. Nevertheless, pre-trained or fine-tuned model fails to capture the complex character and word constituency in the Devanagari script transcription. We proposed a complementary loss function designed to force the model to learn the character constituency of Devanagari script. Our complementary loss function, called as Rule-Based Character Constituency Loss (RBCCL), that penalizes incorrect transcriptions and updates the overall loss during the model training phase. This loss function can be combined with CTC loss or cross-entropy loss as well which are widely used in ASR training. Our experiment shows that combining the existing cross-entropy loss with new complementary loss (RBCCL) improves the Word Error Rate (WER ), reducing it from 47.1% to 23.41% which is quite promising result.</abstract>
      <url hash="d1d07639">2025.chipsal-1.6</url>
    </paper>
    <paper id="7">
      <title>Natural Language Understanding of <fixed-case>D</fixed-case>evanagari Script Languages: Language Identification, Hate Speech and its Target Detection</title>
      <author><first>Surendrabikram</first><last>Thapa</last></author>
      <author><first>Kritesh</first><last>Rauniyar</last></author>
      <author><first>Farhan Ahmad</first><last>Jafri</last></author>
      <author><first>Surabhi</first><last>Adhikari</last></author>
      <author><first>Kengatharaiyer</first><last>Sarveswaran</last></author>
      <author><first>Bal Krishna</first><last>Bal</last></author>
      <author><first>Hariram</first><last>Veeramani</last></author>
      <author><first>Usman</first><last>Naseem</last></author>
      <pages>71–82</pages>
      <abstract>The growing use of Devanagari-script languages such as Hindi, Nepali, Marathi, Sanskrit, and Bhojpuri on social media presents unique challenges for natural language understanding (NLU), particularly in language identification, hate speech detection, and target classification. To address these challenges, we organized a shared task with three subtasks: (i) identifying the language of Devanagari-script text, (ii) detecting hate speech, and (iii) classifying hate speech targets into individual, community, or organization. A curated dataset combining multiple corpora was provided, with splits for training, evaluation, and testing. The task attracted 113 participants, with 32 teams submitting models evaluated on accuracy, precision, recall, and macro F1-score. Participants applied innovative methods, including large language models, transformer models, and multilingual embeddings, to tackle the linguistic complexities of Devanagari-script languages. This paper summarizes the shared task, datasets, and results, and aims to contribute to advancing NLU for low-resource languages and fostering inclusive, culturally aware natural language processing (NLP) solutions.</abstract>
      <url hash="825538c0">2025.chipsal-1.7</url>
    </paper>
    <paper id="8">
      <title><fixed-case>S</fixed-case>i<fixed-case>T</fixed-case>a - <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>inhala and <fixed-case>T</fixed-case>amil Speaker Diarization Dataset in the Wild</title>
      <author><first>Uthayasanker</first><last>Thayasivam</last></author>
      <author><first>Thulasithan</first><last>Gnanenthiram</last></author>
      <author><first>Shamila</first><last>Jeewantha</last></author>
      <author><first>Upeksha</first><last>Jayawickrama</last></author>
      <pages>83–92</pages>
      <abstract>The dynamic field of speaker diarization continues to present significant challenges, despite notable advancements in recent years and the rising focus on complex acoustic scenarios emphasizes the importance of sustained research efforts in this area. While speech resources for speaker diarization are expanding rapidly, aided by semi-automated techniques, many existing datasets remain outdated and lack authentic real-world conversational data. This challenge is particularly acute for low-resource South Asian languages, due to limited public media data and reduced research efforts. Sinhala and Tamil are two such languages with limited speaker diarization datasets. To address this gap, we introduce a new speaker diarization dataset for these languages and evaluate multiple existing models to assess their performance. This work provides essential resources, a novel dataset and valuable insights from model benchmarks to advance speaker diarization for low-resource languages, particularly Sinhala and Tamil.</abstract>
      <url hash="1883e1e0">2025.chipsal-1.8</url>
    </paper>
    <paper id="9">
      <title>Sandhi Splitting in <fixed-case>T</fixed-case>amil and <fixed-case>T</fixed-case>elugu: A Sequence-to-Sequence Approach Leveraging Transformer Models</title>
      <author><first>Priyanka</first><last>Dasari</last></author>
      <author><first>Mupparapu</first><last>Sohan Gupta</last></author>
      <author><first>Nagaraju</first><last>Vuppala</last></author>
      <author><first>Pruthwik</first><last>Mishra</last></author>
      <author><first>Parameswari</first><last>Krishnamurthy</last></author>
      <pages>93–103</pages>
      <abstract>Dravidian languages like Tamil and Telugu are agglutinative languages, they form wordforms by combining two or more elements into a single string with morpho-phonemic changes at the point of concatenation, known as sandhi. This linguistic feature adds complexity to automatic language processing, making the pre-processing of sandhi words essential for NLP applications. We developed extensive sandhi-annotated corpora of 15K for Telugu and Tamil, focusing on the systematic application of sandhi rules which explains the word formation patterns by showing how lexical and functional categories combine to create composite non-compound words. We implemented compact sequence-to-sequence transformer networks for the automatic sandhi processing. To evaluate our models, we manually annotated Telugu and Tamil IN22-Conv Benchmark datasets with sandhi annotations. Our experiments aim to enhance the language processing tasks like machine translation in morphologically rich languages.</abstract>
      <url hash="98f20f93">2025.chipsal-1.9</url>
    </paper>
    <paper id="10">
      <title>Bridge the <fixed-case>GAP</fixed-case>: Multi-lingual Models For Ambiguous Pronominal Coreference Resolution in <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>outh <fixed-case>A</fixed-case>sian Languages</title>
      <author><first>Rahothvarman</first><last>P</last></author>
      <author><first>Adith John</first><last>Rajeev</last></author>
      <author><first>Kaveri</first><last>Anuranjana</last></author>
      <author><first>Radhika</first><last>Mamidi</last></author>
      <pages>104–114</pages>
      <abstract>Coreference resolution, the process of determining what a referring expression (a pronoun or a noun phrase) refers to in discourse, is a critical aspect of natural language understanding. However, the development of computational models for coreference resolution in low-resource languages, such as the Dravidian (and more broadly all South Asian) languages, still remains a significant challenge due to the scarcity of annotated corpora in these languages. To address this data scarcity, we adopt a pipeline that translates the English GAP dataset into various South Asian languages, creating a multi-lingual coreference dataset mGAP. Our research aims to leverage this dataset and develop two novel models, namely the joint embedding model and the cross attention model for coreference resolution with Dravidian languages in mind. We also demonstrate that cross-attention captures pronoun-candidate relations better leading to improved coreference resolution. We also harness the similarity across South Asian languages via transfer learning in order to use high resource languages to learn coreference for low resource languages.</abstract>
      <url hash="58eb3850">2025.chipsal-1.10</url>
    </paper>
    <paper id="11">
      <title>A Dual Contrastive Learning Framework for Enhanced Hate Speech Detection in Low-Resource Languages</title>
      <author><first>Krishan</first><last>Chavinda</last></author>
      <author><first>Uthayasanker</first><last>Thayasivam</last></author>
      <pages>115–123</pages>
      <abstract>Hate speech on social media platforms is a critical issue, especially in low-resource languages such as Sinhala and Tamil, where the lack of annotated datasets and linguistic tools hampers the development of effective detection systems. This research introduces a novel framework for detecting hate speech in low resource languages by leveraging Multilingual Large Language Models (MLLMs) integrated with a Dual Contrastive Learning (DCL) strategy. Our approach enhances detection by capturing the nuances of hate speech in low-resource settings, applying both self-supervised and supervised contrastive learning techniques. We evaluate our framework using datasets from Facebook and Twitter, demonstrating its superior performance compared to traditional deep learning models like CNN, LSTM, and BiGRU. The results highlight the efficacy of DCL models, particularly when fine-tuned on domain-specific data, with the best performance achieved using the Twitter/twhin-bert-base model. This study underscores the potential of advanced machine learning techniques in improving hate speech detection for under-resourced languages, paving the way for further research in this domain.</abstract>
      <url hash="533709d5">2025.chipsal-1.11</url>
    </paper>
    <paper id="12">
      <title>Abstractive Summarization of Low resourced <fixed-case>N</fixed-case>epali language using Multilingual Transformers</title>
      <author><first>Prakash</first><last>Dhakal</last></author>
      <author><first>Daya Sagar</first><last>Baral</last></author>
      <pages>124–133</pages>
      <abstract>Nepali, one of the prominent languages of South Asia, remains underrepresented in natural language processing (NLP) research, particularly in the domain of abstractive summarization. While significant progress has been made in extractive summarization, the complexity of generating coherent, human-like summaries from low-resource languages like Nepali is still largely unexplored. This paper introduces the first comprehensive study on applying multilingual transformer-based models, specifically mBART and mT5, to the task of generating headlines for Nepali news articles through abstractive summarization. Given the absence of large-scale datasets for this task, a new Nepali news headline summarization corpus was created by scraping data from multiple online news portals. The models were fine-tuned with this novel dataset using Low-Rank Adaptation (LoRA) and quantization techniques, allowing for more computationally efficient training while preserving performance. The models’ effectiveness was evaluated using ROUGE scores and a human evaluation approach that focused on relevance, fluency, conciseness, informativeness, factual accuracy, and coverage. The findings demonstrate that a 4-bit quantized mBART model achieves superior performance, offering significant potential for improving digital content summarization for Nepali. This study highlights key challenges in processing Nepali, particularly its orthographic and resource limitations, while providing a path forward for advancing NLP tools for South Asian languages.</abstract>
      <url hash="8a19f317">2025.chipsal-1.12</url>
    </paper>
    <paper id="13">
      <title>Structured Information Extraction from <fixed-case>N</fixed-case>epali Scanned Documents using Layout Transformer and <fixed-case>LLM</fixed-case>s</title>
      <author><first>Aayush</first><last>Neupane</last></author>
      <author><first>Aayush</first><last>Lamichhane</last></author>
      <author><first>Ankit</first><last>Paudel</last></author>
      <author><first>Aman</first><last>Shakya</last></author>
      <pages>134–143</pages>
      <abstract>Despite growing global interest in information extraction from scanned documents, there is still a significant research gap concerning Nepali documents. This study seeks to address this gap by focusing on methods for extracting information from texts with Nepali typeface or Devanagari characters. The primary focus is on the performance of the Language Independent Layout Transformer (LiLT), which was employed as a token classifier to extract information from Nepali texts. LiLT achieved F1 score of approximately 0.87. Complementing this approach, large language models (LLMs), including OpenAI’s proprietary GPT-4o and the open-source Llama 3.1 8B, were also evaluated. The GPT-4o model exhibited promising performance, with an accuracy of around 55-80% accuracy for a complete match, accuracy varying among different fields. Llama 3.1 8B model achieved only 20-40% accuracy. For 90% match both GPT-4o and Llama 3.1 8B had higher accuracy by varying amounts for different fields. Llama 3.1 8B performed particularly poorly compared to the LiLT model. These results aim to provide a foundation for future work in the domain of digitization of Nepali documents.</abstract>
      <url hash="b5b40115">2025.chipsal-1.13</url>
    </paper>
    <paper id="14">
      <title>Domain-adaptative Continual Learning for Low-resource Tasks: Evaluation on <fixed-case>N</fixed-case>epali</title>
      <author><first>Sharad</first><last>Duwal</last></author>
      <author><first>Suraj</first><last>Prasai</last></author>
      <author><first>Suresh</first><last>Manandhar</last></author>
      <pages>144–153</pages>
      <abstract>Continual learning has emerged as an important research direction due to the infeasibility of retraining large language models (LLMs) from scratch in the event of new data availability. Of great interest is the domain-adaptive pre-training (DAPT) paradigm, which focuses on continually training a pre-trained language model to adapt it to a domain it wasn’t originally trained on. In this work, we evaluate the feasibility of DAPT in a low-resource setting, namely the Nepali language. We use synthetic data to continue training Llama 3 8B to adapt it to the Nepali language in a 4-bit QLoRA setting. We evaluate the adapted model on its performance, catastrophic forgetting, and knowledge acquisition. We compare the base model and the final model on their Nepali generation abilities, their performance on popular benchmarks, and run case-studies to probe their linguistic knowledge in Nepali. We use GPT-4o as an evaluator to establish that the final model has learned to generate Nepali. We see some unsurprising forgetting in the final model, but also surprisingly find that increasing the number of shots while evaluation yields better percent increases in the final model (as high as 19.29% increase) compared to the base model (4.98%), suggesting latent retention. We also explore layer–head self-attention heatmaps to establish the dependency resolution abilities of the final model in Nepali. We open-source the model and the code.</abstract>
      <url hash="966bcf80">2025.chipsal-1.14</url>
    </paper>
    <paper id="15">
      <title><fixed-case>POS</fixed-case>-Aware Neural Approaches for Word Alignment in <fixed-case>D</fixed-case>ravidian Languages</title>
      <author><first>Antony Alexander</first><last>James</last></author>
      <author><first>Parameswari</first><last>Krishnamurthy</last></author>
      <pages>154–159</pages>
      <abstract>This research explores word alignment in low-resource languages, specifically focusing on Telugu and Tamil, two languages within the Dravidian language family. Traditional statistical models such as FastAlign, GIZA++, and Eflomal serve as baselines but are often limited in low-resource settings. Neural methods, including SimAlign and AWESOME-align, which leverage multilingual BERT, show promising results by achieving alignment without extensive parallel data. Applying these neural models to Telugu-Tamil and Tamil-Telugu alignments, we found that fine-tuning with POS-tagged data significantly improves alignment accuracy compared to untagged data, achieving an improvement of 6–7%. However, our combined embeddings approach, which merges word embeddings with POS tags, did not yield additional gains. Expanding the study, we included Tamil, Telugu, and English alignments to explore linguistic mappings between Dravidian and an Indo-European languages. Results demonstrate the comparative performance across models and language pairs, emphasizing both the benefits of POS-tag fine-tuning and the complexities of cross-linguistic alignment.</abstract>
      <url hash="528a3e8b">2025.chipsal-1.15</url>
    </paper>
    <paper id="16">
      <title>ne<fixed-case>DIOM</fixed-case>: Dataset and Analysis of <fixed-case>N</fixed-case>epali Idioms</title>
      <author><first>Rhitabrat</first><last>Pokharel</last></author>
      <author><first>Ameeta</first><last>Agrawal</last></author>
      <pages>160–171</pages>
      <abstract>Idioms, integral to any language, convey nuanced meanings and cultural references. However, beyond English, few resources exist to support any meaningful exploration of this unique linguistic phenomenon. To facilitate such an inquiry in a low resource language, we introduce a novel dataset of Nepali idioms and the sentences in which these naturally appear. We describe the methodology of creating this resource as well as discuss some of the challenges we encountered. The results of our empirical analysis under various settings using four distinct multilingual models consistently highlight the difficulties these models face in processing Nepali figurative language. Even fine-tuning the models yields limited benefits. Interestingly, the larger models from the BLOOM family of models failed to consistently outperform the smaller models. Overall, we hope that this new resource will facilitate further development of models that can support processing of idiomatic expressions in low resource languages such as Nepali.</abstract>
      <url hash="8555d145">2025.chipsal-1.16</url>
    </paper>
    <paper id="17">
      <title>Bridging the Bandwidth Gap: A Mixed Band Telephonic <fixed-case>U</fixed-case>rdu <fixed-case>ASR</fixed-case> Approach with Domain Adaptation for Banking Applications</title>
      <author><first>Ayesha</first><last>Khalid</last></author>
      <author><first>Farah</first><last>Adeeba</last></author>
      <author><first>Najm Ul</first><last>Sehar</last></author>
      <author><first>Sarmad</first><last>Hussain</last></author>
      <pages>172–184</pages>
      <abstract>The accuracy of Automatic Speech Recognition (ASR) systems is influenced by the quality and context of speech signals, particularly in telephonic environments prone to errors like channel drops and noise, leading to higher Word Error Rates (WER). This paper presents the development of a large vocabulary Urdu ASR system for telephonic speech, based on a corpus of 445 speakers from diverse domains. The corpus, annotated at the sentence level, is used to train and evaluate GMM-HMM and chain Time-Delay Neural Network (TDNN) models on a 10-hour test set. Results show that the TDNN model outperforms GMM-HMM. Mixing narrowband and wideband speech further reduces WER. The test sets are also evaluated for the pre-trained model Whisper for performance comparison. Additionally, system adaptation for the banking domain with a specialized lexicon and language model demonstrates the system’s potential for domain-specific applications.</abstract>
      <url hash="4ddbb98e">2025.chipsal-1.17</url>
    </paper>
    <paper id="18">
      <title>Impacts of Vocoder Selection on Tacotron-based <fixed-case>N</fixed-case>epali Text-To-Speech Synthesis</title>
      <author><first>Ganesh Dhakal</first><last>Chhetri</last></author>
      <author><first>Kiran Chandra</first><last>Dahal</last></author>
      <author><first>Prakash</first><last>Poudyal</last></author>
      <pages>185–192</pages>
      <abstract>Text-to-speech (TTS) technology enhances human-computer interaction and increases content accessibility. Tacotron and other deep learning models have enhanced the naturalness of text-to-speech systems. The vocoder, which transforms mel-spectrograms into audio waveforms, significantly influences voice quality. This study evaluates Tacotron2 vocoders for Nepali text-to speech synthesis. While English language vocoders have been thoroughly examined, Nepali language vocoders remain underexplored. The study utilizes the WaveNet and MelGAN vocoders to generate speech from mel-spectrograms produced by Tacotron2 for Nepali text. In order to assess the quality of voice synthesis, this paper study the mel-cepstral distortion (MCD) and Mean Opinion Score (MOS) for speech produced by both vocoders. The comparative investigation of the Tacotron2 + MelGAN and Tacotron2 + WaveNet models, utilizing the Nepali OpenSLR and News male voice datasets, consistently reveals the advantage of Tacotron2 + MelGAN in terms of naturalness and accuracy. The Tacotron2 + MelGAN model achieved an average MOS score of 4.245 on the Nepali OpenSLR dataset and 2.885 on the male voice dataset.</abstract>
      <url hash="4a256bac">2025.chipsal-1.18</url>
    </paper>
    <paper id="19">
      <title><fixed-case>E</fixed-case>mo<fixed-case>T</fixed-case>a: A <fixed-case>T</fixed-case>amil Emotional Speech Dataset</title>
      <author><first>Jubeerathan</first><last>Thevakumar</last></author>
      <author><first>Luxshan</first><last>Thavarasa</last></author>
      <author><first>Thanikan</first><last>Sivatheepan</last></author>
      <author><first>Sajeev</first><last>Kugarajah</last></author>
      <author><first>Uthayasanker</first><last>Thayasivam</last></author>
      <pages>193–201</pages>
      <abstract>This paper introduces EmoTa, the first emotional speech dataset in Tamil, designed to reflect the linguistic diversity of Sri Lankan Tamil speakers. EmoTa comprises 936 recorded utterances from 22 native Tamil speakers (11 male, 11 female), each articulating 19 semantically neutral sentences across five primary emotions: anger, happiness, sadness, fear, and neutrality. To ensure quality, inter-annotator agreement was assessed using Fleiss’ Kappa, resulting in a substantial agreement score of 0.74. Initial evaluations using machine learning models, including XGBoost and Random Forest, yielded a high F1-score of 0.91 and 0.90 for emotion classification tasks. By releasing EmoTa, we aim to encourage further exploration of Tamil language processing and the development of innovative models for Tamil Speech Emotion Recognition.</abstract>
      <url hash="a9504e41">2025.chipsal-1.19</url>
    </paper>
    <paper id="20">
      <title>Benchmarking Whisper for Low-Resource Speech Recognition: An N-Shot Evaluation on <fixed-case>P</fixed-case>ashto, <fixed-case>P</fixed-case>unjabi, and <fixed-case>U</fixed-case>rdu</title>
      <author><first>Najm Ul</first><last>Sehar</last></author>
      <author><first>Ayesha</first><last>Khalid</last></author>
      <author><first>Farah</first><last>Adeeba</last></author>
      <author><first>Sarmad</first><last>Hussain</last></author>
      <pages>202–207</pages>
      <abstract>Whisper, a large-scale multilingual model, has demonstrated strong performance in speech recognition benchmarks, but its effectiveness on low-resource languages remains under-explored. This paper evaluates Whisper’s performance on Pashto, Punjabi, and Urdu, three underrepresented languages. While Automatic Speech Recognition (ASR) has advanced for widely spoken languages, low-resource languages still face challenges due to limited data. Whisper’s zero-shot performance was benchmarked and then its small variant was fine-tuned to improve transcription accuracy. Significant reductions in Word Error Rate (WER) were achieved through few-shot fine-tuning, which helped the model better handle challenges such as complex phonetic structures, compared to zero-shot performance. This study contributes to improving multilingual ASR for low-resource languages and highlights Whisper’s adaptability and potential for further enhancement.</abstract>
      <url hash="88f0fd20">2025.chipsal-1.20</url>
    </paper>
    <paper id="21">
      <title>Leveraging Machine-Generated Data for Joint Intent Detection and Slot Filling in <fixed-case>B</fixed-case>angla: A Resource-Efficient Approach</title>
      <author><first>A H M Rezaul</first><last>Karim</last></author>
      <author><first>Özlem</first><last>Uzuner</last></author>
      <pages>208–216</pages>
      <abstract>Natural Language Understanding (NLU) is crucial for conversational AI, yet low-resource languages lag behind in essential tasks like intent detection and slot-filling. To address this gap, we converted the widely-used English SNIPS dataset to Bangla using LLaMA 3, creating a dataset that captures the linguistic complexities of the language. With this translated dataset for model training, our experimental evaluation compares both independent and joint modeling approaches using transformer architecture. Results demonstrate that a joint approach based on multilingual BERT (mBERT) achieves superior performance, with 97.83% intent accuracy and 91.03% F1 score for slot filling. This work advances NLU capabilities for Bangla and provides insights for developing robust models in other low-resource languages.</abstract>
      <url hash="bdecd15a">2025.chipsal-1.21</url>
    </paper>
    <paper id="22">
      <title>Challenges in Adapting Multilingual <fixed-case>LLM</fixed-case>s to Low-Resource Languages using <fixed-case>L</fixed-case>o<fixed-case>RA</fixed-case> <fixed-case>PEFT</fixed-case> Tuning</title>
      <author><first>Omkar</first><last>Khade</last></author>
      <author><first>Shruti</first><last>Jagdale</last></author>
      <author><first>Abhishek</first><last>Phaltankar</last></author>
      <author><first>Gauri</first><last>Takalikar</last></author>
      <author><first>Raviraj</first><last>Joshi</last></author>
      <pages>217–222</pages>
      <abstract>Large Language Models (LLMs) have demonstrated remarkable multilingual capabilities, yet challenges persist in adapting these models for low-resource languages. In this study, we investigate the effects of Low-Rank Adaptation (LoRA) Parameter-Efficient Fine-Tuning (PEFT) on multilingual Gemma models for Marathi, a language with limited resources. Using a translated Alpaca dataset with 52,000 instruction-response pairs, our findings reveal that while evaluation metrics often show a performance decline post-fine-tuning, manual assessments frequently suggest that the fine-tuned models outperform their original counterparts. The observations indicate improvements in target language generation capabilities but a reduction in reasoning abilities following language adaptation. These results underscore the need for improved evaluation methodologies and the creation of high-quality native datasets to accurately assess language-specific model performance in low-resource settings.</abstract>
      <url hash="355b378f">2025.chipsal-1.22</url>
    </paper>
    <paper id="23">
      <title>1-800-<fixed-case>SHARED</fixed-case>-<fixed-case>TASKS</fixed-case>@<fixed-case>NLU</fixed-case> of <fixed-case>D</fixed-case>evanagari Script Languages 2025: Detection of Language, Hate Speech, and Targets using <fixed-case>LLM</fixed-case>s</title>
      <author><first>Jebish</first><last>Purbey</last></author>
      <author><first>Siddartha</first><last>Pullakhandam</last></author>
      <author><first>Kanwal</first><last>Mehreen</last></author>
      <author><first>Muhammad</first><last>Arham</last></author>
      <author><first>Drishti</first><last>Sharma</last></author>
      <author><first>Ashay</first><last>Srivastava</last></author>
      <author><first>Ram Mohan Rao</first><last>Kadiyala</last></author>
      <pages>223–235</pages>
      <abstract>This paper presents a detailed system description of our entry for the CHiPSAL 2025 challenge, focusing on language detection, hate speech identification, and target detection in Devanagari script languages. We experimented with a combination of large language models and their ensembles, including MuRIL, IndicBERT, and Gemma-2, and leveraged unique techniques like focal loss to address challenges in the natural understanding of Devanagari languages, such as multilingual processing and class imbalance. Our approach achieved competitive results across all tasks: F1 of 0.9980, 0.7652, and 0.6804 for Sub-tasks A, B, and C respectively. This work provides insights into the effectiveness of transformer models in tasks with domain-specific and linguistic challenges, as well as areas for potential improvement in future iterations.</abstract>
      <url hash="a6f39d0b">2025.chipsal-1.23</url>
    </paper>
    <paper id="24">
      <title><fixed-case>A</fixed-case>ni<fixed-case>S</fixed-case>an@<fixed-case>NLU</fixed-case> of <fixed-case>D</fixed-case>evanagari Script Languages 2025: Optimizing Language Identification with Ensemble Learning</title>
      <author><first>Anik Mahmud</first><last>Shanto</last></author>
      <author><first>Mst. Sanjida Jamal</first><last>Priya</last></author>
      <author><first>Mohammad Shamsul</first><last>Arefin</last></author>
      <pages>236–241</pages>
      <abstract>Identifying languages written in Devanagari script, including Hindi, Marathi, Nepali, Bhojpuri, and Sanskrit, is essential in multilingual contexts but challenging due to the high overlap between these languages. To address this, a shared task on “Devanagari Script Language Identification” has been organized, with a dataset available for subtask A to test language identification models. This paper introduces an ensemble-based approach that combines mBERT, XLM-R, and IndicBERT models through majority voting to improve language identification accuracy across these languages. Our ensemble model has achieved an impressive accuracy of 99.68%, outperforming individual models by capturing a broader range of language features and reducing model biases that often arise from closely related linguistic patterns. Additionally, we have fine-tuned other transformer models as part of a comparative analysis, providing further validation of the ensemble’s effectiveness. The results highlight the ensemble model’s ability in distinguishing similar languages within the Devanagari script, offering a promising approach for accurate language identification in complex multilingual contexts.</abstract>
      <url hash="a0d92d37">2025.chipsal-1.24</url>
    </paper>
    <paper id="25">
      <title>byte<fixed-case>S</fixed-case>ized<fixed-case>LLM</fixed-case>@<fixed-case>NLU</fixed-case> of <fixed-case>D</fixed-case>evanagari Script Languages 2025: Hate Speech Detection and Target Identification Using Customized Attention <fixed-case>B</fixed-case>i<fixed-case>LSTM</fixed-case> and <fixed-case>XLM</fixed-case>-<fixed-case>R</fixed-case>o<fixed-case>BERT</fixed-case>a Base Embeddings</title>
      <author><first>Rohith Gowtham</first><last>Kodali</last></author>
      <author><first>Durga Prasad</first><last>Manukonda</last></author>
      <author><first>Daniel</first><last>Iglesias</last></author>
      <pages>242–247</pages>
      <abstract>This paper presents a novel approach to hate speech detection and target identification across Devanagari-script languages, with a focus on Hindi and Nepali. Leveraging an Attention BiLSTM-XLM-RoBERTa architecture, our model effectively captures language-specific features and sequential dependencies crucial for multilingual natural language understanding (NLU). In Task B (Hate Speech Detection), our model achieved a Macro F1 score of 0.7481, demonstrating its robustness in identifying hateful content across linguistic variations. For Task C (Target Identification), it reached a Macro F1 score of 0.6715, highlighting its ability to classify targets into “individual,” “organization,” and “community” with high accuracy. Our work addresses the gap in Devanagari-scripted multilingual hate speech analysis and sets a benchmark for future research in low-resource language contexts.</abstract>
      <url hash="4dd61eb8">2025.chipsal-1.25</url>
    </paper>
    <paper id="26">
      <title>byte<fixed-case>S</fixed-case>ized<fixed-case>LLM</fixed-case>@<fixed-case>NLU</fixed-case> of <fixed-case>D</fixed-case>evanagari Script Languages 2025: Language Identification Using Customized Attention <fixed-case>B</fixed-case>i<fixed-case>LSTM</fixed-case> and <fixed-case>XLM</fixed-case>-<fixed-case>R</fixed-case>o<fixed-case>BERT</fixed-case>a base Embeddings</title>
      <author><first>Durga Prasad</first><last>Manukonda</last></author>
      <author><first>Rohith Gowtham</first><last>Kodali</last></author>
      <pages>248–252</pages>
      <abstract>This study explores the challenges of natural language understanding (NLU) in multilingual contexts, focusing on Devanagari-scripted languages such as Nepali, Marathi, Sanskrit, Bhojpuri, and Hindi. Language identification within these languages is complex due to their structural and lexical similarities. We present a hybrid Attention BiLSTM-XLM-RoBERTa model, achieving a state-of-the-art F1 score of 0.9974 on the test set, despite limited resources. Our model effectively distinguishes between closely related Devanagari-scripted languages, providing a solid foundation for context-aware NLU systems that enhance language-specific processing and promote inclusive digital interactions across diverse linguistic communities.</abstract>
      <url hash="dc29f339">2025.chipsal-1.26</url>
    </paper>
    <paper id="27">
      <title><fixed-case>CUET</fixed-case>_<fixed-case>B</fixed-case>ig_<fixed-case>O</fixed-case>@<fixed-case>NLU</fixed-case> of <fixed-case>D</fixed-case>evanagari Script Languages 2025: Identifying Script Language and Detecting Hate Speech Using Deep Learning and Transformer Model</title>
      <author><first>Md. Refaj</first><last>Hossan</last></author>
      <author><first>Nazmus</first><last>Sakib</last></author>
      <author><first>Md. Alam</first><last>Miah</last></author>
      <author><first>Jawad</first><last>Hossain</last></author>
      <author><first>Mohammed Moshiul</first><last>Hoque</last></author>
      <pages>253–259</pages>
      <abstract>Text-based hate speech has been prevalent and is usually used to incite hostility and violence. Detecting this content becomes imperative, yet the task is challenging, particularly for low-resource languages in the Devanagari script, which must have the extensive labeled datasets required for effective machine learning. To address this, a shared task has been organized for identifying hate speech targets in Devanagari-script text. The task involves classifying targets such as individuals, organizations, and communities and identifying different languages within the script. We have explored several machine learning methods such as LR, SVM, MNB, and Random Forest, deep learning models using CNN, BiLSTM, GRU, CNN+BiLSTM, and transformer-based models like Indic-BERT, m-BERT, Verta-BERT, XLM-R, and MuRIL. The CNN with BiLSTM yielded the best performance (F1-score of 0.9941), placing the team 13th in the competition for script identification. Furthermore, the fine-tuned MuRIL-BERT model resulted in an F1 score of 0.6832, ranking us 4th for detecting hate speech targets.</abstract>
      <url hash="fb1226ef">2025.chipsal-1.27</url>
    </paper>
    <paper id="28">
      <title><fixed-case>CUET</fixed-case>_<fixed-case>H</fixed-case>ate<fixed-case>S</fixed-case>hield@<fixed-case>NLU</fixed-case> of <fixed-case>D</fixed-case>evanagari Script Languages 2025: Transformer-Based Hate Speech Detection in <fixed-case>D</fixed-case>evanagari Script Languages</title>
      <author><first>Sumaiya Rahman</first><last>Aodhora</last></author>
      <author><first>Shawly</first><last>Ahsan</last></author>
      <author><first>Mohammed Moshiul</first><last>Hoque</last></author>
      <pages>260–266</pages>
      <abstract>Social media has become a vital platform for information exchange and free expression, yet its open nature also contributes to the spread of harmful content, including hate speech, cyberbullying, and offensive language, posing serious risks to societal well-being. Such content is linked to adverse impacts, including mental health issues. This study aims to develop an automated system for detecting hate speech in Devanagari script languages, enabling efficient moderation and prompt intervention. Our approach utilizes a fine-tuned transformer model to classify offensive content. We experimented with various machine learning (Logistic Regression, SVM, Ensemble methods) and deep learning architectures (CNN, BiLSTM, CNN-BiLSTM) alongside transformer-based models (Indic-SBERT, m-BERT, MuRIL, Indic-SBERT, XLM-R). Notably, the fine-tuned XLM-Roberta model achieved the highest performance, reaching a macro-average F1-score of 0.74, demonstrating its efficacy in detecting hate speech in Devanagari script languages. However, the model we submitted achieved a macro-average F1-score of 0.73, securing 13th place in the subtask.</abstract>
      <url hash="de197965">2025.chipsal-1.28</url>
    </paper>
    <paper id="29">
      <title><fixed-case>CUET</fixed-case>_<fixed-case>INS</fixed-case>ights@<fixed-case>NLU</fixed-case> of <fixed-case>D</fixed-case>evanagari Script Languages 2025: Leveraging Transformer-based Models for Target Identification in Hate Speech</title>
      <author><first>Farjana Alam</first><last>Tofa</last></author>
      <author><first>Lorin Tasnim</first><last>Zeba</last></author>
      <author><first>Md</first><last>Osama</last></author>
      <author><first>Ashim</first><last>Dey</last></author>
      <pages>267–272</pages>
      <abstract>Hate speech detection in multilingual content is a challenging problem especially when it comes to understanding the specific targets of hateful expressions. Identifying the targets of hate speech whether directed at individuals, organizations or communities is crucial for effective content moderation and understanding the context. A shared task on hate speech detection in Devanagari Script Languages organized by CHIPSAL@COLING 2025 allowed us to address the challenge of identifying the target of hate speech in the Devanagari Script Language. For this task, we experimented with various machine learning (ML) and deep learning (DL) models including Logistic Regression, Decision Trees, Random Forest, SVM, CNN, LSTM, BiLSTM, and transformer-based models like MiniLM, m-BERT, and Indic-BERT. Our experiments demonstrated that Indic-BERT achieved the highest F1-score of 0.69, ranked 3rd in the shared task. This research contributes to advancing the field of hate speech detection and natural language processing in low-resource languages.</abstract>
      <url hash="01d5c358">2025.chipsal-1.29</url>
    </paper>
    <paper id="30">
      <title><fixed-case>CUFE</fixed-case>@<fixed-case>NLU</fixed-case> of <fixed-case>D</fixed-case>evanagari Script Languages 2025: Language Identification using fast<fixed-case>T</fixed-case>ext</title>
      <author><first>Michael</first><last>Ibrahim</last></author>
      <pages>273–277</pages>
      <abstract>Language identification is a critical area of research within natural language processing (NLP), particularly in multilingual contexts where accurate language detection can enhance the performance of various applications, such as machine translation, content moderation, and user interaction systems. This paper presents a language identification system developed using fastText. In the CHIPSAL@COLING 2025 Task on Devanagari Script Language Identification, the proposed method achieved first place, with an F1 score of 0.9997.</abstract>
      <url hash="0d9c86bf">2025.chipsal-1.30</url>
    </paper>
    <paper id="31">
      <title><fixed-case>D</fixed-case>ll5143<fixed-case>A</fixed-case>@<fixed-case>NLU</fixed-case> of <fixed-case>D</fixed-case>evanagari Script Languages 2025: Detection of Hate Speech and Targets Using Hierarchical Attention Network</title>
      <author><first>Ashok</first><last>Yadav</last></author>
      <author><first>Vrijendra</first><last>Singh</last></author>
      <pages>278–288</pages>
      <abstract>Hate speech poses a significant challenge on social networks, particularly in Devanagari scripted languages, where subtle expressions can lead to harmful narratives. This paper details our participation in the “Shared Task on Natural Language Understanding of Devanagari Script Languages” at CHIPSAL@COLING 2025, addressing hate speech detection and target identification. In Sub-task B, we focused on classifying the text either hate or non-hate classified text to determine the presence of hate speech, while Sub-task C focused on identifying targets, such as individuals, organizations, or communities. We utilized the XLM-RoBERTa model as our base and explored various adaptations, including Adaptive Weighting and Gated Adaptive Weighting methods. Our results demonstrated that the Hierarchical Gated adaptive weighting model achieved 86% accuracy in hate speech detection with a macro F1 score of 0.72, particularly improving performance for minority class detection. For target detection, the same model achieved 75% accuracy and a 0.69 macro F1 score. Our proposed architecture demonstrated competitive performance, ranking 8th in Subtask B and 11th in Subtask C among all participants.</abstract>
      <url hash="40f7aff4">2025.chipsal-1.31</url>
    </paper>
    <paper id="32">
      <title><fixed-case>DSLNLP</fixed-case>@<fixed-case>NLU</fixed-case> of <fixed-case>D</fixed-case>evanagari Script Languages 2025: Leveraging <fixed-case>BERT</fixed-case>-based Architectures for Language Identification, Hate Speech Detection and Target Classification</title>
      <author><first>Shraddha</first><last>Chauhan</last></author>
      <author><first>Abhinav</first><last>Kumar</last></author>
      <pages>289–294</pages>
      <abstract>The rapid rise of social media has emphasized the spread of harmful and hateful content, making it challenging for its identification. Contextual semantics is very important as prior studies present that context level semantics is a more trustworthy indicator of hatefulness than word level semantics for detecting hate speech. This paper attempts to check the usability of transformer-based models for the identification of hate speech on code-mixed datasets, which includes Google-MuRIL, LaBSE, XLMRoberta-base, mbert and distil-mbert. The above is largely due to its ability for high-level representations of complex and context-dense meaning. Besides this, we experiment on ensemble approach that covers all of the above models to reach out for an even higher level of performance in detection. The experiment results show the best performing macro F1-scores are reported in case of MuRIL in comparison to other implemented models.</abstract>
      <url hash="5beb69b3">2025.chipsal-1.32</url>
    </paper>
    <paper id="33">
      <title><fixed-case>IITR</fixed-case>-<fixed-case>CIOL</fixed-case>@<fixed-case>NLU</fixed-case> of <fixed-case>D</fixed-case>evanagari Script Languages 2025: Multilingual Hate Speech Detection and Target Identification in <fixed-case>D</fixed-case>evanagari-Scripted Languages</title>
      <author><first>Siddhant</first><last>Gupta</last></author>
      <author><first>Siddh</first><last>Singhal</last></author>
      <author><first>Azmine Toushik</first><last>Wasi</last></author>
      <pages>295–300</pages>
      <abstract>This work focuses on two subtasks related to hate speech detection and target identification in Devanagari-scripted languages, specifically Hindi, Marathi, Nepali, Bhojpuri, and Sanskrit. Subtask B involves detecting hate speech in online text, while Subtask C requires identifying the specific targets of hate speech, such as individuals, organizations, or communities. We develop a deep neural network built on the pretrained multilingual transformer model ‘ia-multilingual-transliterated-roberta’ by IBM, optimized for classification tasks in multilingual and transliterated contexts. The model leverages contextualized embeddings to handle linguistic diversity, with a classifier head for binary classification. We received 88.40% accuracy in Subtask B and 66.11% accuracy in Subtask C, in the test set.</abstract>
      <url hash="b2cbeea5">2025.chipsal-1.33</url>
    </paper>
    <paper id="34">
      <title><fixed-case>LLM</fixed-case>s<fixed-case>A</fixed-case>gainst<fixed-case>H</fixed-case>ate@<fixed-case>NLU</fixed-case> of <fixed-case>D</fixed-case>evanagari Script Languages 2025: Hate Speech Detection and Target Identification in <fixed-case>D</fixed-case>evanagari Languages via Parameter Efficient Fine-Tuning of <fixed-case>LLM</fixed-case>s</title>
      <author><first>Rushendra</first><last>Sidibomma</last></author>
      <author><first>Pransh</first><last>Patwa</last></author>
      <author><first>Parth</first><last>Patwa</last></author>
      <author><first>Aman</first><last>Chadha</last></author>
      <author><first>Vinija</first><last>Jain</last></author>
      <author><first>Amitava</first><last>Das</last></author>
      <pages>301–307</pages>
      <abstract>The detection of hate speech has become increasingly important in combating online hostility and its real-world consequences. Despite recent advancements, there is limited research addressing hate speech detection in Devanagari-scripted languages, where resources and tools are scarce. While large language models (LLMs) have shown promise in language-related tasks, traditional fine-tuning approaches are often infeasible given the size of the models. In this paper, we propose a Parameter Efficient Fine tuning (PEFT) based solution for hate speech detection and target identification. We evaluate multiple LLMs on the Devanagari dataset provided by Thapa et al. (2025), which contains annotated instances in 2 languages - Hindi and Nepali. The results demonstrate the efficacy of our approach in handling Devanagari-scripted content. Code will be made publicly available on GitHub following acceptance.</abstract>
      <url hash="a03b44be">2025.chipsal-1.34</url>
    </paper>
    <paper id="35">
      <title><fixed-case>MDSB</fixed-case>ots@<fixed-case>NLU</fixed-case> of <fixed-case>D</fixed-case>evanagari Script Languages 2025: Detection of Language, Hate Speech, and Targets using <fixed-case>MURT</fixed-case>weet</title>
      <author><first>Prabhat</first><last>Ale</last></author>
      <author><first>Anish</first><last>Thapaliya</last></author>
      <author><first>Suman</first><last>Paudel</last></author>
      <pages>308–313</pages>
      <abstract>In multilingual contexts, an automated system for accurate language identification, followed by hate speech detection and target identification, plays a critical role in processing low-resource hate speech data and mitigating its negative impact. This paper presents our approach to the three subtasks in the Shared Task on Natural Language Understanding of Devanagari Script Languages at CHIPSAL@COLING 2025: (i) Language Identification, (ii) Hate Speech Detection, and (iii) Target Identification. Both classical machine learning and multilingual transformer models were explored, where MuRIL Large, trained on undersampled data for subtasks A and B outperformed the classical models. For subtask C, the Hybrid model trained on augmented data achieved superior performance over classical and transformer-based approaches. The top-performing models, named MURTweet for subtasks A and B and NER-MURTweet for subtask C, secured sixth, third, and first rank respectively, in the competition.</abstract>
      <url hash="4a041909">2025.chipsal-1.35</url>
    </paper>
    <paper id="36">
      <title><fixed-case>N</fixed-case>epali Transformers@<fixed-case>NLU</fixed-case> of <fixed-case>D</fixed-case>evanagari Script Languages 2025: Detection of Language, Hate Speech and Targets</title>
      <author><first>Pilot</first><last>Khadka</last></author>
      <author><first>Ankit</first><last>Bk</last></author>
      <author><first>Ashish</first><last>Acharya</last></author>
      <author><first>Bikram</first><last>K.c.</last></author>
      <author><first>Sandesh</first><last>Shrestha</last></author>
      <author><first>Rabin</first><last>Thapa</last></author>
      <pages>314–319</pages>
      <abstract>The Devanagari script, an Indic script used by a diverse range of South Asian languages, presents a significant challenge in Natural Language Processing (NLP) research. The dialect and language variation, complex script features, and limited language-specific tools make development difficult. This shared task aims to address this challenge by bringing together researchers and practitioners to solve three key problems: Language identification, Hate speech detection, and Targets of Hate speech identification. The selected languages- Hindi, Nepali, Marathi, Sanskrit, and Bhojpuri- are widely used in South Asia and represent distinct linguistic structures. In this work, we explore the effectiveness of both machine-learning models and transformer-based models on all three sub-tasks. Our results demonstrate strong performance of the multilingual transformer model, particularly one pre-trained on domain-specific social media data, across all three tasks. The multilingual RoBERTa model, trained on the Twitter dataset, achieved a remarkable accuracy and F1-score of 99.5% on language identification (Task A), 88.3% and 72.5% on Hate Speech detection (Task B), and 68.6% and 61.8% on Hate Speech Target Classification (Task C).</abstract>
      <url hash="d49dc62b">2025.chipsal-1.36</url>
    </paper>
    <paper id="37">
      <title><fixed-case>NLP</fixed-case>ineers@ <fixed-case>NLU</fixed-case> of <fixed-case>D</fixed-case>evanagari Script Languages 2025: Hate Speech Detection using Ensembling of <fixed-case>BERT</fixed-case>-based models</title>
      <author><first>Nadika</first><last>Poudel</last></author>
      <author><first>Anmol</first><last>Guragain</last></author>
      <author><first>Rajesh</first><last>Piryani</last></author>
      <author><first>Bishesh</first><last>Khanal</last></author>
      <pages>320–326</pages>
      <abstract>This paper explores hate speech detection in Devanagari-scripted languages, focusing on Hindi and Nepali, for Subtask B of the CHIPSAL@COLING 2025 Shared Task. Using a range of transformer-based models such as XLM-RoBERTa, MURIL, and IndicBERT, we examine their effectiveness in navigating the nuanced boundary between hate speech and free expression. Our best performing model, implemented as ensemble of multilingual BERT models achieve Recall of 0.7762 (Rank 3/31 in terms of recall) and F1 score of 0.6914 (Rank 17/31). To address class imbalance, we used backtranslation for data augmentation, and cosine similarity to preserve label consistency after augmentation. This work emphasizes the need for hate speech detection in Devanagari-scripted languages and presents a foundation for further research. We plan to release the code upon acceptance.</abstract>
      <url hash="c36b3345">2025.chipsal-1.37</url>
    </paper>
    <paper id="38">
      <title>One_by_zero@ <fixed-case>NLU</fixed-case> of <fixed-case>D</fixed-case>evanagari Script Languages 2025: Target Identification for Hate Speech Leveraging Transformer-based Approach</title>
      <author><first>Dola</first><last>Chakraborty</last></author>
      <author><first>Jawad</first><last>Hossain</last></author>
      <author><first>Mohammed Moshiul</first><last>Hoque</last></author>
      <pages>327–333</pages>
      <abstract>People often use written words to spread hate aimed at different groups that cannot be practically detected manually. Therefore, developing an automatic system capable of identifying hate speech is crucial. However, creating such a system in a low-resourced languages (LRLs) script like Devanagari becomes challenging. Hence, the Devanagari script has organized a shared task targeting hate speech identification. This work proposes a pre-trained transformer-based model to identify the target of hate speech, classifying it as directed toward an individual, organization, or community. We performed extensive experiments, exploring various machine learning (LR, SVM, and ensemble), deep learning (CNN, LSTM, CNN+BiLSTM), and transformer-based models (IndicBERT, mBERT, MuRIL, XLM-R) to identify hate speech. Experimental results indicate that the IndicBERT model achieved the highest performance among all other models, obtaining a macro F1-score of 0.6785, which placed the team 6th in the task.</abstract>
      <url hash="8d0373d7">2025.chipsal-1.38</url>
    </paper>
    <paper id="39">
      <title>Paramananda@<fixed-case>NLU</fixed-case> of <fixed-case>D</fixed-case>evanagari Script Languages 2025: Detection of Language, Hate Speech and Targets using <fixed-case>F</fixed-case>ast<fixed-case>T</fixed-case>ext and <fixed-case>BERT</fixed-case></title>
      <author><first>Darwin</first><last>Acharya</last></author>
      <author><first>Sundeep</first><last>Dawadi</last></author>
      <author><first>Shivram</first><last>Saud</last></author>
      <author><first>Sunil</first><last>Regmi</last></author>
      <pages>334–338</pages>
      <abstract>This paper presents a comparative analysis of FastText and BERT-based approaches for Natural Language Understanding (NLU) tasks in Devanagari script languages. We evaluate these models on three critical tasks: language identification, hate speech detection, and target identification across five languages: Nepali, Marathi, Sanskrit, Bhojpuri, and Hindi. Our experiments, although with raw tweet dataset but extracting only devanagari script, demonstrate that while both models achieve exceptional performance in language identification (F1 scores &gt; 0.99), they show varying effectiveness in hate speech detection and target identification tasks. FastText with augmented data outperforms BERT in hate speech detection (F1 score: 0.8552 vs 0.5763), while BERT shows superior performance in target identification (F1 score: 0.5785 vs 0.4898). These findings contribute to the growing body of research on NLU for low-resource languages and provide insights into model selection for specific tasks in Devanagari script processing.</abstract>
      <url hash="31c4bdfe">2025.chipsal-1.39</url>
    </paper>
    <paper id="40">
      <title><fixed-case>SKPD</fixed-case> Emergency @ <fixed-case>NLU</fixed-case> of <fixed-case>D</fixed-case>evanagari Script Languages 2025: <fixed-case>D</fixed-case>evanagari Script Classification using <fixed-case>CBOW</fixed-case> Embeddings with Attention-Enhanced <fixed-case>B</fixed-case>i<fixed-case>LSTM</fixed-case></title>
      <author><first>Shubham</first><last>Shakya</last></author>
      <author><first>Saral</first><last>Sainju</last></author>
      <author><first>Subham Krishna</first><last>Shrestha</last></author>
      <author><first>Prekshya</first><last>Dawadi</last></author>
      <author><first>Shreya</first><last>Khatiwada</last></author>
      <pages>339–343</pages>
      <abstract>Devanagari script, encompassing languages such as Nepali, Marathi, Sanskrit, Bhojpuri and Hindi, involves challenges for identification due to its overlapping character sets and lexical characteristics. To address this, we propose a method that utilizes Continuous Bag of Words (CBOW) embeddings integrated with attention-enhanced Bidirectional Long Short-Term Memory (BiLSTM) network. Our methodology involves meticulous data preprocessing and generation of word embeddings to better the model’s ability. The proposed method achieves an overall accuracy of 99%, significantly outperforming character level identification approaches. The results reveal high precision across most language pairs, though minor classification confusions persist between closely related languages. Our findings demonstrate the robustness of the CBOW-BiLSTM model for Devanagari script classification and highlights the importance of accurate language identification in preserving linguistic diversity in multilingual environments. Keywords: Language Identification, Devanagari Script, Natural Language Processing, Neural Networks</abstract>
      <url hash="1c92c60c">2025.chipsal-1.40</url>
    </paper>
  </volume>
</collection>
