<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<collection id="2025.ontolex">
  <volume id="1" ingest-date="2025-09-27" type="proceedings">
    <meta>
      <booktitle>Proceedings of the 5th Conference on Language, Data and Knowledge: The 5th OntoLex Workshop</booktitle>
      <editor><first>Katerina</first><last>Gkirtzou</last><affiliation>ILSP ``Athena'' Research Center, Greece</affiliation></editor>
      <editor><first>Slavko</first><last>Žitnik</last><affiliation>University of Ljubljana, Slovenia</affiliation></editor>
      <editor><first>Jorge</first><last>Gracia</last><affiliation>University of Zaragoza, Spain</affiliation></editor>
      <editor><first>Dagmar</first><last>Gromann</last><affiliation>University of Vienna, Austria</affiliation></editor>
      <editor><first>Maria Pia</first><last>di Buono</last><affiliation>University of Naples “L’Orientale”, Italy</affiliation></editor>
      <editor><first>Johanna</first><last>Monti</last><affiliation>University of Naples “L’Orientale”, Italy</affiliation></editor>
      <editor><first>Maxim</first><last>Ionov</last><affiliation>University of Zaragoza, Spain</affiliation></editor>
      <publisher>Unior Press</publisher>
      <address>Naples, Italy</address>
      <month>September</month>
      <year>2025</year>
      <url hash="7937dedc">2025.ontolex-1</url>
      <venue>ontolex</venue>
      <venue>ws</venue>
      <isbn>978-88-6719-334-9</isbn>
    </meta>
    <frontmatter>
      <url hash="7814f27a">2025.ontolex-1.0</url>
      <bibkey>ontolex-ws-2025-1</bibkey>
    </frontmatter>
    <paper id="1">
      <title>Inferring Adjective Hypernyms with Language Models to Increase the Connectivity of Open <fixed-case>E</fixed-case>nglish <fixed-case>W</fixed-case>ordnet</title>
      <author><first>Lorenzo</first><last>Augello</last></author>
      <author><first>John Philip</first><last>McCrae</last></author>
      <pages>1-11</pages>
      <abstract/>
      <url hash="fbf8cb6a">2025.ontolex-1.1</url>
      <bibkey>augello-mccrae-2025-inferring</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="2">
      <title>Bringing <fixed-case>IATE</fixed-case> into the Semantic Web Family</title>
      <author><first>Paula</first><last>Diez Ibarbia</last></author>
      <author><first>Patricia</first><last>Martín Chozas</last></author>
      <author><first>Elena</first><last>Montiel Ponsoda</last></author>
      <pages>12-17</pages>
      <abstract>This paper is an extension of previous work by the authors and other researchers that studies the application of the OntoLex-lemon model for representing the InterActive Terminology for Europe (IATE) database in the Semantic Web. While traditional XML-based approaches have been effective for multilingual terminological work, the Semantic Web enables richer, more interoperable representations. The study evaluates the suitability of OntoLex-lemon for modeling IATE’s complex structure and identifies limitations in existing vocabularies. To address these, this paper tries to identify orher existing vocabularies and ontologies that could satisfy those limitations, which include term reliability, regional usage, lifecycle statuses, lookup forms, and concept cross-references. Still, some representation requirements are not covered by existing vocabularies and may need to be further discussed within the community.</abstract>
      <url hash="2685f852">2025.ontolex-1.2</url>
      <bibkey>diez-ibarbia-etal-2025-bringing</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="3">
      <title>Ontologies for historical languages: using the <fixed-case>L</fixed-case>i<fixed-case>L</fixed-case>a and <fixed-case>O</fixed-case>nto<fixed-case>L</fixed-case>ex-Lemon framework to build a Lemma Bank for <fixed-case>O</fixed-case>ld <fixed-case>I</fixed-case>rish</title>
      <author><first>Theodorus</first><last>Fransen</last></author>
      <pages>18-29</pages>
      <abstract>This paper presents a Linked Data approach to digitising and structuring Old Irish linguistic resources using the Lila (Linking Latin) ontology, which is itself largely based on the OntoLex-Lemon framework (Cimiano et al., 2016). Old Irish, as an ancient Celtic language with fragmented textual traditions, presents unique challenges for the creation and interoperability of digital resources. This work is part of the MOLOR project, whose aim is to create a knowledge base for Old Irish by interlinking texts, lexicons, and inflectional data. The first step in this ambitious endeavour is described here: the creation of an RDF linguistic Linked Data hub known as a Lemma Bank, similar to the one created as part of the LiLa project, addressing specific linguistic challenges and opportunities while adhering to the LiLa ontology.</abstract>
      <url hash="84cc7b95">2025.ontolex-1.3</url>
      <bibkey>fransen-2025-ontologies</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="4">
      <title>A Lightweight String Based Method of Encoding Etymologies in Linked Data Lexical Resources</title>
      <author><first>Anas Fahad</first><last>Khan</last></author>
      <author><first>Maxim</first><last>Ionov</last></author>
      <author><first>Paola</first><last>Marongiu</last></author>
      <author><first>Ana</first><last>Salgado</last></author>
      <pages>30-34</pages>
      <abstract>In this submission we propose an approach to encoding etymological information as strings (“etymology strings”). We begin by discussing the advantages of such an approach with respect to one in which etymologies and etymons are explicitly represented as RDF individuals. Next we give a formal description of the regular language underlying our approach as an Extended Backus-Naur Form grammar (EBNF). We use the Chamuça Hindi lexicon as a test case for our approach and show some of the kinds of SPARQL queries which can be made using etymological strings.</abstract>
      <url hash="98789e1a">2025.ontolex-1.4</url>
      <bibkey>khan-etal-2025-lightweight</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="5">
      <title>Ontolex-Lemon in <fixed-case>W</fixed-case>ikidata and other Wikibase instances</title>
      <author><first>David</first><last>Lindemann</last></author>
      <pages>35-45</pages>
      <abstract>This paper provides insight into how the core elements of the Ontolex-Lemon model are inte- grated in the Wikibase Ontology, the data model fundamental to any instance of the Wikibase software, including Wikidata lexemes, which today is probably the largest Ontolex-Lemon use case, a dataset collaboratively built by the community of Wikidata users. We describe how lexical entries are modeled on a Wikibase, including the linguistic description of lexemes, the linking of lexical entries, lexical senses and lexical forms across resources, and links across the domain of lexemes and the ontological part of a Wikibase knowledge graph. Our aim is to present Wikibase as a solution for storing and collaboratively editing lexical data follow- ing Semantic Web standards, and to identify relevant research questions to be addressed in future work.</abstract>
      <url hash="daa92678">2025.ontolex-1.5</url>
      <bibkey>lindemann-2025-ontolex</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="6">
      <title>Philosophising Lexical Meaning as an <fixed-case>O</fixed-case>nto<fixed-case>L</fixed-case>ex-Lemon Extension</title>
      <author><first>Veruska</first><last>Zamborlini</last></author>
      <author><first>Jiaqi</first><last>Zhu</last></author>
      <author><first>Marieke</first><last>van Erp</last></author>
      <author><first>Arianna</first><last>Betti</last></author>
      <pages>46-57</pages>
      <abstract>OntoLex-Lemon is a model for representing lexical information, focusing on the use of lexical entries in texts rather than their definitions. This work proposes an extension to the model that aims to capture the definition of senses attributed to lexical entries. We explicitly represent a conceptual setup authored by an agent that operates on lexical content. It either proposes new senses for existing lexical entries in a language or coins new terms to express proposed senses. It provides textual and/or formal definitions to senses/concepts, and can serve as an interpretation of other senses/concepts through rephrasing, translation, formalization, or comparison. Because a conceptual setup and its interpretations may not be unanimously accepted, it is important to support the selection of relevant meanings, as for example, those proposed by a certain author. We illustrate the application of our proposed extension with two case studies, one about the philosophical definition of the concept of idea and its interpretations, and one about historical attributions of meaning to the Dutch East India Company (VOC).</abstract>
      <url hash="01a12ed3">2025.ontolex-1.6</url>
      <bibkey>zamborlini-etal-2025-philosophising</bibkey>
    </paper>
  </volume>
</collection>
