<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<collection id="2026.vardial">
  <volume id="1" type="proceedings" ingest-date="2026-03-17">
    <meta>
      <booktitle>Proceedings of the 13th Workshop on <fixed-case>NLP</fixed-case> for Similar Languages, Varieties and Dialects</booktitle>
      <editor><first>Yves</first><last>Scherrer</last></editor>
      <editor id="noemi-aepli"><first>Noëmi</first><last>Aepli</last></editor>
      <editor id="verena-blaschke"><first>Verena</first><last>Blaschke</last></editor>
      <editor><first>Tommi</first><last>Jauhiainen</last></editor>
      <editor><first>Nikola</first><last>Ljubešić</last></editor>
      <editor id="preslav-nakov"><first>Preslav</first><last>Nakov</last></editor>
      <editor id="jorg-tiedemann"><first>Jörg</first><last>Tiedemann</last></editor>
      <editor id="marcos-zampieri"><first>Marcos</first><last>Zampieri</last></editor>
      <publisher>Association for Computational Linguistics</publisher>
      <address>Rabat, Morocco</address>
      <month>March</month>
      <year>2026</year>
      <url hash="dd826d4b">2026.vardial-1</url>
      <venue>vardial</venue>
      <venue>ws</venue>
    </meta>
    <frontmatter>
      <url hash="2d2942bf">2026.vardial-1.0</url>
      <bibkey>vardial-2026-1</bibkey>
    </frontmatter>
    <paper id="1">
      <title><fixed-case>AMIYA</fixed-case> Shared Task: <fixed-case>A</fixed-case>rabic Modeling In Your Accent at <fixed-case>V</fixed-case>ar<fixed-case>D</fixed-case>ial 2026</title>
      <author><first>Nathaniel R.</first><last>Robinson</last></author>
      <author><first>Shahd</first><last>Abdelmoneim</last></author>
      <author><first>Anjali</first><last>Kantharuban</last></author>
      <author><first>Otba</first><last>Alsboul</last></author>
      <author><first>Salima</first><last>Lamsiyah</last></author>
      <author><first>Kelly</first><last>Marchisio</last></author>
      <author><first>Kenton</first><last>Murray</last></author>
      <pages>1-17</pages>
      <abstract>Arabic, often considered a single language, actually describes a wide variety of sometimes mutually unintelligible language varieties. While large language models (LLMs) have revolutionized natural language processing (NLP) with rapid advances, these models still best serve speakers of high-resource and standard language varieties. One particular deficiency of theirs is in dialectal Arabic. We present the first ever shared task for dialectal Arabic language modeling: Arabic Modeling In Your Accent, or AMIYA. The goal of the shared task was to develop LLMs that could (1) respond in the correct dialectal variety when explicitly or implicitly prompted to, (2) translate between dialectal Arabic and standard Arabic or English, (3) adhere to LLM instructions in dialectal Arabic, and (4) produce fluent Arabic outputs. We called for submissions in the dialectal varieties of five countries: Morocco, Egypt, Palestine, Syria, and Saudi Arabia. We received 45 submitted systems from six participating teams. We saw positive results from supervised fine-tuning on a translation objective, and reinforcement learning to improve dialectness. Manual evaluation also showed that some systems had learned to output dialectal words or phrases, but at the expense of actual fluency or coherence. Overall the most effective system involved continual pre-training and supervised fine-tuning of 12 candidate LLMs, followed by selection of the best performing models.</abstract>
      <url hash="13f80bb6">2026.vardial-1.1</url>
      <bibkey>robinson-etal-2026-amiya</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="2">
      <title>Far Out: Evaluating Language Models on Slang in <fixed-case>A</fixed-case>ustralian and <fixed-case>I</fixed-case>ndian <fixed-case>E</fixed-case>nglish</title>
      <author><first>Deniz Kaya</first><last>Dilsiz</last></author>
      <author><first>Dipankar</first><last>Srirag</last></author>
      <author><first>Aditya</first><last>Joshi</last></author>
      <pages>18-31</pages>
      <abstract>Language models exhibit systematic performance gaps when processing text in non-standard language varieties, yet their ability to comprehend variety-specific slang remains underexplored for several languages. We present a comprehensive evaluation of slang awareness in Indian English (en-IN) and Australian English (en-AU) across seven state-of-the-art language models. We construct two complementary datasets: WEB, containing 377 web-sourced usage examples from Urban Dictionary, and GEN, featuring 1,492 synthetically generated usages of these slang terms, across diverse scenarios. We assess language models on three tasks: target word prediction (TWP), guided target word prediction (TWP*) and target word selection (TWS). Our results reveal four key findings: (1) Higher average model performance TWS versus TWP and TWP*, with average accuracy score increasing from 0.03 to 0.49 respectively (2) Stronger average model performance on WEB versus GEN datasets, with average similarity score increasing by 0.03 and 0.05 across TWP and TWP* tasks respectively (3) en-IN tasks outperform en-AU when averaged across all models and datasets, with TWS demonstrating the largest disparity, increasing average accuracy from 0.44 to 0.54. These findings underscore fundamental asymmetries between generative and discriminative competencies for variety-specific language, particularly in the context of slang expressions despite being in a technologically rich language such as English.</abstract>
      <url hash="9df61b6d">2026.vardial-1.2</url>
      <bibkey>dilsiz-etal-2026-far</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="3">
      <title>Effects of Speaker Bias in Dialect Identification and Automatic Transcription with Self-Supervised Speech Models</title>
      <author><first>Olli</first><last>Kuparinen</last></author>
      <pages>32-44</pages>
      <abstract>A major issue in audio modeling is speaker bias, in which the models learn language external traits, such as a speaker’s timbre or pitch, and use this information as a shortcut to a language task. This is especially problematic for dialectology, as it is typical in dialect corpora that only a few speakers represent a complete dialect area. In this paper, we explore the effects of speaker bias in two dialectal tasks: dialect identification and automatic dialectal transcription. We build two different data partitions of dialect interviews in Finnish and Norwegian: 1) a speaker dependent partition in which all of the speakers appear in training, development, and test sets, and 2) a speaker independent partition where each speaker only appears in exactly one set. We further experiment with modifications of the training data by augmenting the original audio with pitch shifts and noise, as well as changing the original speakers’ voices with voice conversion models. We show that the dialect identification models are highly affected by speaker bias, whereas automatic dialectal transcription models are not. The audio modifications do not offer major performance gains for either of the languages or tasks.</abstract>
      <url hash="a7797745">2026.vardial-1.3</url>
      <bibkey>kuparinen-2026-effects</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="4">
      <title><fixed-case>O</fixed-case>c<fixed-case>W</fixed-case>iki<fixed-case>D</fixed-case>ialects: A <fixed-case>W</fixed-case>ikipedia Dataset With Rich Metadata for <fixed-case>O</fixed-case>ccitan Dialect Identification</title>
      <author><first>Oriane</first><last>Nédey</last></author>
      <author><first>Rachel</first><last>Bawden</last></author>
      <author><first>Thibault</first><last>Clérice</last></author>
      <author><first>Benoît</first><last>Sagot</last></author>
      <pages>45-57</pages>
      <abstract>Occitan is a Romance language spoken mostly in the South of France and characterised by rich dialectal variation, which can pose problems for certain NLP tools. This shortfall is largely attributable to the scarcity of dialect-annotated corpora, in a context where linguistic classification within the Occitan dialect continuum is still debated and major nomenclatures, such as ISO 639, fail to provide granular codes for varieties below the generic "Occitan" label. In this paper, we introduce OcWikiDialects, a new dataset comprising articles from the Occitan Wikipedia. The corpus features rich metadata, including dialect labels, and is segmented at both paragraph and sentence levels. Combined with previously released datasets, we explore approaches for Occitan dialect identification by training three types of model on up to 8 labels: linear SVM classifiers based on word and character n-grams, FastText classifiers based on pretrained vectors, and BERT-based neural classifiers adapted through fine-tuning. Evaluations across in- and out-of-domain test sets demonstrate the substantial impact of our new dataset for the task. However, a peak macro-averaged F1 score of 58.15 underscores persistent challenges for underrepresented Occitan varieties, supported by our per-dialect analysis. Code, dataset and models are available: https://github.com/DEFI-COLaF/OcWikiDialects.</abstract>
      <url hash="893ba501">2026.vardial-1.4</url>
      <bibkey>nedey-etal-2026-ocwikidialects</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="5">
      <title>Language Mixture to Develop Accurate <fixed-case>G</fixed-case>alician Dependency Parsers: An Exploration of Its Effects</title>
      <author><first>Xabier</first><last>Irastortza-Urbieta</last></author>
      <author><first>José M.</first><last>García-Miguel</last></author>
      <author><first>Marcos</first><last>Garcia</last></author>
      <pages>58-69</pages>
      <abstract>The development of accurate syntactic parsers remains a challenge for low-resource languages. To overcome it, the literature has proposed leveraging syntactic annotations from typologically related languages. This work investigates the viability and adequacy of this approach for Galician, evaluating the use of annotations from major Romance languages as source data. Our methodology extends beyond standard automatic evaluation to incorporate a detailed error analysis, which precisely quantifies the effects of multilingual training and assesses the practical scalability of the method. The results establish the necessity of embedding models for effective cross-lingual transfer and demonstrate that even languages not particularly close can yield adequate parsers. This work confirms the benefits of cross-lingual data augmentation while delineating its scalability limits. Furthermore, the error analysis identifies specific, typologically conditioned grammatical dependencies that remain persistent challenges for accurate dependency parsing.</abstract>
      <url hash="f02a6e08">2026.vardial-1.5</url>
      <bibkey>irastortza-urbieta-etal-2026-language</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="6">
      <title>Crowdsourcing Piedmontese to Test <fixed-case>LLM</fixed-case>s on Non-Standard Orthography</title>
      <author><first>Gianluca</first><last>Vico</last></author>
      <author><first>Jindřch</first><last>Libovický</last></author>
      <pages>70-86</pages>
      <abstract>We present a crowdsourced dataset for Piedmontese, an endangered Romance language of northwestern Italy. The dataset comprises 145 Italian–Piedmontese parallel sentences derived from Flores+, with translations produced by speakers writing in their natural orthographic style rather than adhering to standardized conventions, along with manual word alignment. We use this resource to benchmark several large language models on tokenization parity, topic classification, and machine translation. Our analysis reveals that Piedmontese incurs a tokenization penalty relative to higher-resource Romance languages, yet LLMs achieve classification performance approaching that of Italian, French, and English. Machine translation results are asymmetric: models translate adequately from Piedmontese into high-resource languages, but generation into Piedmontese remains challenging. The dataset and code are publicly released.</abstract>
      <url hash="5848cda7">2026.vardial-1.6</url>
      <bibkey>vico-libovicky-2026-crowdsourcing</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="7">
      <title><fixed-case>G</fixed-case>erman-<fixed-case>E</fixed-case>nglish Code-Switching in Large Language Models</title>
      <author><first>Firat Cem</first><last>Aksüt</last></author>
      <author><first>Stefan</first><last>Hillmann</last></author>
      <author><first>Pia</first><last>Knoeferle</last></author>
      <author><first>Sebastian</first><last>Möller</last></author>
      <pages>87-100</pages>
      <abstract>Code-Switching (CS) is common in multilingual communication, yet it is unclear how well current Large Language Models (LLMs) reproduce naturally occurring switching patterns. This paper studies German–English CS ("Denglisch") generated by GPT-4o and LLaMA-3.3, using Reddit data from the Denglisch Corpus as a reference. Model outputs are compared to authentic posts using established CS metrics (M-Index, I-Index, CESAR), an analysis of Shared Lexical Items (SLIs) as switch triggers, and a human evaluation of perceived naturalness and fluency. Both models approximate global CS characteristics but differ in the diversity and complexity in comparison to real data. LLaMA-3.3 more closely matches corpus-level metrics, whereas GPT-4o produces more conservative switching that is rated as significantly more natural and fluent. In addition, GPT-4o reproduces SLI-triggered switching patterns similar to those found in authentic data, while this effect is weaker for LLaMA-3.3.</abstract>
      <url hash="28caf27b">2026.vardial-1.7</url>
      <bibkey>aksut-etal-2026-german</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="8">
      <title>Perplexity as a Metric for Dialectal Distance: A Computational Study of <fixed-case>G</fixed-case>reek Varieties</title>
      <author><first>Stergios</first><last>Chatzikyriakidis</last></author>
      <author><first>Erofili</first><last>Psaltaki</last></author>
      <author><first>Dimitrios</first><last>Papadakis</last></author>
      <author><first>Erik</first><last>Henriksson</last></author>
      <author><first>Veronika</first><last>Laippala</last></author>
      <pages>101-112</pages>
      <abstract>In this paper, we use LLM perplexity as a measure to assess Greek dialectal distance. We test seven models on Standard Modern Greek (SMG) and eight dialects, namely Heptanesian, Cypriot, Maniot, Pontic, Northern, Cretan, Tsakonian, and Griko. Using samples of 5k, 15k, and 25k tokens from the GRDD+ corpus for each variety, we find a consistent dialect ranking across models, with Heptanesian closest to SMG, and Griko most distant (perplexity ratio 3.6–14.5× depending on model). These results are largely in agreement with theoretical dialectological knowledge. For example, Tsakonian consistently appears distant in all measures, reflecting its status as the sole Doric descendant, while Heptanesian appears closer by all metrics, pointing to its status as one of the dialects used to shape the official variety. Perplexity correlates strongly with Bits Per-Character (mean r = 0.94) and Normalized Compression Distance (mean r = 0.87, range 0.76–0.93), providing support for its use as a dialectometric tool. However, a number of important confounds are also found. First, tokenization effects compress Llama 2’s perplexity range. Second, genre artifacts seem to inflate the results for Cretan. Third, potential training data contamination likely reduces perplexity for Cypriot and Pontic. Lastly, we find that Greek-specific models like Meltemi and Krikri do not consistently outperform general models.</abstract>
      <url hash="1585b2c7">2026.vardial-1.8</url>
      <bibkey>chatzikyriakidis-etal-2026-perplexity</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="9">
      <title>A Subword Embedding Approach for Variation Detection in <fixed-case>L</fixed-case>uxembourgish User Comments</title>
      <author><first>Anne-Marie</first><last>Lutgen</last></author>
      <author><first>Alistair</first><last>Plum</last></author>
      <author><first>Christoph</first><last>Purschke</last></author>
      <pages>113-122</pages>
      <abstract>This paper presents an embedding-based approach to detecting variation without relying on prior normalisation or predefined variant lists. The method trains subword embeddings on raw text and groups related forms through combined cosine and n-gram similarity. This allows spelling and morphological diversity to be examined and analysed as linguistic structure rather than treated as noise. Using a large corpus of Luxembourgish user comments, the approach uncovers extensive lexical and orthographic variation that aligns with patterns described in dialectal and sociolinguistic research. The induced families capture systematic correspondences and highlight areas of regional and stylistic differentiation. The procedure does not strictly require manual annotation, but does produce transparent clusters that support both quantitative and qualitative analysis. The results demonstrate that distributional modelling can reveal meaningful patterns of variation even in “noisy” or low-resource settings, offering a reproducible methodological framework for studying language variety in multilingual and small-language contexts.</abstract>
      <url hash="8ebf22fa">2026.vardial-1.9</url>
      <bibkey>lutgen-etal-2026-subword</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="10">
      <title>Onomasiological Sense Alignment Across Dialect Dictionaries. A Taxonomy-Constrained <fixed-case>LLM</fixed-case> Classification</title>
      <author><first>Nathalie</first><last>Mederake</last></author>
      <author><first>Nico</first><last>Urbach</last></author>
      <author><first>Hanna</first><last>Fischer</last></author>
      <author><first>Alfred</first><last>Lameli</last></author>
      <pages>123-138</pages>
      <abstract>We propose a taxonomy-guided approach to semantic alignment that assigns lexicographic senses to an onomasiological taxonomy derived from the Hallig–Wartburg/Post system. Using an LLM under strict taxonomic constraints, short and heterogeneous meaning descriptions are assigned to a common conceptual space. Evaluation against expert annotation shows that run-to-run model agreement (kappa = 0.73) closely matches human agreement (kappa = 0.74), with robustness at coarse taxonomic levels and predictable degradation at finer granularity. A qualitative network analysis demonstrates the resulting potential for cross-dictionary exploration of dialectal variation in semantics.</abstract>
      <url hash="1b5658c9">2026.vardial-1.10</url>
      <bibkey>mederake-etal-2026-onomasiological</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="11">
      <title>On the Intelligibility of <fixed-case>R</fixed-case>omance Language Varieties: <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>panish and <fixed-case>P</fixed-case>ortuguese in <fixed-case>E</fixed-case>urope and <fixed-case>A</fixed-case>merica</title>
      <author><first>Liviu P.</first><last>Dinu</last></author>
      <author><first>Ana Sabina</first><last>Uban</last></author>
      <author><first>Teodor-George</first><last>Marchitan</last></author>
      <author><first>Ioan-Bogdan</first><last>Iordache</last></author>
      <author><first>Simona</first><last>Georgescu</last></author>
      <pages>139-144</pages>
      <abstract>Mutual intelligibility within language families presents a significant challenge for multilingual NLP, particularly due to the prevalence of dialectal variation and asymmetric comprehension. In this paper, we present a corpus-based computational analysis to quantify linguistic proximity across Romance language variants, with a focus on major Spanish (Argentine, Chilean and European) and Portuguese (Brazilian and European) varieties and the other main Romance languages (Italian, French, Romanian). We apply a computational metric of lexical intelligibility based on surface and semantic similarity of related words to measure mutual intelligibility for the five main Romance languages in relation to the Spanish and Portuguese varieties studied.</abstract>
      <url hash="18ca4697">2026.vardial-1.11</url>
      <bibkey>dinu-etal-2026-intelligibility</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="12">
      <title>Dialect Matters: Cross-Lingual <fixed-case>ASR</fixed-case> Transfer for Low-Resource <fixed-case>I</fixed-case>ndic Language Varieties</title>
      <author><first>Akriti</first><last>Dhasmana</last></author>
      <author><first>Aarohi</first><last>Srivastava</last></author>
      <author><first>David</first><last>Chiang</last></author>
      <pages>145-156</pages>
      <abstract>We conduct an empirical study of cross-lingual transfer using spontaneous, noisy, and code-mixed speech across a wide range of Indic dialects and language varieties. Our results indicate that although ASR performance is generally associated with phylogenetic distance across languages, this factor alone does not fully explain performance in dialectal settings. Often, fine-tuning on smaller amounts of dialectal data yields performance comparable to fine-tuning on larger amounts of phylogenetically-related, high-resource standardized languages. We also present a case study on Garhwali, a low-resource Pahari language variety, and evaluate multiple contemporary ASR models. Finally, we analyze transcription errors to examine bias toward pre-training languages, providing additional insight into challenges faced by ASR systems on dialectal and non-standardized speech.</abstract>
      <url hash="ec880ea9">2026.vardial-1.12</url>
      <bibkey>dhasmana-etal-2026-dialect</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="13">
      <title>Ara-<fixed-case>HOPE</fixed-case>: Human-Centric Post-Editing Evaluation for Dialectal <fixed-case>A</fixed-case>rabic to <fixed-case>M</fixed-case>odern <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>tandard <fixed-case>A</fixed-case>rabic Translation</title>
      <author><first>Abdullah</first><last>Alabdullah</last></author>
      <author><first>Lifeng</first><last>Han</last></author>
      <author><first>Chenghua</first><last>Lin</last></author>
      <pages>157-171</pages>
      <abstract>Dialectal Arabic to Modern Standard Arabic (DA-MSA) translation is a challenging task in Machine Translation (MT) due to significant lexical, syntactic, and semantic divergences between Arabic dialects and MSA. Existing automatic evaluation metrics and general-purpose human evaluation frameworks struggle to capture dialect-specific MT errors, hindering progress in translation assessment. This paper introduces Ara-HOPE, a human-centric post-editing evaluation framework designed to systematically address these challenges. The framework includes a five-category error taxonomy and a decision-tree annotation protocol. Through comparative evaluation of three MT systems (Arabic-centric Jais, general-purpose GPT-3.5, and baseline NLLB-200), Ara-HOPE effectively highlights systematic performance differences between these systems. Our results show that dialect-specific terminology and semantic preservation remain the most persistent challenges in DA-MSA translation. Ara-HOPE establishes a new framework for evaluating Dialectal Arabic MT quality and provides actionable guidance for improving dialect-aware MT systems. For reproducibility, we make the annotation files and related materials publicly available at https://github.com/abdullahalabdullah/Ara-HOPE.</abstract>
      <url hash="41134f10">2026.vardial-1.13</url>
      <bibkey>alabdullah-etal-2026-ara</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="14">
      <title><fixed-case>I</fixed-case>ndic-<fixed-case>T</fixed-case>uned<fixed-case>L</fixed-case>ens: Interpreting Multilingual Models in <fixed-case>I</fixed-case>ndian Languages</title>
      <author><first>Mihir</first><last>Panchal</last></author>
      <author><first>Deeksha</first><last>Varshney</last></author>
      <author><first>Mamta</first><last>.</last></author>
      <author><first>Asif</first><last>Ekbal</last></author>
      <pages>172-185</pages>
      <abstract>Multilingual large language models (LLMs) are increasingly deployed in linguistically diverse regions like India, yet most interpretability tools remain tailored to English. Prior work reveals that LLMs often operate in English centric representation spaces, making cross lingual interpretability a pressing concern. We introduce Indic-TunedLens, a novel interpretability framework specifically for Indian languages that learns shared affine transformations. Unlike the standard Logit Lens, which directly decodes intermediate activations, Indic-TunedLens adjusts hidden states for each target language, aligning them with the target output distributions to enable more faithful decoding of model representations. We evaluate our framework on 10 Indian languages using the MMLU benchmark and find that it significantly improves over SOTA interpretability methods, especially for morphologically rich, low resource languages. Our results provide crucial insights into the layer-wise semantic encoding of multilingual transformers. Our model is available at https://huggingface.co/spaces/MihirRajeshPanchal/IndicTunedLens. Our code is available at https://github.com/MihirRajeshPanchal/IndicTunedLens.</abstract>
      <url hash="077551df">2026.vardial-1.14</url>
      <bibkey>panchal-etal-2026-indic</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="15">
      <title>Building <fixed-case>ASR</fixed-case> Resources for the Hutsul Dialect of <fixed-case>U</fixed-case>krainian</title>
      <author><first>Roman</first><last>Kyslyi</last></author>
      <author><first>Artem</first><last>Orlovskyi</last></author>
      <author><first>Pavlo</first><last>Khomenko</last></author>
      <author><first>Bohdan</first><last>Onyshchenko</last></author>
      <author><first>Zakhar</first><last>Guzii</last></author>
      <pages>186-195</pages>
      <abstract>Dialectal speech remains largely underexplored in Automatic Speech Recognition (ASR) research, particularly for Slavic languages. While Ukrainian ASR systems have rapidly improved in recent years with the adoption of Whisper, XLS-R, and Wav2Vec-based models, performance on dialectal variants remains unknown and often significantly degraded. In this work, we present the first dedicated effort to build ASR resources for the Hutsul dialect of Ukrainian. We develop a data preparation and segmentation pipeline, evaluate multiple forced alignment strategies, and benchmark state-of-the-art ASR models under zero-shot and fine-tuned conditions. We evaluate results using WER and CER demonstrating that large multilingual ASR models struggle with dialectal speech, while lightweight fine-tuning produces substantial improvements. All scripts, alignment tools, and training recipes are made publicly available to support future research on Ukrainian dialect speech.</abstract>
      <url hash="f93b2e1b">2026.vardial-1.15</url>
      <bibkey>kyslyi-etal-2026-building</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="16">
      <title>From <fixed-case>F</fixed-case>us<fixed-case>H</fixed-case>a to Folk: Exploring Cross-Lingual Transfer in <fixed-case>A</fixed-case>rabic Language Models</title>
      <author><first>Abdulmuizz</first><last>Khalak</last></author>
      <author><first>Abderrahmane</first><last>Issam</last></author>
      <author><first>Gerasimos</first><last>Spanakis</last></author>
      <pages>196-209</pages>
      <abstract>Arabic Language Models (LMs) are pretrained predominately on Modern Standard Arabic (MSA) and are expected to transfer to its dialects. While MSA as the standard written variety is commonly used in formal settings, people speak and write online in various dialects that are spread across the Arab region. This poses limitations for Arabic LMs, since its dialects vary in their similarity to MSA. In this work we study cross-lingual transfer of Arabic models using probing on 3 Natural Language Processing (NLP) Tasks, and representational similarity. Our results indicate that transfer is possible but disproportionate across dialects, which we find to be partially explained by their geographic proximity. Furthermore, we find evidence for negative interference in models trained to support all Arabic dialects. This questions their degree of similarity, and raises concerns for cross-lingual transfer in Arabic models.</abstract>
      <url hash="2d1c98f8">2026.vardial-1.16</url>
      <bibkey>khalak-etal-2026-fusha</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="17">
      <title>Extending <fixed-case>ASR</fixed-case> Evaluation Resources for <fixed-case>M</fixed-case>odern <fixed-case>G</fixed-case>reek Dialects</title>
      <author><first>Chara</first><last>Tsoukala</last></author>
      <author><first>Stavros</first><last>Bompolas</last></author>
      <author><first>Antigoni</first><last>Margariti</last></author>
      <author><first>Konstantina</first><last>Panagiotou</last></author>
      <author><first>Maria Elisavet</first><last>Plaiti</last></author>
      <author><first>Nefeli</first><last>Tzanakaki</last></author>
      <author><first>Petros</first><last>Karatsareas</last></author>
      <author><first>Angela</first><last>Ralli</last></author>
      <author><first>Antonios</first><last>Anastasopoulos</last></author>
      <author><first>Stella</first><last>Markantonatou</last></author>
      <pages>210-222</pages>
      <abstract>Recent progress in Automatic Speech Recognition (ASR) has primarily benefited high-resource standard languages, while dialectal speech remains challenging and underexplored. We present an expanded benchmark for low-resource Modern Greek dialects, covering Aperathiot, Cretan, Lesbian, and Cappadocian, spanning southern, northern, and contact-influenced varieties with varying degrees of divergence from Standard Modern Greek. The benchmark provides dialectal transcriptions in the Greek alphabet, following SMG-based orthographic conventions, while preserving dialectal lexical and morphophonological forms. Using this benchmark, we evaluate state-of-the-art multilingual ASR models in a zero-shot setting and by further fine-tuning per dialect. Zero-shot results reveal a clear performance gradient with dialectal distance from Standard Modern Greek, with best WERs ranging from about 60-70% for southern dialects to over 80% for Lesbian and nearly 97% for Cappadocian. Fine-tuning substantially reduces error rates (up to 47% relative WER improvement), with Cappadocian remaining the most challenging variety (best WER 68.17%). Overall, our results highlight persistent limitations of current pretrained ASR models under dialectal variation and the need for dedicated benchmarks and adaptation strategies.</abstract>
      <url hash="ec5d70f2">2026.vardial-1.17</url>
      <bibkey>tsoukala-etal-2026-extending</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="18">
      <title>How Should We Model the Probability of a Language?</title>
      <author><first>Rasul</first><last>Dent</last></author>
      <author><first>Pedro</first><last>Ortiz Suarez</last></author>
      <author><first>Thibault</first><last>Clérice</last></author>
      <author><first>Benoît</first><last>Sagot</last></author>
      <pages>223-233</pages>
      <abstract>Of the over 7,000 languages spoken in the world, commercial language identification (LID) systems only reliably identify a few hundred in written form. Research-grade systems extend this coverage under certain circumstances, but for most languages coverage remains patchy or nonexistent. This position paper argues that this situation is largely self-imposed. In particular, it arises from a persistent framing of LID as decontextualized text classification, which obscures the central role of prior probability estimation and is reinforced by institutional incentives that favor global, fixed-prior models. We argue that improving coverage for tail languages requires rethinking LID as a routing problem and developing principled ways to incorporate environmental cues that make languages locally plausible.</abstract>
      <url hash="c716bb16">2026.vardial-1.18</url>
      <bibkey>dent-etal-2026-model</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="19">
      <title>Bridging Dialectal Variation: A Phonetic Transcription Tool for <fixed-case>T</fixed-case>amil</title>
      <author><first>Ahrane</first><last>Mahaganapathy</last></author>
      <author><first>Sumirtha</first><last>Karunakaran</last></author>
      <author><first>Kavitha</first><last>Navakulan</last></author>
      <author><first>Kengatharaiyer</first><last>Sarveswaran</last></author>
      <pages>234-241</pages>
      <abstract>Phonetic transcription is vital for speech processing and linguistic documentation, particularly in languages like Tamil with complex phonology and dialectal variation. Challenges such as consonant gemination, retroflexion, vowel length, and one-to-many grapheme-phoneme mappings are compounded by limited data on Sri Lankan Tamil dialects. We present a dialect-aware, rule-based transcription tool for Tamil that supports Indian and Jaffna Tamil, with extensions underway for other dialects. Using a two-stage pipeline: Tamil script to Latin, then to IPA with context-sensitive rules, the tool handles dialect shifts. A real-time interface enables dialect selection. Evaluated on a 7,830-word corpus, it achieves 94.54% accuracy for Jaffna Tamil and is higher than other tools like eSpeak NG, advancing linguistic preservation and accessible speech technology for Tamil communities.</abstract>
      <url hash="a5fcfe87">2026.vardial-1.19</url>
      <bibkey>mahaganapathy-etal-2026-bridging</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="20">
      <title>Regional Variation in the Performance of <fixed-case>ASR</fixed-case> Models on <fixed-case>C</fixed-case>roatian and <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>erbian</title>
      <author><first>Tanja</first><last>Samardžić</last></author>
      <author><first>Peter</first><last>Rupnik</last></author>
      <author><first>Nikola</first><last>Ljubešić</last></author>
      <pages>242-249</pages>
      <abstract>Regional variation was a limiting factor for automatic speech recognition (ASR) before large language models. With the new technology, speech processing becomes more general, which opens the question of how to use data in similar languages such as Croatian and Serbian. In this paper, we analyse model performance in the currently available train-test scenarios with the goal of better understanding the mutual interference of these two languages. Our findings suggest that better performing models are not very sensitive to the regional variation. Training from scratch in one of the languages can give good results on both of them, while fine-tuning large pre-trained multilingual models on smaller data sets does not give the expected results.</abstract>
      <url hash="0f2908c4">2026.vardial-1.20</url>
      <bibkey>samardzic-etal-2026-regional</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="21">
      <title>Syllable Structures Across <fixed-case>A</fixed-case>rabic Varieties</title>
      <author><first>Abdelrahim</first><last>Qaddoumi</last></author>
      <author><first>Jordan</first><last>Kodner</last></author>
      <author><first>Salam</first><last>Khalifa</last></author>
      <author><first>Ellen</first><last>Broselow</last></author>
      <author><first>Owen</first><last>Rambow</last></author>
      <pages>250-260</pages>
      <abstract>This study compares the syllable structures of nine Arabic varieties from Wiktionary, using a computational syllabifier. It further investigates methods for learning syllable boundaries in unsyllabified words transcribed in the International Phonetic Alphabet (IPA). The syllabification algorithm is evaluated under three conditions: (i) Default, employing fixed rules; (ii) Joint, learning onsets and codas across all varieties collectively; and (iii) Per-variety, learning onsets and codas specific to each variety. Results indicate that the default configuration yields the highest accuracy, ranging from 97.05% to 100%. The per-variety approach achieves 90.64% to 100% accuracy, while the joint approach ranges from 84.63% to 94.74%. A cross-variety analysis using Jensen-Shannon divergence reveals three principal groupings: Egyptian, Hejazi, and Modern Standard Arabic are closely related; Levantine and Gulf varieties constitute a second cluster; and Juba Arabic, Maltese, and Moroccan emerge as outliers. A cleaned dataset encompassing all nine varieties is also provided.</abstract>
      <url hash="631ba9e0">2026.vardial-1.21</url>
      <bibkey>qaddoumi-etal-2026-syllable</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="22">
      <title>Curriculum Learning and Pseudo-Labeling Improve the Generalization of Multi-Label <fixed-case>A</fixed-case>rabic Dialect Identification Models</title>
      <author><first>Ali</first><last>Mekky</last></author>
      <author><first>Mohamed</first><last>El Zeftawy</last></author>
      <author><first>Lara</first><last>Hassan</last></author>
      <author><first>Amr</first><last>Keleg</last></author>
      <author><first>Preslav</first><last>Nakov</last></author>
      <pages>261-274</pages>
      <abstract>Being modeled as a single-label classification task for a long time, recent work has argued that Arabic Dialect Identification (ADI) should be framed as a multi-label classification task. However, ADI remains constrained by the availability of single-label datasets, with no large-scale multi-label resources available for training. By analyzing models trained on single-label ADI data, we show that the main difficulty in repurposing such datasets for Multi-Label Arabic Dialect Identification (MLADI) lies in the selection of negative samples, as many sentences treated as negative could be acceptable in multiple dialects. To address these issues, we construct a multi-label dataset by generating automatic multi-label annotations using GPT-4o and binary dialect acceptability classifiers, with aggregation guided by the Arabic Level of Dialectness (ALDi). Afterward, we train a BERT-based multi-label classifier using curriculum learning strategies aligned with dialectal complexity and label cardinality. On the MLADI leaderboard, our best-performing LahjatBERT model achieves a macro F1 of 0.69, compared to 0.55 for the strongest previously reported system.</abstract>
      <url hash="c6f3d1a4">2026.vardial-1.22</url>
      <bibkey>mekky-etal-2026-curriculum</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="23">
      <title><fixed-case>O</fixed-case>pen<fixed-case>LID</fixed-case>-v3: Improving the Precision of Closely Related Language Identification – An Experience Report</title>
      <author><first>Mariia</first><last>Fedorova</last></author>
      <author><first>Nikolay</first><last>Arefyev</last></author>
      <author><first>Maja</first><last>Buljan</last></author>
      <author><first>Jindřich</first><last>Helcl</last></author>
      <author><first>Stephan</first><last>Oepen</last></author>
      <author><first>Egil</first><last>Rønningstad</last></author>
      <author><first>Yves</first><last>Scherrer</last></author>
      <pages>275-292</pages>
      <abstract>Language identification (LID) is an essential step in building high-quality multilingual datasets from web data. Existing LID tools (such as OpenLID or GlotLID) often struggle to identify closely related languages and to distinguish valid natural language from noise, which contaminates language-specific subsets, especially for low-resource languages. In this work we extend the OpenLID classifier by adding more training data, merging problematic language variant clusters, and introducing a special label for marking noise. We call this extended system OpenLID-v3 and evaluate it against GlotLID on multiple benchmarks. During the development we focus on three groups of closely related languages (Bosnian, Croatian, and Serbian; Romance varieties of Northern Italy and Southern France; and Scandinavian languages) and contribute new evaluation datasets where existing ones are inadequate. We find that ensemble approaches improve precision but also substantially reduce coverage for low-resource languages.</abstract>
      <url hash="25cde462">2026.vardial-1.23</url>
      <bibkey>fedorova-etal-2026-openlid</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="24">
      <title>Improving Dialect Robustness in Large Language Models via <fixed-case>L</fixed-case>o<fixed-case>RA</fixed-case> and Mixture-of-Experts</title>
      <author><first>Sanjh</first><last>Maheshwari</last></author>
      <author><first>Aniket Singh</first><last>Rajpoot</last></author>
      <author><first>Oana</first><last>Cocarascu</last></author>
      <author><first>Mamta</first><last>.</last></author>
      <pages>293-303</pages>
      <abstract>Despite the success of large language models (LLMs) in a wide range of applications, it has been shown that their performance varies across English dialects. Differences among English dialects are reflected in vocabulary, syntax, and writing style, and can adversely affect model performance. Several studies evaluate the dialect robustness of LLMs, yet research on enhancing their robustness to dialectal variation remains limited. In this paper, we propose two parameter-efficient frameworks for improving dialectal robustness in LLMs: DialectFusion where we train separate LoRA layers for each dialect and apply different LoRA merging methods, and DialectMoE which is built on top of Mixture of Experts LoRA and introduces multiple LoRA-based experts to the feed-forward layer to internally model the dialectal dependencies. Our comprehensive analysis on five open-source LLMs for sentiment and sarcasm tasks in zero- and few-shot settings shows that our proposed approaches enhance the dialect robustness of LLMs and outperforms instruct and LoRA fine-tuning based approaches.</abstract>
      <url hash="421c7eb3">2026.vardial-1.24</url>
      <bibkey>maheshwari-etal-2026-improving</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="25">
      <title>Evaluation Framework for Transfer Learning between Closely Related Lects: A Case Study of Lemko</title>
      <author><first>Ilia</first><last>Afanasev</last></author>
      <pages>304-316</pages>
      <abstract>The creation of a robust evaluation methodology is one of the pivotal issues for transfer learning between closely related lects. The current study proposes to resolve this issue by concisely implementing a group of evaluation methods that enable a more systematic qualitative analysis of errata (for instance, string similarity measures to assess lemmatisation more effectively). The paper introduces a robustness score, a metric that aims to assess the stabilityof model performance across different datasets. The case study is a morphosyntactic tagging of a small historical (beginning of the twentieth century) corpus of Lemko (Slavic clade, Transcarpathian area). It presents a diversity of cross-dependent tasks, made rather complex by the rich Lemko morphology, highly influenced by areal convergence processes. The tagger is a pre-trained Stanza. The study uses modern standard Ukrainian as the source language, as it is the closest to the Lemko high-resource lect. The analysis reveals that linguistically-aware metrics improve the speed and accuracy of analysis of the errata, especially those caused by the differences between source and target lects. The key data contribution is the open- source dataset of Lemko, obtained during the tagging tasks. Future research directions include a larger-scale test that applies more models to a more extensive material.</abstract>
      <url hash="ce8f3c10">2026.vardial-1.25</url>
      <bibkey>afanasev-2026-evaluation</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="26">
      <title>Do Large Language Models Adapt to Language Variation across Socioeconomic Status?</title>
      <author><first>Elisa</first><last>Bassignana</last></author>
      <author><first>Mike</first><last>Zhang</last></author>
      <author><first>Dirk</first><last>Hovy</last></author>
      <author><first>Amanda</first><last>Cercas Curry</last></author>
      <pages>317-338</pages>
      <abstract>Humans adjust their linguistic style to the audience they are addressing. However, the extent to which LLMs adapt to different social contexts is largely unknown. As these models increasingly mediate human-to-human communication, their failure to adapt to diverse styles can perpetuate stereotypes and marginalize communities whose linguistic norms are less closely mirrored by the models, thereby reinforcing social stratification. We study the extent to which LLMs integrate into social media communication across different socioeconomic status (SES) communities. We collect a novel dataset from Reddit and YouTube, stratified by SES. We prompt four LLMs with incomplete text from that corpus and compare the LLM-generated completions to the originals along 94 sociolinguistic metrics, including syntactic, rhetorical, and lexical features. LLMs modulate their style with respect to SES to only a minor extent, often resulting in approximation or caricature, and tend to emulate the style of upper SES more effectively. Our findings (1) show how LLMs risk amplifying linguistic hierarchies and (2) call into question their validity for agent-based social simulation, survey experiments, and any research relying on language style as a social signal.</abstract>
      <url hash="7f5912d7">2026.vardial-1.26</url>
      <bibkey>bassignana-etal-2026-large</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="27">
      <title>Aladdin-<fixed-case>FTI</fixed-case> @ <fixed-case>AMIYA</fixed-case> Three Wishes for <fixed-case>A</fixed-case>rabic <fixed-case>NLP</fixed-case>: Fidelity, Diglossia, and Multidialectal Generation</title>
      <author><first>Jonathan</first><last>Mutal</last></author>
      <author><first>Perla</first><last>Al Almaoui</last></author>
      <author><first>Simon</first><last>Hengchen</last></author>
      <author><first>Pierrette</first><last>Bouillon</last></author>
      <pages>339-351</pages>
      <abstract>Arabic dialects have long been under-represented in Natural Language Processing (NLP) research due to their non-standardization and high variability, which pose challenges for computational modeling. Recent advances in the field, such as Large Language Models (LLMs), offer promising avenues to address this gap by enabling Arabic to be modeled as a pluricentric language rather than a monolithic system. This paper presents Aladdin-FTI, our submission to the AMIYA shared task. The proposed system is designed to both generate and translate dialectal Arabic (DA). Specifically, the model supports text generation in Moroccan, Egyptian, Palestinian, Syrian, and Saudi dialects, as well as bidirectional translation between these dialects, Modern Standard Arabic (MSA), and English. The code and trained model will be released upon paper acceptance.</abstract>
      <url hash="1da291da">2026.vardial-1.27</url>
      <bibkey>mutal-etal-2026-aladdin</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="28">
      <title>Maastricht University at <fixed-case>AMIYA</fixed-case>: Adapting <fixed-case>LLM</fixed-case>s for Dialectal <fixed-case>A</fixed-case>rabic using Fine-tuning and <fixed-case>MBR</fixed-case> Decoding</title>
      <author><first>Abdulhai</first><last>Alali</last></author>
      <author><first>Abderrahmane</first><last>Issam</last></author>
      <pages>352-358</pages>
      <abstract>Large Language Models (LLMs) are becoming increasingly multilingual, supporting hundreds of languages especially high resource ones. Unfortunately, Dialect variations are still underrepresented due to limited data and linguistic variation. In this work, we adapt a pre-trained LLM to improve dialectal performance. Specifically, we use Low Rank Adaptation (LoRA) fine-tuning on monolingual and English–Dialect parallel data, adapter merging and dialect-aware MBR decoding to improve dialectal fidelity generation and translation. Experiments on Syrian, Moroccan, and Saudi Arabic show that merging and MBR improve dialectal fidelity while preserving semantic accuracy. This combination provides a compact and effective framework for robust dialectal Arabic generation.</abstract>
      <url hash="973fcdf2">2026.vardial-1.28</url>
      <bibkey>alali-issam-2026-maastricht</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="29">
      <title><fixed-case>SDNLP</fixed-case> at <fixed-case>AMIYA</fixed-case> 2026: <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>yrian <fixed-case>A</fixed-case>rabic Dialect Modeling with <fixed-case>L</fixed-case>o<fixed-case>RA</fixed-case></title>
      <author><first>Hasan</first><last>Alkhder</last></author>
      <author><first>Mohammad</first><last>Abboush</last></author>
      <pages>359-364</pages>
      <abstract>Dialectal Arabic continues to represent a persistent challenge for contemporary large language models, which are predominantly trained and optimized for Modern Standard Arabic (MSA) and therefore exhibit limited capability when processing colloquial varieties. In this study, a dedicated system developed for participation in the AMIYA shared task focusing on Syrian Arabic is presented. The proposed solution is based on the integration of parameter-efficient fine-tuning through Low-Rank Adaptation (LoRA) with prompt-guided inference, aiming to enhance dialectal adequacy and linguistic naturalness. Rather than emphasizing strict factual precision, the system is deliberately designed to prioritize fluent and authentic Syrian Arabic generation, in accordance with the evaluation principles adopted by the AL-QASIDA benchmark. This design choice reflects a focus on human-perceived language quality and dialectal fidelity, which are central to effective dialect-aware language modeling.</abstract>
      <url hash="a2ff0807">2026.vardial-1.29</url>
      <bibkey>alkhder-abboush-2026-sdnlp</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="30">
      <title><fixed-case>NUS</fixed-case>-<fixed-case>IDS</fixed-case> at <fixed-case>AMIYA</fixed-case>/<fixed-case>V</fixed-case>ar<fixed-case>D</fixed-case>ial 2026: Improving <fixed-case>A</fixed-case>rabic Dialectness in <fixed-case>LLM</fixed-case>s with Reinforcement Learning</title>
      <author><first>Sujatha Das</first><last>Gollapalli</last></author>
      <author><first>Mouad</first><last>Hakam</last></author>
      <author><first>Mingzhe</first><last>Du</last></author>
      <author><first>See-Kiong</first><last>Ng</last></author>
      <pages>365-372</pages>
      <abstract>In this paper, we describe models developed by our team, NUS-IDS, for the Closed data track at the Arabic Modeling In Your Accent (AMIYA) shared task at VarDial 2026. The core idea behind our solution involves data augmentation enabled by a dialect classifier trained on AMIYA data. We effectively combine various translation, summarization, and question answering prompts with AMIYA training data to form dialectal prompts for use with state-of-the-art LLMs. Next, dialect predictions from our classifier on outputs from these LLMs are used to compile preference data for Reinforcement Learning (RL). We report model performance on dialectal Arabic from Egypt, Morocco, Palestine, Saudi Arabia and Syria using FLORES+, a multilingual machine translation dataset. Our experiments illustrate that though our RL models show significant performance gains on dialectness scores, they under perform on translation metrics such as chrF++ compared to base LLMs.</abstract>
      <url hash="1aee2dd2">2026.vardial-1.30</url>
      <bibkey>gollapalli-etal-2026-nus</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="31">
      <title><fixed-case>MBZUAI</fixed-case> at <fixed-case>AMIYA</fixed-case> Shared Task 2026: Adapting Open-Source <fixed-case>LLM</fixed-case>s for Dialectal <fixed-case>A</fixed-case>rabic</title>
      <author><first>Rana</first><last>Gaber</last></author>
      <author><first>Yara</first><last>Allam</last></author>
      <author><first>Serag</first><last>Amin</last></author>
      <author><first>Ranwa</first><last>Aly</last></author>
      <author><first>Bashar</first><last>Alhafni</last></author>
      <pages>373-384</pages>
      <abstract>This paper presents our contribution to the closed data track of the AMIYA Shared Task on Dialectal Arabic text generation. In this track, we train fully open-source Large Language Models (LLMs) on five Arabic dialects: Egyptian, Moroccan, Palestinian, Saudi, and Syrian, using the provided training datasets. We experiment with different base and instruct models using several pretraining and instruction tuning approaches. In total, five models were submitted, with three variants per dialect. Our best-performing models for the five dialects are ALLaM for Egyptian, LLaMa for Moroccan, and Palestinian, and Aya for Saudi and Syrian.</abstract>
      <url hash="0a710b67">2026.vardial-1.31</url>
      <bibkey>gaber-etal-2026-mbzuai</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="32">
      <title>A Closed-Track System for Palestinian <fixed-case>A</fixed-case>rabic in the <fixed-case>AMIYA</fixed-case> Shared Task</title>
      <author><first>Khaleel</first><last>Hamad</last></author>
      <author><first>Ahmad</first><last>Al-Najjar</last></author>
      <pages>385-392</pages>
      <abstract>We describe a closed track system for mod- eling Palestinian Arabic that is developed for the AMIYA shared task using a parameter effi- cient fine-tuning strategy. A 1.5B instruction- tuned language model was adapted with LoRA (Hu et al., 2021), updating only .28% of the model parameters, and trained on an aggre- gated set of conversations between Palestini- ans and resources covering both translation and generation. Model selection was guided by a comparative benchmark that prioritized performance efficiency and its tradeoffs. At the same time the paper focuses on targeting error analysis as well as structured instruction following. These findings illustrate both the viability and shed light on the current limita- tions of efficient adaptation methods for low- resource Arabic dialects.</abstract>
      <url hash="8c6f1591">2026.vardial-1.32</url>
      <bibkey>hamad-al-najjar-2026-closed</bibkey>
    </paper>
  </volume>
</collection>
