<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<collection id="2026.retroeval">
  <volume id="main" type="proceedings" ingest-date="2026-06-08">
    <meta>
      <booktitle>Proceedings of the 1st Symposium on Natural Language Generation Evaluations</booktitle>
      <editor><first>Saad</first><last>Mahamood</last></editor>
      <editor><first>David M.</first><last>Howcroft</last></editor>
      <editor><first>Kees</first><last>van Deemter</last></editor>
      <editor><first>Simone</first><last>Balloccu</last></editor>
      <editor><first>Adarsa</first><last>Sivaprasad</last></editor>
      <editor><first>Barkavi</first><last>Sundararajan</last></editor>
      <editor><first>Alberto</first><last>Bugarín Diz</last></editor>
      <editor><first>Jose María</first><last>Alonso-Moral</last></editor>
      <publisher>Association for Computational Linguistics</publisher>
      <address>Aberdeen, United Kingdom</address>
      <isbn>979-8-89176-436-1</isbn>
      <month>June</month>
      <year>2026</year>
      <url hash="05235ff4">2026.retroeval-main</url>
      <sig>siggen</sig>
      <venue>retroeval</venue>
    </meta>
    <frontmatter>
      <url hash="b0549cf4">2026.retroeval-main.0</url>
      <bibkey>retroeval-2026-main</bibkey>
    </frontmatter>
    <paper id="1">
      <title>Decomposition Does Not Help: Evidence from Semantic Clustering in <fixed-case>LLM</fixed-case>-based Causal Graph Discovery</title>
      <author><first>Nikolay</first><last>Babakov</last></author>
      <author><first>Alberto</first><last>Bugarín-Diz</last></author>
      <pages>1-7</pages>
      <abstract>Recent advances in large language models (LLMs) have enabled their application to non-traditional tasks such as causal graph construction, a key component of reasoning frameworks, including Bayesian Networks. The most effective existing approaches rely on direct prompting, where an LLM generates a complete graph from a full set of variables in a single step. However, the performance of such methods degrades as the number of graph nodes increases. To address this limitation, we explore a divide-and-conquer alternative based on semantic clustering. Node representations are first embedded and clustered, after which subgraphs are constructed independently for each cluster using LLM prompting. The resulting subgraphs are then merged pairwise into a global graph. Contrary to our expectations, this approach leads to a substantial degradation in performance compared to direct prompting baselines, as measured by Structural Hamming Distance (SHD). We attribute this to the misalignment between semantic similarity and causal structure, as well as error propagation during subgraph merging. We report these negative results to highlight the limitations of decomposition strategies in LLM-based causal graphs construction.</abstract>
      <url hash="3d63442b">2026.retroeval-main.1</url>
      <bibkey>babakov-bugarin-diz-2026-decomposition</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="2">
      <title><fixed-case>NLG</fixed-case> Evaluation: Past, Present, Future</title>
      <author><first>Ehud</first><last>Reiter</last></author>
      <pages>8-15</pages>
      <abstract>Natural Language Generation (NLG) evaluation has changed dramatically since 1990, and will continue to evolve in the future. In 1990, when NLG had close ties to linguistics, there was very little formal experimental evaluation in the modern sense. In 2026, when NLG is closely linked to machine learning, experimental evaluation is expected and indeed fundamental to research. Many evaluation techniques were developed over this period, including most recently LLM-as-Judge. I expect NLG evaluation will continue to evolve in the future. In particular, impact, qualitative, and safety evaluation will become more important as large numbers of people routinely use NLG technology.</abstract>
      <url hash="b7be4d72">2026.retroeval-main.2</url>
      <bibkey>reiter-2026-nlg</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="3">
      <title>Evaluation and Assessment as Complementary Frameworks</title>
      <author><first>Elie</first><last>Antoine</last></author>
      <pages>16-23</pages>
      <abstract>Language model capabilities have advanced faster than the methods used to evaluate them, particularly since the move from task-specific systems to general-purpose models which are deployed across an ever-widening range of tasks. When models were built for a single task, evaluation sat in a tight relationship between the task, the data, and the model. General-purpose models have weakened this relationship, and the evaluation practices that were built around it have not adjusted. This paper argues that addressing this gap requires treating evaluation, understood as quantitative performance measurement, and assessment, understood as the analysis of mechanisms and real-world behavior, as complementary rather than interchangeable. This distinction matters because evaluation is now often asked to stand alone in settings where a benchmark score cannot tell us what a model is doing, or how its behavior will hold up outside the benchmark.</abstract>
      <url hash="79ad8c99">2026.retroeval-main.3</url>
      <bibkey>antoine-2026-evaluation</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="4">
      <title>The <fixed-case>A</fixed-case>rabic <fixed-case>B</fixed-case>ible as an Evaluation Tool: The Case Study of the Khalīlī <fixed-case>A</fixed-case>rabic Dialect</title>
      <author><first>Jakub</first><last>Zbrzeżny</last></author>
      <author><first>Ehud</first><last>Reiter</last></author>
      <author><first>Wei</first><last>Zhao</last></author>
      <pages>24-32</pages>
      <abstract>The paper presents a fully documented case study of how high-quality data combined with evaluators’ expertise can be utilised for conducting basic NLP experiments in the realm of low-resource languages such as local varieties of Colloquial Arabic, and how the Arabic Bible, hitherto underutilised in NLP, can serve as an evaluation tool. Our experiments on one of the rural Palestinian Arabic dialects of al-Khalīl / Hebron illustrate two points. On the one hand, popular models are clearly limited in their ability to produce outputs of a high level of dialectal specificity (here: rural area surrounding a major urban centre). On the other hand, they are capable to generate accurate translations from such dialects into Modern Standard Arabic. Thus, the models appear better at understanding dialects than at producing dialects.</abstract>
      <url hash="2642392b">2026.retroeval-main.4</url>
      <bibkey>zbrze-z-ny-etal-2026-arabic</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="5">
      <title><fixed-case>RAG</fixed-case> as a collapsed <fixed-case>NLG</fixed-case> pipeline</title>
      <author><first>Adarsa</first><last>Sivaprasad</last></author>
      <author><first>Barkavi</first><last>Sundararajan</last></author>
      <author><first>David M.</first><last>Howcroft</last></author>
      <pages>33-38</pages>
      <abstract>The NLG pipeline of Reiter and Dale has long served as the foundational framework for data-to-text system design and evaluation. However its relationship to modern generative architec- tures remains underexplored. In this conceptual analysis, we argue that Retrieval-Augmented Generation (RAG) constitutes a collapsed and partially reconstructed instantiation of the classical NLG pipeline, using it to identify failure modes of RAG around context faithfulness and retrieval non-determinism.</abstract>
      <url hash="27a99e98">2026.retroeval-main.5</url>
      <bibkey>sivaprasad-etal-2026-rag</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="6">
      <title>A Comparative Evaluation of End-to-End and Pipeline Approaches for Summarisation</title>
      <author><first>Fahime</first><last>Same</last></author>
      <author><first>Saad</first><last>Mahamood</last></author>
      <author><first>Srinivas Ramesh</first><last>Kamath</last></author>
      <pages>39-52</pages>
      <abstract>We describe and evaluate two different architectures for creating book highlights from unstructured data. Given the prevalence of large language models, we examine whether a pipeline-based approach with intermediate steps for text generation is still necessary and whether it continues to offer any benefits over an end-to-end approach. Our comparative evaluations using LLM-as-a-judge across multiple models with different parameter sizes and generation scenarios show that highlights generated by the end-to-end approach are preferred. However, there is a slight but consistent increase in faithfulness for the pipeline-generated highlights when generating at a thematic level. Additionally, our analysis across multiple models shows that while larger models are more faithful, the degree of faithfulness increases when they are used with a pipeline architecture. The findings from our work indicate that whilst there is comparability between the two approaches, the greater faithfulness, controllability, and observability of pipeline-based approaches offer tangible benefits in applied settings.</abstract>
      <url hash="27b7ae19">2026.retroeval-main.6</url>
      <bibkey>same-etal-2026-comparative</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="7">
      <title>Solving the Task but Not the Problem: A Customer Support Case Study on Why Extrinsic Evaluation Matters</title>
      <author><first>Daniel</first><last>Braun</last></author>
      <pages>53-62</pages>
      <abstract>Natural Language Processing has long been used in customer support to automate and augment human agents. Despite its long-standing use and clear practical relevance, most scientific evaluations rely on intrinsic evaluations and metrics such as accuracy or F1-score. In this paper, we argue that such evaluations often fail to reflect real-world system impact. We present a case study of an NLP system for email-based customer support evaluated both intrinsically and extrinsically via a before-and-after study in deployment. While the system achieves strong intrinsic performance, we observe no measurable improvement in key operational metrics such as average handle time per email. These results highlight a mismatch between benchmark performance and real-world effectiveness, supporting calls for more systematic extrinsic evaluation of NLP systems.</abstract>
      <url hash="12663dc0">2026.retroeval-main.7</url>
      <bibkey>braun-2026-solving</bibkey>
    </paper>
    <paper id="8">
      <title>Never Truly Out of Fashion: A Retrospective Look at Evaluation in <fixed-case>NLG</fixed-case></title>
      <author><first>Patrícia</first><last>Schmidtová</last></author>
      <author><first>Saad</first><last>Mahamood</last></author>
      <author><first>Ondřej</first><last>Dušek</last></author>
      <pages>63-72</pages>
      <abstract>Human evaluation (HE) remains the gold standard for assessing natural language generation (NLG) systems, yet automatic metrics are cheaper and faster, creating mounting pressure to skip it. We ask how evaluation practices have changed as NLG research scales. We analyse 24,291 papers from the ACL Anthology (1952–2025) through regular-expression-powered keyword analysis. Before 1990, the majority of NLG papers reported no evaluation at all; today, evaluation is near-universal and HE has held broadly stable over the past decade – it has not collapsed. However, large language model (LLM) judges (referred to as LLM-as-a-judge) have emerged rapidly since 2023, and while they currently serve predominantly as a complement rather than a full substitute for human evaluation, a substantial share of papers already use LLM judges without any human validation. Faithfulness has become the fastest-rising evaluation criterion since 2020, coming back into fashion after almost 15 years of decline, tracking the prominence of hallucination research, while criteria such as grammaticality and fluency are receding, suggesting these qualities may increasingly be taken for granted as model outputs improve. Our findings provide a longitudinal baseline for tracking where the field stands.</abstract>
      <url hash="be927d30">2026.retroeval-main.8</url>
      <bibkey>schmidtova-etal-2026-never</bibkey>
    </paper>
  </volume>
</collection>
