<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<collection id="2026.silkroadnlp">
  <volume id="1" type="proceedings" ingest-date="2026-03-17">
    <meta>
      <booktitle>The Proceedings of the First Workshop on <fixed-case>NLP</fixed-case> and <fixed-case>LLM</fixed-case>s for the <fixed-case>I</fixed-case>ranian Language Family</booktitle>
      <editor><first>Rayyan</first><last>Merchant</last></editor>
      <editor><first>Karine</first><last>Megerdoomian</last></editor>
      <publisher>Association for Computational Linguistics</publisher>
      <address>Rabat, Morocco</address>
      <isbn>979-8-89176-371-5</isbn>
      <month>March</month>
      <year>2026</year>
      <url hash="198f3979">2026.silkroadnlp-1</url>
      <venue>silkroadnlp</venue>
      <venue>ws</venue>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2026.silkroadnlp-1</doi>
    </meta>
    <frontmatter>
      <url hash="4bc6a269">2026.silkroadnlp-1.0</url>
      <bibkey>silkroadnlp-2026-1</bibkey>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2026.silkroadnlp-1.0</doi>
    </frontmatter>
    <paper id="1">
      <title>Unmasking the Factual-Conceptual Gap in <fixed-case>P</fixed-case>ersian Language Models</title>
      <author><first>Alireza</first><last>Sakhaeirad</last><affiliation>EPFL</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Ali</first><last>Ma'manpoosh</last><affiliation>University of Isfahan</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Arshia</first><last>Hemmat</last><affiliation>University of Oxford</affiliation></author>
      <pages>1-12</pages>
      <abstract>While emerging Persian NLP benchmarks have expanded into pragmatics and politeness, they rarely distinguish between memorized cultural facts and the ability to reason about implicit social norms. We introduce DIVANBENCH, a diagnostic benchmark focused on superstitions and customs, arbitrary, context-dependent rules that resist simple logical deduction. Through 315 questions across three task types (factual retrieval, paired scenario verification, and situational reasoning), we evaluate seven Persian LLMs and reveal three critical failures: most models exhibit severe acquiescence bias, correctly identifying appropriate behaviors but failing to reject clear violations; continuous Persian pretraining amplifies this bias rather than improving reasoning, often degrading the model’s ability to discern contradictions; and all models show a 21% performance gap between retrieving factual knowledge and applying it in scenarios. These findings demonstrate that cultural competence requires more than scaling monolingual data, as current models learn to mimic cultural patterns without internalizing the underlying schemas.</abstract>
      <url hash="c9e7710e">2026.silkroadnlp-1.1</url>
      <bibkey>sakhaeirad-etal-2026-unmasking</bibkey>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2026.silkroadnlp-1.1</doi>
    </paper>
    <paper id="2">
      <title>Benchmarking Offensive Language Detection in <fixed-case>P</fixed-case>ersian and <fixed-case>P</fixed-case>ashto</title>
      <author><first>Zahra</first><last>Bokaei</last><affiliation>School of Informatics, University of Edinburgh</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Bonnie</first><last>Webber</last><affiliation>School of Informatics, University of Edinburgh</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Walid</first><last>Magdy</last><affiliation>School of Informatics, University of Edinburgh</affiliation></author>
      <pages>13-23</pages>
      <abstract>Offensive language detection and target identification are essential for maintaining respectful online environments. While these tasks have been widely studied for English, comparatively less attention has been given to other language, including Persian and Pashto, and the effectiveness of recent large language models for these languages remains underexplored. To address this gap, we created a comprehensive benchmark of diverse modeling approaches in Persian and Pashto. Our evaluation covers zeroshot, fine-tuned, and cross-lingual transfer settings, analyzing when detection succeeds or fails across different model approaches. This study provides one of the first systematic analyses of offensive language detection and crosslingual transfer between these languages.</abstract>
      <url hash="9736559b">2026.silkroadnlp-1.2</url>
      <bibkey>bokaei-etal-2026-benchmarking</bibkey>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2026.silkroadnlp-1.2</doi>
    </paper>
    <paper id="3">
      <title>Do Large Language Models Understand Double Mismatches? Evidence from <fixed-case>F</fixed-case>arsi</title>
      <author><first>Maryam</first><last>Mohammadi</last><affiliation>Bielefeld University</affiliation></author>
      <pages>24-28</pages>
      <abstract>Large language models (LLMs) are increasingly used for communication in many languages, therefore, understanding their limitations with respect to culture-specific pragmatics is important. While LLMs perform well on statistically frequent structures, their shortcomings are most evident in rare pragmatic phenomena. This study investigates whether LLMs can generate a (rare) complex honorific mismatch in Farsi. The pattern arises at two levels:(i) a plural pronoun disagrees with a singular referent for the sake of honorification, and (ii) the related components violate the Polite Plural Generalization due to intimacy implication. This double mismatch pattern is attested in everyday speech, though it is statistically sparse. We tested GPT-4 across multiple scenarios. The results reveal that the model successfully employs the first mismatch to indicate honorific, but fails to adopt the second mismatch that simultaneously conveys intimacy. The model thus deviates from humanlike behavior at the syntax–pragmatics interface. These findings suggest that, while machine models demonstrate partial success in generating honorifics, they rely primarily on statistical patterns and lack the deeper pragmatic understanding necessary for contextual competence.</abstract>
      <url hash="9318f6e3">2026.silkroadnlp-1.3</url>
      <bibkey>mohammadi-2026-large</bibkey>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2026.silkroadnlp-1.3</doi>
    </paper>
    <paper id="4">
      <title><fixed-case>T</fixed-case>aj<fixed-case>P</fixed-case>ers<fixed-case>L</fixed-case>exon: A <fixed-case>T</fixed-case>ajik–<fixed-case>P</fixed-case>ersian Lexical Resource and Hybrid Model for Cross-Script Low-Resource <fixed-case>NLP</fixed-case></title>
      <author><first>Mullosharaf Kurbonovich</first><last>Arabov</last><affiliation>Kazan (Volga Region) Federal University</affiliation></author>
      <pages>29-37</pages>
      <abstract>This work introduces TajPersLexon, a curated Tajik–Persian parallel lexical resource of 40,112 word and short-phrase pairs for cross-script lexical retrieval, transliteration, and alignment in low-resource settings. We conduct a comprehensive CPU-only benchmark comparing three methodological families:(i) a lightweight hybrid pipeline, (ii) neural sequence-to-sequence models, and (iii) retrieval methods. Our evaluation establishes that the task is essentially solvable, with neural and retrieval baselines achieving 98-99% top-1 accuracy. Crucially, we demonstrate that while large multilingual sentence transformers fail on this exact lexical matching, our interpretable hybrid model offers a favorable accuracy-efficiency trade-off for practical applications, achieving 96.4% accuracy in an OCR post-correction task. All experiments use fixed random seeds for full reproducibility. The dataset, code, and models will be publicly released.</abstract>
      <url hash="b328a3e9">2026.silkroadnlp-1.4</url>
      <bibkey>arabov-2026-tajperslexon</bibkey>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2026.silkroadnlp-1.4</doi>
    </paper>
    <paper id="5">
      <title>A Computational Approach to Language Contact – A Case Study of <fixed-case>P</fixed-case>ersian</title>
      <author><first>Ali</first><last>Basirat</last><affiliation>Center for Langauge Technology (CST), University of Copenhagen</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Danial</first><last>Namazifard</last><affiliation>University of Tehran</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Navid Baradaran</first><last>Hemmati</last><affiliation>Certified Translation Agency No. 1141, Mashhad, Iran</affiliation></author>
      <pages>38-49</pages>
      <abstract>We investigate structural traces of language contact in the intermediate representations of a monolingual language model. Focusing on Persian (Farsi) as a historically contact-rich language, we probe the representations of a Persian-trained model when exposed to languages with varying degrees and types of contact with Persian. Our methodology quantifies the amount of linguistic information encoded in intermediate representations and assesses how this information is distributed across model components for different morphosyntactic features. The results show that universal syntactic information is largely insensitive to historical contact, whereas morphological features such as CASE and GENDER are strongly shaped by language-specific structure, suggesting that contact effects in monolingual language models are selective and structurally constrained.</abstract>
      <url hash="64157eb6">2026.silkroadnlp-1.5</url>
      <bibkey>basirat-etal-2026-computational</bibkey>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2026.silkroadnlp-1.5</doi>
    </paper>
    <paper id="6">
      <title>Online Polarization Detection in <fixed-case>P</fixed-case>ersian (<fixed-case>F</fixed-case>arsi) Social Media</title>
      <author><first>Saeedeh</first><last>Davoudi</last><affiliation>Information Retrieval Lab, Computer Science Department, Georgetown University</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Nazli</first><last>Goharian</last><affiliation>Information Retrieval Lab, Computer Science Department, Georgetown University</affiliation></author>
      <pages>50-59</pages>
      <abstract>Polarization detection in low-resource and mid-resource languages remains a significant challenge for social understanding. This paper presents the first comprehensive benchmark to evaluate transformer-based models for detection of polarized language in Persian (also called Farsi) social media. The aim is to evaluate 1) how and if finetuning the pre-trained models have substantial impact; 2) how Persian specific monolingual models compare to multilingual for this task; 3) how and if transfer learning from models trained on other languages such as culturally-distant English, and culturally-close[er] Turkish, and Arabic can be of interest for this task; and 4) how competitive Large Language Models (LLMs) are in a zero-shot setting. Our evaluation of ten transformer-based models and two LLMs on a publicly available Farsi polarization dataset shows promising findings,highlighting both the strengths and limitations of each approach.</abstract>
      <url hash="7ec90df6">2026.silkroadnlp-1.6</url>
      <bibkey>davoudi-goharian-2026-online</bibkey>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2026.silkroadnlp-1.6</doi>
    </paper>
    <paper id="7">
      <title><fixed-case>P</fixed-case>ars<fixed-case>CORE</fixed-case>: The <fixed-case>P</fixed-case>ersian Corpus of Online Registers</title>
      <author><first>Alireza</first><last>Razzaghi</last><affiliation>TurkuNLP, University of Turku</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Erik</first><last>Henriksson</last><affiliation>TurkuNLP, University of Turku</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Veronika</first><last>Laipalla</last><affiliation>TurkuNLP, University of Turku</affiliation></author>
      <pages>60-73</pages>
      <abstract>Despite recent advances in automatic web register (genre) labeling and its applications to web-scale datasets and LLM development, the effectiveness of these tools for digitally lowresource languages remains unclear. This study introduces ParsCORE, the first largescale collection of Persian web registers (genres), and evaluates deep learning models for register classification and keyword analysis across major registers. Using 2,000 humanannotated documents, the models achieved a micro F1-score of 0.76. The findings provide a foundation for future research on the linguistic and cultural specificities of Persian registers.</abstract>
      <url hash="0902aaac">2026.silkroadnlp-1.7</url>
      <bibkey>razzaghi-etal-2026-parscore</bibkey>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2026.silkroadnlp-1.7</doi>
    </paper>
    <paper id="8">
      <title><fixed-case>PMWP</fixed-case>: A Benchmark for Math Word Problem Solving in <fixed-case>P</fixed-case>ersian</title>
      <author><first>Marzieh</first><last>Abdolmaleki</last><affiliation>LT3, Ghent University, Belgium</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Mehrnoush</first><last>Shamsfard</last><affiliation>NLP Lab, Shahid Beheshti University, Iran</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Veronique</first><last>Hoste</last><affiliation>LT3, Ghent University, Belgium</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Els</first><last>Lefever</last><affiliation>LT3, Ghent University, Belgium</affiliation></author>
      <pages>74-82</pages>
      <abstract>Mathematical reasoning captures fundamental aspects of human cognitive ability. Although recent advances in LLMs have led to substantial improvements in automated mathematical problem solving, most existing benchmarks remain focused on English. As a result, robust mathematical reasoning remains a challenging and insufficiently explored capability for underrepresented languages including Persian. To address this gap, we introduce PMWP, the first dataset of 15K elementary-level Persian math word problems that supports both supervised training and evaluation of reasoning models. By expanding mathematical reasoning resources beyond English, PMWP contributes to the development of multilingual AI systems with stronger reasoning capabilities. In this work, we conduct a systematic evaluation of the Persian math word problem solving capabilities of different state-of-the-art LLMs. Our results indicate that DeepSeek-V3 exhibits reduced language bias when problem texts are translated into English, while Gemini-2.5-Flash achieves the highest equation value accuracy (72.02%) in Persian. In addition, we investigate parameter-efficient adaptation for equation generation by applying LoRA-based fine-tuning to LLaMA-3-8B and Qwen-2.5-7B. Our results show that, following fine-tuning, these openweight models achieve 91.65% and 92.53% exact equation match accuracy, respectively. Overall, our findings provide insights into the comparative strengths and limitations of proprietary and open-weight models for mathematical reasoning in Persian.</abstract>
      <url hash="e7cf4963">2026.silkroadnlp-1.8</url>
      <bibkey>abdolmaleki-etal-2026-pmwp</bibkey>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2026.silkroadnlp-1.8</doi>
    </paper>
    <paper id="9">
      <title><fixed-case>APARSIN</fixed-case>: A Multi-Variety Sentiment and Translation Benchmark for Iranic Languages</title>
      <author><first>Sadegh</first><last>Jafari</last><affiliation>Ghent University, Belgium</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Tara</first><last>Azin</last><affiliation>Carleton University, Canada</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Farhad</first><last>Roodi</last><affiliation>Purdue University, USA</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Zahra Dehghani</first><last>Tafti</last><affiliation>University of Tehran, Iran</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Mehrdad</first><last>Ghadrdan</last><affiliation>Islamic Azad University Science and Research, Iran</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Elham Vatankhahan</first><last>Esfahani</last><affiliation>Tarbiat Modares University, Iran</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Aylin</first><last>Naebzadeh</last><affiliation>University of Hull, England</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Mohammadhadi</first><last>Shahhosseini</last><affiliation>University of Milan, Italy</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Ghafoor</first><last>Khan</last><affiliation>Ghulam Ishaq Khan Institute of Engineering Sciences and Technology, Pakistan</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Kazem</first><last>Forghani</last><affiliation>Iran University of Science and Technology, Iran</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Danial</first><last>Namazi</last><affiliation>University of Tehran, Iran</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Seyed Mohammad Hossein</first><last>Hashemi</last><affiliation>Shahid Beheshti University, Iran</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Farhan</first><last>Farsi</last><affiliation>Amirkabir University of Technology, Iran</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Mohammad</first><last>Osoolian</last><affiliation>Iran University of Science and Technology, Iran</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Maede</first><last>Mohammadi</last><affiliation>Ferdowsi University of Mashhad, Iran</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Mohammad Erfan</first><last>Zare</last><affiliation>University of Tehran, Iran</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Muhammad Hasnain</first><last>Khan</last><affiliation>Iran University of Science and Technology, Iran</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Muhammad</first><last>Hussain</last><affiliation>Yuan Ze University, Taiwan</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Nooreen</first><last>Zaki</last><affiliation>Polytechnical University, Xian, China</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Joma</first><last>Mohammadi</last><affiliation>Amirkabir University of technology, Iran</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Shayan</first><last>Bali</last><affiliation>Yuan Ze University, Taiwan</affiliation></author>
      <author id="mohammad-javad-ranjbar-kalahroodi"><first>Mohammad Javad</first><last>Ranjbar</last><affiliation>University of Tehran, Iran</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Els</first><last>Lefever</last><affiliation>Ghent University, Belgium</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Veronique</first><last>Hoste</last><affiliation>Ghent University, Belgium</affiliation></author>
      <pages>83-97</pages>
      <abstract>The Iranic language family includes many underrepresented languages and dialects that remain largely unexplored in modern NLP research. We introduce APARSIN, a multi-variety benchmark covering 14 Iranic languages, dialects, and accents, designed for sentiment analysis and machine translation. The dataset includes both high and low-resource varieties, several of which are endangered, capturing linguistic variation across them. We evaluate a set of instruction-tuned Large Language Models (LLMs) on these tasks and analyze their performance across the varieties. Our results highlight substantial performance gaps between standard Persian and other Iranic languages and dialects, demonstrating the need for more inclusive multilingual and dialectally diverse NLP benchmarks.</abstract>
      <url hash="c8288e59">2026.silkroadnlp-1.9</url>
      <bibkey>jafari-etal-2026-aparsin</bibkey>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2026.silkroadnlp-1.9</doi>
    </paper>
    <paper id="10">
      <title>One Language, Three of Its Voices: Evaluating Multilingual <fixed-case>LLM</fixed-case>s Across <fixed-case>P</fixed-case>ersian, <fixed-case>D</fixed-case>ari, and <fixed-case>T</fixed-case>ajiki on Translation and Understanding Tasks</title>
      <author><first>Noor Mairukh Khan</first><last>Arnob</last><affiliation>Research &amp; Innovation Lab, University of Asia Pacific</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Abu Bakar Siddique</first><last>Mahi</last><affiliation>BUBT Research Graduate School, Bangladesh University of Business and Technology</affiliation></author>
      <pages>98-104</pages>
      <abstract>The Iranian linguistic family is pluricentric, encompassing Iranian Persian, Dari (Afghanistan), and Tajiki (Tajikistan). While Multilingual Large Language Models (MLLMs) claim broad coverage, their robustness across these regional variants and script differences (Perso-Arabic vs. Cyrillic) remains under-explored, particularly in the open-weight landscape. We evaluate five openweight models from the Qwen, Bloomz, and Gemma families across four downstream tasks: Sentiment Analysis, Machine Translation (MT), NLI, and QA. Utilizing a dataset of over 240,000 processed samples, we observe severe performance disparities. While the fine-tuned gemma-3-4b-persian achieves promising results on Iranian Persian (77.3% accuracy in Sentiment), almost all tested models appear to suffer catastrophic degradation on Tajiki script (dropping to 1.0 BLEU). These findings highlight a critical “script barrier” in current open-weight MLLM development for Central Asian languages. Code and data available here.</abstract>
      <url hash="0ed43ccd">2026.silkroadnlp-1.10</url>
      <bibkey>arnob-mahi-2026-one</bibkey>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2026.silkroadnlp-1.10</doi>
    </paper>
    <paper id="11">
      <title><fixed-case>P</fixed-case>ersian<fixed-case>P</fixed-case>unc: A Large-Scale Dataset and <fixed-case>BERT</fixed-case>-Based Approach for <fixed-case>P</fixed-case>ersian Punctuation Restoration</title>
      <author id="mohammad-javad-ranjbar-kalahroodi"><first>Mohammad Javad</first><last>Ranjbar Kalahroodi</last><affiliation>University of Tehran, Tehran, Iran</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Heshaam</first><last>Faili</last></author>
      <author><first>Azadeh</first><last>Shakery</last><affiliation>University of Tehran, Tehran, Iran and Institute for Research in Fundamental Sciences (IPM), Tehran, Iran</affiliation></author>
      <pages>105-113</pages>
      <abstract>Punctuation restoration is essential for improving the readability and downstream utility of automatic speech recognition (ASR) outputs, yet remains underexplored for Persian despite its importance. We introduce PersianPunc, a large-scale, high-quality dataset of 17 million samples for Persian punctuation restoration, constructed through systematic aggregation and filtering of existing textual resources. We formulate punctuation restoration as a token-level sequence labeling task and fine-tune ParsBERT to achieve strong performance. Through comparative evaluation, we demonstrate that while large language models can perform punctuation restoration, they suffer from critical limitations: over-correction tendencies that introduce undesired edits beyond punctuation insertion (particularly problematic for speech-to-text pipelines) and substantially higher computational requirements. Our lightweight BERT-based approach achieves a macro-averaged F1 score of 91.33% on our test set while maintaining efficiency suitable for real-time applications. We make our dataset and model publicly available to facilitate future research in Persian NLP and provide a scalable framework applicable to other morphologically rich, low-resource languages.</abstract>
      <url hash="fbcd1180">2026.silkroadnlp-1.11</url>
      <attachment hash="2d79545c" type="poster">2026.silkroadnlp-1.11.poster.pdf</attachment>
      <bibkey>ranjbar-kalahroodi-etal-2026-persianpunc</bibkey>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2026.silkroadnlp-1.11</doi>
    </paper>
    <paper id="12">
      <title><fixed-case>S</fixed-case>hughni Machine Translation Enhanced by Donor Languages</title>
      <author><first>Dmitry</first><last>Novokshanov</last><affiliation>HSE University</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Innokentiy S.</first><last>Humonen</last><affiliation>AXXX, iMak Lab, Trusted AI Research Center, RAS</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Ilya</first><last>Makarov</last><affiliation>AXXX, iMak Lab, Trusted AI Research Center, RAS</affiliation></author>
      <pages>114-120</pages>
      <abstract>This paper presents the first machine translation system for Shughni, an extremely lowresource Eastern Iranian language spoken in Tajikistan and Afghanistan. We fine-tune NLLB-200 models and explore auxiliary language selection through typological similarity and "super-donor" experiments. Our final Shughni–Russian model achieves a chrF++ score of 36.3 (45.7 on BivalTyp data), establishing the first computational translation resource for this language. Beyond reporting system performance, this work demonstrates a practical path toward supporting languages with virtually no prior MT resources. Our demo system with Shughni-Russian- English translation (Russian serves as a pivot language for the Shughni- English pair) is available on Hugging- Face (https://huggingface.co/spaces/Novokshanov/Shughni-Translator).</abstract>
      <url hash="ac34b4a6">2026.silkroadnlp-1.12</url>
      <bibkey>novokshanov-etal-2026-shughni</bibkey>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2026.silkroadnlp-1.12</doi>
    </paper>
    <paper id="13">
      <title>Segmentation Strategy Matters: Benchmarking Whisper on <fixed-case>P</fixed-case>ersian <fixed-case>Y</fixed-case>ou<fixed-case>T</fixed-case>ube Content</title>
      <author><first>Reihaneh</first><last>Iranmanesh</last><affiliation>Georgetown University</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Rojin</first><last>Ziaei</last><affiliation>Georgetown University</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Joe</first><last>Garman</last><affiliation>Georgetown University</affiliation></author>
      <pages>121-130</pages>
      <abstract>Automatic Speech Recognition (ASR) transcription accuracy remains highly sensitive to audio segmentation strategies, yet most benchmarks assume oracle timestamps unavailable in deployment. We systematically evaluate how audio segmentation affects Whisper’s performance on 10 hours of Persian YouTube content, comparing transcript-aligned (oracle) versus silence-based (realistic) approaches across contrasting acoustic conditions. Results reveal striking content-type dependency: podcast content benefits from timestamp segmentation (33% lower mean WER), while entertainment content favors silence-based segmentation (8% lower mean WER). This finding demonstrates that optimal segmentation must be content-aware, with silence detection better capturing natural boundaries in acoustically heterogeneous media while avoiding mid-utterance splits. We publicly release our evaluation framework, 10 hours of audio with gold transcripts, and segmentation results here: https://github.com/ri164-bolleit/persian-youtube-whisper-benchmark</abstract>
      <url hash="874fd02c">2026.silkroadnlp-1.13</url>
      <bibkey>iranmanesh-etal-2026-segmentation</bibkey>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2026.silkroadnlp-1.13</doi>
    </paper>
    <paper id="14">
      <title>Multi-modal Neural Machine Translation for Low-Resource Classical <fixed-case>P</fixed-case>ersian Poetry: A Culture-Aware Evaluation</title>
      <author><first>Soheila</first><last>Ansari</last><affiliation>Université du Québec à Montréal</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Mounir</first><last>Boukadoum</last><affiliation>Université du Québec à Montréal</affiliation></author>
      <author><first>Fatiha</first><last>Sadat</last><affiliation>Université du Québec à Montréal</affiliation></author>
      <pages>131-139</pages>
      <abstract>Persian poetry, particularly Rumi’s Masnaviye-Ma’navi, is known for its complex form, mystical narrative style, rich cultural information, and linguistic nuances, and is considered a low-resource domain. Translating Persian poetry is a challenging task for neural machine translation (NMT) systems. To address this challenge, we present a novel multimodal NMT system for Rumi’s Masnavi in four stages. First, we built a new multi-modal parallel Persian-English corpus of 26,571 aligned verses from all six books of Masnavi, and all paired with aligned audio recitations. Second, a strong text-only baseline is developed by applying domain-adaptive fine-tuning to mBART- 50, pre-trained on a large monolingual Persian poetry corpus, followed by training on the parallel Masnavi corpus (train set). Third, we extend this model to a multi-modal scenario by adding aligned audio representations using a cross-attention fusion mechanism. Fourth, we conduct a culture-aware evaluation. We propose a culture-specific item (CSI) evaluation approach by developing a CSI classification system and a Persian-English CSI dictionary alongside the standard MT metrics. Our findings demonstrate that integrating audio recitations increased the BLEU score from 9.85 to 17.95, and raised CSI-recall from 61.60% to 82.04%, suggesting greater consistency in producing culturally meaningful terms.</abstract>
      <url hash="2bb3a0b5">2026.silkroadnlp-1.14</url>
      <bibkey>ansari-etal-2026-multi</bibkey>
      <doi>10.18653/v1/2026.silkroadnlp-1.14</doi>
    </paper>
  </volume>
</collection>
