<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<collection id="2026.beyondalignment">
  <volume id="1" type="proceedings" ingest-date="2026-06-26">
    <meta>
      <booktitle>Proceedings of Beyond Alignment: Transdisciplinary Conversations on Human-<fixed-case>AI</fixed-case> Futures</booktitle>
      <editor><first>Malihe</first><last>Alikhani</last></editor>
      <editor><first>Camille</first><last>Gagnier</last></editor>
      <editor><first>Lauren M. E.</first><last>Goodlad</last></editor>
      <editor><first>Dan</first><last>Roth</last></editor>
      <editor><first>Mark</first><last>Sammons</last></editor>
      <editor><first>Matthew</first><last>Stone</last></editor>
      <publisher>Association for Computational Linguistics</publisher>
      <address>San Diego, CA, USA</address>
      <isbn>979-8-89176-419-4</isbn>
      <month>July</month>
      <year>2026</year>
      <url hash="355ae5a2">2026.beyondalignment-1</url>
      <venue>beyondalignment</venue>
      <venue>ws</venue>
    </meta>
    <frontmatter>
      <url hash="c711f11d">2026.beyondalignment-1.0</url>
      <bibkey>beyondalignment-2026-1</bibkey>
    </frontmatter>
    <paper id="1">
      <title>“<fixed-case>I</fixed-case> Was a Young <fixed-case>AI</fixed-case>”: On Probing the Effectiveness of Intervening on Anthropomorphic <fixed-case>AI</fixed-case> System Outputs</title>
      <author id="su-lin-blodgett"><first>Su Lin</first><last>Blodgett</last><affiliation>Mila - Québec AI Institute</affiliation></author>
      <author id="myra-cheng"><first>Myra</first><last>Cheng</last><affiliation>Stanford University</affiliation></author>
      <author id="alexandra-olteanu"><first>Alexandra</first><last>Olteanu</last><affiliation>Mila - Québec AI Institute</affiliation></author>
      <pages>1-10</pages>
      <abstract>We see growing concerns about how the increasingly pervasive deployment of AI systems whose outputs appear human-like might impact people. These concerns have already motivated work both examining what makes such outputs appear human-like, as well as developing interventions to help reduce perceptions of human-likeness or mitigate adverse impacts. In this paper, we report on an exploratory crowd study we designed to examine challenges for assessing the effectiveness of interventions, including whether interventions intended to minimize perceptions of human-likeness also mitigate adverse impacts. We find variations both in what kinds of outputs different participants deem more human-like, as well as in their preferences for human-like outputs. Even when participants seem to prefer the outputs they deem more human-like, many of them also recognize that such outputs can have adverse impacts. Drawing on these results and prior work, we discuss challenges to and considerations for assessing the effectiveness of interventions.</abstract>
      <url hash="bd0ad151">2026.beyondalignment-1.1</url>
      <bibkey>blodgett-etal-2026-young</bibkey>
    </paper>
  </volume>
</collection>
