<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<volume id="J79">
<paper id="1000">
  <title>ACL Microfiche Series 1-83, including Computational Linguistics (1974-1979)</title>
</paper>

<paper id="1001">
  <title><fixed-case>NSF</fixed-case> sponsorship for <fixed-case>AJCL</fixed-case> (<fixed-case>A</fixed-case>.<fixed-case>H</fixed-case>ood Roberts), Microfiche viewing equipment guide (<fixed-case>R</fixed-case>onald P. Borden), <fixed-case>ACL</fixed-case> Officers 1975 (Aravind <fixed-case>K</fixed-case>.<fixed-case>J</fixed-case>oshi), <fixed-case>ACL</fixed-case> program, <fixed-case>J</fixed-case>uly 26-27, 1974, Association for Literary and Linguistic Computing (<fixed-case>R</fixed-case>.<fixed-case>A</fixed-case>.<fixed-case>W</fixed-case>isbey), Computer at <fixed-case>MIT</fixed-case> Can Read (Jonathan <fixed-case>A</fixed-case>llen), Computer-Assisted Lexicography (Richard W Bailey), Current Bibliography (Brian <fixed-case>H</fixed-case>arris; <fixed-case>R</fixed-case>.<fixed-case>L</fixed-case>askowski)</title>
</paper>

<paper id="1002">
  <title>The Lexical Subclasses Of The Linguistic String Parser</title>
  <author><first>Eileen</first><last>Fitzpatrick</last></author>
  <author><first>Naomi</first><last>Sager</last></author>
</paper>

<paper id="1003">
  <title>Natural Semantics In Artificial Intelligence</title>
  <author><first>Jaime R.</first><last>Carbonell</last></author>
  <author><first>Allan M.</first><last>Collins</last></author>
</paper>

<paper id="1004">
  <title>A Few Steps Towards Computer Lexicometry</title>
  <author><first>Nicholas V.</first><last>Findler</last></author>
  <author><first>Heino</first><last>Viil</last></author>
</paper>

<paper id="1005">
  <title>Pattern-Matching Rules for the Recognition of Natural Language Dialogue Expressions</title>
  <author><first>Kenneth Mark</first><last>Colby</last></author>
  <author><first>Roger C.</first><last>Parkison</last></author>
  <author><first>Bill</first><last>Faught</last></author>
</paper>

<paper id="1006">
  <title>Personal Notes, Computational Semantics Tutorial at Lugano in March, Artificial Intelligence: Directory being compiled (<fixed-case>D</fixed-case>onald E Walker), Letters: Logos Development Corporation on <fixed-case>MT</fixed-case> System (Yorick Wilks), Solar Project Distributes Materials (Tim Diller; John Olney; <fixed-case>N</fixed-case>athan Ucuzoglu), <fixed-case>NAS</fixed-case>/<fixed-case>NRC</fixed-case> Studies International Information Programs, <fixed-case>NFAIS</fixed-case> Meeting Overlap Study Indexer Training Kit (Ben H Weil), On-line Terminal Searching Course at <fixed-case>P</fixed-case>ratt in <fixed-case>J</fixed-case>anuary (Patricia Breivik), Educational Data Systems Association Convention, Publication Problems: Journal Prices Rising (Philip H Abelson), 3rd Pisa Summer School: Report of Courses Lectures (Antonio Zampoli), Summer School at <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>tuttgart: Report of Lectures (Hans Jochen Schneider), Information and Philology Conference Report (Marichal), Ariosto Concordance in Progress (Cesare Segre), Text Data: Round Table on Analytic Procedures Held, <fixed-case>SIGLASH</fixed-case> (Micheal <fixed-case>L</fixed-case>esk; <fixed-case>R</fixed-case>obert Wachal; Dolores Burton; Karen Mullen), Political Science Concepts to be Collected and Analyzed (<fixed-case>G</fixed-case>eorge J Grahan), Realiable Software Conference Los Angeles <fixed-case>A</fixed-case>pril (M L Shooman), Psycholinguistics Conference New York <fixed-case>J</fixed-case>anuary, <fixed-case>NSF</fixed-case>: Excepts from the Organizational Directory (H Guyford Stever), Microfiche Equipment: Background Information for Buyers (Dake Gaddy), Artificial Intelligence in Poland Bibliography, <fixed-case>AAAS</fixed-case> Meeting: <fixed-case>J</fixed-case>anuary (W M Carlson), Current Bibliography (Brian <fixed-case>H</fixed-case>arris; R Laskowski)</title>
</paper>

<paper id="1007">
  <title>Semantic Directed Translation of Context Free Languages</title>
  <author><first>H. William</first><last>Buttelmann</last></author>
</paper>

<paper id="1008">
  <title>String Transformations in the <fixed-case>R</fixed-case>equest System</title>
  <author><first>Warren J.</first><last>Plath</last></author>
</paper>

<paper id="1009">
  <title><fixed-case>COLING</fixed-case> 76 (Dr Guy Rondeau), <fixed-case>WORKSHOP</fixed-case> on Theoretical Issues in Natural Language Processing (<fixed-case>TINLAP</fixed-case>) (Bonnie Nash Webber; Roger Schank), Summer School on Computational Linguistics at Rocquencourt (M Andreewsky), Summer School on Literary Statistics at <fixed-case>C</fixed-case>ambridge, England (M H T Alford), International Conference on Computers and the Humanities (<fixed-case>R</fixed-case>obert Dilligan; Rudolf Hirschmann; Joseph Raben; <fixed-case>D</fixed-case>onald Ross; Todd K Bender; Grace C Hertlein), <fixed-case>NFAIS</fixed-case> <fixed-case>CONFERENCE</fixed-case> information interfaces (Ben H Weil; Joseph Coyne; Ann Farren; A Hood Roberts), <fixed-case>IEEE</fixed-case> Conference: computers to reach the people (Martin L Rubin; Susan Wittig; Kerry Mark Joels; O Firschein And R K Summat), <fixed-case>IFIP</fixed-case> Conference: computers in education, International Conference: developing countries (Dr H A Al-Bayati; A A M Veenhuis; Richard C Atkinson) <fixed-case>NEH</fixed-case> <fixed-case>CALENDAR</fixed-case>: grant applications, <fixed-case>NATIONAL</fixed-case> <fixed-case>PROGRAM</fixed-case> <fixed-case>DRAFT</fixed-case>: library and information services, <fixed-case>RESEARCH</fixed-case> <fixed-case>PROGRESS</fixed-case>: Index Thomisticue in press (Roberto Busa <fixed-case>S</fixed-case>.<fixed-case>J</fixed-case>), <fixed-case>COMPUTER</fixed-case> <fixed-case>SECURITY</fixed-case>: <fixed-case>AFIPS</fixed-case> and <fixed-case>ACM</fixed-case> publish guides (<fixed-case>R</fixed-case>obert L Patrick), <fixed-case>OPINION</fixed-case>: A restricted sublanguage approach to high quality translation (Victor Raskin), <fixed-case>TECHNIQUE</fixed-case>: Letters with variable values and the mechanical inflection of <fixed-case>R</fixed-case>omanian words  (Minerva Rocva), <fixed-case>ACL</fixed-case> Secretary-Treasurer’s report, Editor’s Report</title>
</paper>

<paper id="1010">
  <title>Verbalization and Translation by Machine</title>
  <author><first>Wallace L.</first><last>Chafe</last></author>
</paper>

<paper id="1011">
  <title>A Discriminant Function Analysis of Co-Variation of a Number of Syntactic Devices in Five Prose Genres</title>
  <author><first>Mary Lois</first><last>Marckworth</last></author>
  <author><first>Wm. J.</first><last>Baker</last></author>
</paper>

<paper id="1012">
  <title>The <fixed-case>Y</fixed-case>erkish Language For Non-Human Primates</title>
  <author><first>Ernst</first><last>von Glasersfeld</last></author>
</paper>

<paper id="1013">
  <title>Understanding By Conceptual Inference</title>
  <author><first>Chuck</first><last>Rieger</last></author>
</paper>

<paper id="1014">
  <title>General (<fixed-case>T</fixed-case>homas A Sebeok), Phonetics (Iris Kameny), Speech recognition (Clifford J Weinstein; Victor W Zue), Speech synthesis (W A Ainsworth), Orthography (B.Blesser), Concordance, Lexicography (Godelieve L M Berry Rogghe), Grammar (<fixed-case>C</fixed-case>harles N Li), Parsers (William H Paxton), Semantics (Ju D Apresjan), Discourse (Barbara G Deutsch), Comprehensive, (<fixed-case>D</fixed-case>onald E Walker), Expression (Neil M Golden), Information structures (Micheal E Senku), Inference (c Willam Skinner), Dialectology (Sheldon <fixed-case>K</fixed-case>lein; V Rozencvejg), Acquisition (Lerry R <fixed-case>H</fixed-case>arris), Instruction (Daniel N Kalikow), Documentation (Christine Schaab), Translation (E J Lehmann), Programming (Jacques Andre; Catherine Fuchs), Pictures Analysis (J M Tenenbaum; T D Garvey; S A Weyl; H C Wolf); Literature (J L <fixed-case>M</fixed-case>itchell), Mathematics (Hubert Huther), Name Index</title>
</paper>

<paper id="1015">
  <title>Editorial Review Experimental Procedure, Information Retrieval Course (Gerard Salton), Linguistics Summer School (<fixed-case>A</fixed-case>lex Auswaks), Indexing Seminar (E H Brenner), Document Access System Proposed, Current Bibliography, Membership Directory 1974, 2nd <fixed-case>US</fixed-case>-Japan Travel Package, Solar Bibliography</title>
</paper>

<paper id="1016">
  <title>Simple Digital Speech Synthesis</title>
  <author><first>William M.</first><last>Fisher</last></author>
  <author><first>A. Maynard</first><last>Engebretson</last></author>
</paper>

<paper id="1017">
  <title>Personal Notes, <fixed-case>COLING</fixed-case> 76: Sixth International Conference on <fixed-case>CL</fixed-case> (Guy Rondeau), Letters: Yorick Wilks on <fixed-case>LOGOS</fixed-case> M T (Fondazione Dalle Molle), <fixed-case>AWARDS</fixed-case> <fixed-case>AFIPS</fixed-case> (Kenneth E Iversion; Norton M Astrahan), <fixed-case>NSF</fixed-case> Chapin New Program Officer For Linguistics (<fixed-case>P</fixed-case>aul G Chapin), <fixed-case>ACM</fixed-case> Forstythe Student paper competition, National Computer Conference 1976 Hamper <fixed-case>W</fixed-case>inkler (Carl Hammer; Stanley <fixed-case>W</fixed-case>inkler), <fixed-case>AAAS</fixed-case> Section T new name fellowship program (Joseph Becker), <fixed-case>O</fixed-case>ttawa Linguistics Documentation Centre (<fixed-case>T</fixed-case>homas R Hofmann), <fixed-case>MT</fixed-case> and <fixed-case>MAT</fixed-case> list of system and centre (Herbert Bruderer), <fixed-case>NFAIS</fixed-case> officers for 1975 (Ben H Weil), Abstracting And Indexing World Inventory of Service  (Gaye Hofsman; Toni Carbo Bearman), The <fixed-case>ATEF</fixed-case> and <fixed-case>CETA</fixed-case> sytem  (J Chauche), Political Science Terminology  (<fixed-case>G</fixed-case>eorge J Graham Jr), <fixed-case>COMPUTATIONAL</fixed-case> Semantics Reports on the Tutorial At Villa (Suzanne Hannin; Gregers Koch; Georg Sondergaard), Formulae in Coherent Text  (Felix Dreizin), <fixed-case>AFIPS</fixed-case> constituent Societies Purposes Membership Requirement Activities Publications Dues Addresses</title>
</paper>

<paper id="1018">
  <title>Semantically Analyzing an <fixed-case>E</fixed-case>nglish Subset for the Clowns Microworld</title>
  <author><first>Robert F.</first><last>Simmons</last></author>
  <author><first>Gordon</first><last>Bennett-Novak</last></author>
</paper>

<paper id="1019">
  <title>A Case History in Computer Exploraton of Fast Speech Rules</title>
  <author><first>Douglas B.</first><last>Moran</last></author>
</paper>

<paper id="1020">
  <title>Summaries of Contributions To The First National Conference on the Application of Mathematical Models and Computers in Linguistics (Part I: Roman Alphabet Contributions)</title>
  <author><first>A.</first><last>Ljudskanov</last></author>
</paper>

<paper id="1021">
  <title>Recent computer science research in natural language processing (Allen Klinger), Current bibliography</title>
</paper>

<paper id="1022">
  <title><fixed-case>ACL</fixed-case> Nominating Committee (William A Woods Jr; <fixed-case>R</fixed-case>obert Simmons; <fixed-case>R</fixed-case>obert Barnes), 13th Annual Meeting Abstracts Of Papers (Tim Diller; Jon <fixed-case>A</fixed-case>llen; Joyce Friedman; Bonnie Nash Webber; Chuck Rieger), <fixed-case>ASIS</fixed-case> Annual Meeting (Ruth Tighe), <fixed-case>ACM</fixed-case> Annual Conference, Solar Project Terminates <fixed-case>APRA</fixed-case> Support Ends (Dr Tim Diller), Energy Inofrmation Tools <fixed-case>IIA</fixed-case> <fixed-case>NFAIS</fixed-case> Workshop (<fixed-case>P</fixed-case>aul Zurkowski), <fixed-case>MT</fixed-case> <fixed-case>C</fixed-case>hinese Journals Offered on Subscription from Hong <fixed-case>K</fixed-case>ong (Shiu Chang Loh), Libraian of Congress <fixed-case>ASIS</fixed-case> telegram to President ford (Joshua <fixed-case>I</fixed-case> Smith), Bibliography on Semantics and Cognition at Castagnols (Fondazine Dalle Molle), Recent Publications (Roger C Schank; Neil M Goldman; <fixed-case>C</fixed-case>harles J Rieger <fixed-case>III</fixed-case>; Christopher k Riesbeck), Personal Notes</title>
</paper>

<paper id="1023">
  <title><fixed-case>AUTONOTE</fixed-case>2: Network Mediated Natural Language Communication in a Personal Information Retrieval System</title>
  <author><first>William E.</first><last>Linn, Jr.</last></author>
  <author><first>Walter</first><last>Reitman</last></author>
</paper>

<paper id="1024">
  <title>The <fixed-case>SQAP</fixed-case> Data Base for Natural Language Information</title>
  <author><first>Jacob</first><last>Palme</last></author>
</paper>

<paper id="1025">
  <title>Natural Language as a Special Case of Programming Languages</title>
  <author><first>Geoffrey</first><last>Sampson</last></author>
</paper>

<paper id="1026">
  <title><fixed-case>J</fixed-case>unction <fixed-case>G</fixed-case>rammar as a Base for Natural Language Processing</title>
  <author><first>Eldon G.</first><last>Lytel</last></author>
  <author><first>Dennis</first><last>Packard</last></author>
  <author><first>Daryl</first><last>Gibb</last></author>
  <author><first>Alan K.</first><last>Melby</last></author>
  <author><first>Floyd H.</first><last>Billings, Jr.</last></author>
</paper>

<paper id="1027">
  <title>A Formal Psycholinguistic Model Of Sentence Comprehension</title>
  <author><first>Peter</first><last>Reimold</last></author>
</paper>

<paper id="1028">
  <title>Summaries Of Contributions To The First National Conference on the Application of Mathematical Models and Computers in Linguistics (Part II: Russian Language Contributions)</title>
  <author><first>A.</first><last>Ljudskanov</last></author>
</paper>

<paper id="1029">
  <title><fixed-case>ACL</fixed-case> Officers 1976 (Stanley R Petrick), <fixed-case>ACL</fixed-case> Executive Committee Meeting (Joshi), <fixed-case>ACL</fixed-case> Financial Report (A Hood Roberts), Personal Notes, <fixed-case>NSF</fixed-case> Reorganization (Dr Edward Creutz), <fixed-case>MT</fixed-case> Latsec Shows in <fixed-case>Z</fixed-case>urich (Mr Herbert Bruderer), <fixed-case>XII</fixed-case> th International Congress of Linguistics (Wolfgang U Dressler), Acm Conference Employment Register (Orrin E Taulbee), Compcom 76 (Edward E <fixed-case>D</fixed-case>avid Jr; J Presper Eckert), Cybernetics And Systems Research (Schottengasse), Literary and Linguistics Computing  (Mrs J M Smith), <fixed-case>C</fixed-case>harles S Peirce Society (Carolyn Eisele), Computer Applicaton to Learning, Historical Linguistics (William Christie), Short Announcement and Reminders, <fixed-case>ACLS</fixed-case> Soviet Studies East <fixed-case>E</fixed-case>uropean languages, Special Libraries Association Scholarships, Acknowledgement (<fixed-case>A</fixed-case>llen <fixed-case>K</fixed-case>linger), Computer Generation of Sentences By Systemic Grammar (John Self), Interpretation And Integration of sentences into A C-net (Th. R Hofmann)</title>
</paper>

<paper id="1030">
  <title>Computers in the Humanities, edited by J. L. <fixed-case>M</fixed-case>itchell, Reviewed By Edith J Hols and Dan Burrows (J L <fixed-case>M</fixed-case>itchell), Speech Understanding Research Report <fixed-case>SRI</fixed-case> (<fixed-case>D</fixed-case>onald E Walker), Michigan Early Modern <fixed-case>E</fixed-case>nglish Materials (Richard W Bailey; <fixed-case>J</fixed-case>ames W Downer; Jay L Robinson; Patricia v Lehman), Voice Response Papers At Compcom 75 (<fixed-case>D</fixed-case>onald A Biggar), <fixed-case>NFAIS</fixed-case> Reports and Charts, <fixed-case>NYU</fixed-case> LINGUISTIC STRING PROJECT Bibliography, Multiple-Valued Logic Proceedings Tables of contents, Artificial Intelligence In Poland Bibliography 1972-1974, Current Bibliography (Januez Stanislaw Bien), <fixed-case>AFIPS</fixed-case> Press Catalog</title>
</paper>

<paper id="1031">
  <title>A Case-Driven Parser for Natural Language</title>
  <author><first>Brock H.</first><last>Taylor</last></author>
  <author><first>Richard S.</first><last>Rosenberg</last></author>
</paper>

<paper id="1032">
  <title>Proceedings, 13th Annual Meeting, Association for Computational Linguistics (1: Language Understanding Systems)</title>
  <editor><first>Timothy C.</first><last>Diller</last></editor>
</paper>

<paper id="1033">
  <title>Proceedings, 13th Annual Meeting, Association for Computational Linguistics (2: Language Generation Systems)</title>
  <editor><first>Timothy C.</first><last>Diller</last></editor>
</paper>

<paper id="1034">
  <title>Proceedings, 13th Annual Meeting, Association for Computational Linguistics (3: Parsing, Syntax, and Semantics)</title>
  <editor><first>Timothy C.</first><last>Diller</last></editor>
</paper>

<paper id="1035">
  <title>Proceedings, 13th Annual Meeting, Association for Computational Linguistics (4: Modeling Discourse And World Knowledge I)</title>
  <editor><first>Timothy C.</first><last>Diller</last></editor>
</paper>

<paper id="1036">
  <title>Proceedings, 13th Annual Meeting, Association for Computational Linguistics (5: Modeling Discourse And World Knowledge II, and Text Analysis)</title>
  <editor><first>Timothy C.</first><last>Diller</last></editor>
</paper>

<paper id="1037">
  <title><fixed-case>ACL</fixed-case> President 1976 (Stanley R Petrick), Personal Notes, Semantics <fixed-case>G</fixed-case>eorgetown Round Table, <fixed-case>AAAS</fixed-case> Program Excerpts Science And Expectations, New Application Deadline, Science And Government Ralston Speaks At <fixed-case>NCC</fixed-case> 76 (Dr Ralston), Architecture for <fixed-case>N</fixed-case>on<fixed-case>N</fixed-case>umeric Processing (Y W Su; G Jack Lipovski), <fixed-case>ASIS</fixed-case> President 1976 (Melvin S Day), Literary and Linguistics Computing Meeting Notes, Abstracting and Indexing Societies Conference, Instituto Per Gli Studi Semantic Cognitivi, <fixed-case>P</fixed-case>etrarch Translated by Computer (SUNY Binghamton), Stenotype Computer Aided transciption (Micheal E <fixed-case>L</fixed-case>a<fixed-case>B</fixed-case>orde), Serials Librarianship <fixed-case>D</fixed-case>rexel Library Quarterly (Benita M Weber), A Computer Simultion of <fixed-case>A</fixed-case>merican Sign Language (Harry W Hoemann; Vicki A Florian; Shirley A Hoemann), Platon A new Programming Language For Natural Language Analysis (Makoto Nagao; Jun-Ichi Tsujii), <fixed-case>ACL</fixed-case> Membership Data, Editor’s Report, Survey of Members Preliminary Report, <fixed-case>IEEE</fixed-case> Tutorials Computer Society</title>
</paper>

<paper id="1038">
  <title>Verb Paradigms For Sentence Recognition</title>
  <author><first>Marianne</first><last>Celce-Murcia</last></author>
</paper>

<paper id="1039">
  <title>Artificial Intelligence And Language Processing: A Directory Of Research Personnel</title>
  <author><first>Donald E.</first><last>Walker</last></author>
</paper>

<paper id="1040">
  <title>Natural Language Understanding Systems within the <fixed-case>A</fixed-case>. <fixed-case>I</fixed-case>. Paradigm: A Survey and Some Comparisons</title>
  <author><first>Yorick</first><last>Wilks</last></author>
</paper>

<paper id="1041">
  <title>Analysis Of <fixed-case>J</fixed-case>apanese Sentences</title>
  <author><first>Makoto</first><last>Nagao</last></author>
  <author><first>Jun-Ichi</first><last>Tsujii</last></author>
</paper>

<paper id="1042">
  <title>Abstracts from the 1975 <fixed-case>LSA</fixed-case> Meeting (Aravind K Joshi), Current Bibliography, Proceedings, 2nd <fixed-case>US</fixed-case>-Japan Computer Conference</title>
</paper>

<paper id="1043">
  <title>Personal Notes (Jaime <fixed-case>C</fixed-case>arbonell; Collins), 1976 National Computer Conference (J <fixed-case>P</fixed-case>aul Lyet), <fixed-case>NIMH</fixed-case> Technical Help for Proposers Minority Programs (Richard Lopez), <fixed-case>NSF</fixed-case> Foreign Currency Program <fixed-case>E</fixed-case>gypt, <fixed-case>I</fixed-case>ndia and Pakistan, Catastrophe Theory Thom At <fixed-case>SIAM</fixed-case> Meeting (Rene Thom), <fixed-case>NATO</fixed-case>, Advanced Study Institute (Joseph M Scandura), <fixed-case>C</fixed-case>.<fixed-case>S</fixed-case>. Pierce International Congress (Max H Fisch), New Journal Cognitive Science (Eugene <fixed-case>C</fixed-case>harniak; Allan Collins; Roger C Schank), <fixed-case>NSF</fixed-case> Rejected Proposals and Reconsideration, Conference Chronicle, 1976 Linguistics Institute Oswego New York, <fixed-case>BAAL</fixed-case> Seminar On Translation At Essex England (R R K Hartmann; W S Dodo), Indexing in Perspective seminar ar warsaw, <fixed-case>NFAIS</fixed-case> Officers 1976-77 (John E Crepa Jr), Experiments With A Powerful Parser (Martin Kay), <fixed-case>AFIPS</fixed-case> <fixed-case>W</fixed-case>ashington Report (Anthony Ralston)</title>
</paper>

<paper id="1044">
  <title>Computer Understanding Of Metaphorically Used Verbs</title>
  <author><first>Sylvia Weber</first><last>Russell</last></author>
</paper>

<paper id="1045">
  <title>Syntax In Automatic Speech Understanding</title>
  <author><first>Madeleine</first><last>Bates</last></author>
</paper>

<paper id="1046">
  <title><fixed-case>FBIS</fixed-case> Seminar On Machine Translation</title>
  <editor><first>David G.</first><last>Hays</last></editor>
  <editor><first>J.</first><last>Mathias</last></editor>
</paper>

<paper id="1047">
  <title>A Survey Of Syntactic Analysis Procedures For Natural Language</title>
  <author><first>Ralph</first><last>Grishman</last></author>
</paper>

<paper id="1048">
  <title>Abstracts of the 1976 <fixed-case>I</fixed-case>nternational <fixed-case>C</fixed-case>onference on <fixed-case>C</fixed-case>omputational <fixed-case>L</fixed-case>inguistics - <fixed-case>COLING</fixed-case> -</title>
  <editor><first>Martin</first><last>Kay</last></editor>
</paper>

<paper id="1049">
  <title><fixed-case>CLAM</fixed-case> A Computer Language Model  (Nicholas J. S. Dobree), <fixed-case>RFP</fixed-case>: Federal Research And Development By Contact (Mr Mort Grant), <fixed-case>AFIPS</fixed-case> Social Implicatons Committee (Herbert B Safford), <fixed-case>NFAIS</fixed-case> Structure And Purpose (Toni Carbo Bearman), <fixed-case>K</fixed-case>urzweil Reading Machine, Translating Machine Developed (<fixed-case>J</fixed-case>ames Cary)</title>
</paper>

<paper id="1050">
  <title>An Organization For A Dictionary (Dick H Frederickson), Current Bibliography (Dermot Ronan F Collis), Cashier du Groupe de travail Analyse et Experimntation (E Chouraqui and J Virbel), Bibliography and Subject index Current Computing , Directory Of University Computing Science (John W Hamblem), Privacy Security and the Information Processing Industry (Dehl A Gerberick)</title>
</paper>

<paper id="1051">
  <title><fixed-case>ACL</fixed-case> 14th Annual Meeting Program And Abstracts, <fixed-case>ACM</fixed-case> Employment Register At Computer Science Conference (Orrin E Taulbee), <fixed-case>NSF</fixed-case> Adivisory Panel For Linguistics (William D Dingwall; Victoria Fromkin; Ives Goddard; Roger Shuy;Carlota Smith; Arnold Zwicky), Europeon Congress on Information Systems and Networks, New Journal Transaction On Data Dase Systems (<fixed-case>D</fixed-case>avid k Hsaid), Applied Linguistics 5 th International Congress (Jacques d Garard), <fixed-case>AFIPS</fixed-case> Officers And Honors (Theodore J <fixed-case>W</fixed-case>illiams), <fixed-case>ACM</fixed-case> Officers 1976-1978 (Herbert R J Grosch), <fixed-case>LATSEC</fixed-case> Congressman Question Payment, The Future Of <fixed-case>MT</fixed-case> (Rudolph C Troike), <fixed-case>MT</fixed-case> Moscow International Seminar (<fixed-case>I</fixed-case> <fixed-case>I</fixed-case> Qubine), Book Review Essays on Lexical Semantics Vol <fixed-case>I</fixed-case> (V Ju Rozenvejg), <fixed-case>AFIPS</fixed-case> <fixed-case>W</fixed-case>ashington Report, Zwei Bilde Fur Das Arbeitszimmer Eines Geologen (C Edgen Wegmann)</title>
</paper>

<paper id="1052">
  <title>A Computational Treatment of Coordinate Conjunctions</title>
  <author><first>Carol</first><last>Raze</last></author>
</paper>

<paper id="1053">
  <title>Computer Understanding of Physics Problems Stated in Natural Language</title>
  <author><first>Gordon S.</first><last>Novak Jr.</last></author>
</paper>

<paper id="1054">
  <title>Multiple Environments Approach to Natural Language</title>
  <author><first>Janusz Stanisław</first><last>Bien</last></author>
</paper>

<paper id="1055">
  <title><fixed-case>ACL</fixed-case> New Officers for 1977 (<fixed-case>P</fixed-case>aul Chapin), Humanities 3rd International Conference (J S North), Linguistics and Literary Analysis 5th International (D E Ager), Computer Graphics and Interactive Techinque 4th Annual Conference (<fixed-case>J</fixed-case>ames E <fixed-case>G</fixed-case>eorge), Undergraduate Curricula and Computing Conference (Gerald l Engel), Representation and Understanding  (Daniel G Bobrow; Allan Collins), The Role Of Speech in Language (<fixed-case>J</fixed-case>ames F Kavanagh), Algebraic Parsing of Context-free Languages (Stephen F Weiss; <fixed-case>D</fixed-case>onald F Stanat), <fixed-case>SNOPAR</fixed-case> A Grammar Testing System (T P Kehler)</title>
</paper>

<paper id="1056">
  <title>Processing Case</title>
  <author><first>Yorick</first><last>Wilks</last></author>
</paper>

<paper id="1057">
  <title>Phonological Rules for a Text-to-Speech System</title>
  <author><first>Sharon</first><last>Hunnicutt</last></author>
</paper>

<paper id="1058">
  <title>Current Bibliography, Mathematical Models of Language  (<fixed-case>D</fixed-case>avid B Benson), Description Grammaticale du parler de l’Ile-aux-Coudres, Quebec (<fixed-case>D</fixed-case>avid A Dinneen)</title>
</paper>

<paper id="1059">
  <title>Editorial Board Three Years Terms Inaugrated, Eulogy Of A Ljudskanov  (G Rondeazu), Letters Concerning Igor Mel’chuk (<fixed-case>D</fixed-case>onald F Welker), <fixed-case>IFIP</fixed-case> Congress 77 Invited Speakers etc, Compcom Spring 1977 Program Excerpts (Stephan W Miller), <fixed-case>COLING</fixed-case> 76 Invited Papers Published in <fixed-case>SMIL</fixed-case>, <fixed-case>SMIL</fixed-case> Journal Of Linguistics Calculus (New Policy), Research In Progress <fixed-case>SSIE</fixed-case> Search Service, Epigraphy Informatic Methods Papers Published, Linguistics And Philosophy (New Journal) (<fixed-case>R</fixed-case>obert Wall), <fixed-case>C</fixed-case>anadian Linguistics Institute, Patent Information and Documentation Symposium Munich, Lacus Forum (Micheal <fixed-case>P</fixed-case>aradis), <fixed-case>IFIP</fixed-case> on Selection and Aquicsition of Data Base Systems, National Computer Conference 1977 Major Speakers etc (Mark Shepherd Jr), Information Industry Association Conference, <fixed-case>ASIS</fixed-case> Officers for 1977 (Margeret T Fischer), Taxonomy of Computer Science, Meetings <fixed-case>ACM</fixed-case> , <fixed-case>AFIPS</fixed-case> Seminar for <fixed-case>FCC</fixed-case> on data Communications, Notice to <fixed-case>AJCL</fixed-case> contributors Short-Paper format, Review Dynamic information and Library Processing (Gerard Salton), Current Bibliography</title>
</paper>

<paper id="1060">
  <title>Pitch Contour Generation in Speech Synthesis: A <fixed-case>J</fixed-case>unction <fixed-case>G</fixed-case>rammar Approach</title>
  <author><first>Alan K.</first><last>Melby</last></author>
  <author><first>William J.</first><last>Strong</last></author>
  <author><first>Eldon G.</first><last>Lytle</last></author>
  <author><first>Ronald</first><last>Millett</last></author>
</paper>

<paper id="1061">
  <title>Towards a “Natural” Language Question-Answering Facility</title>
  <author><first>Bill D.</first><last>Maxwell</last></author>
  <author><first>Francis D.</first><last>Tuggle</last></author>
</paper>

<paper id="1062">
  <title>Explanation Capabilities of Production-Based Consultation Systems</title>
  <author><first>A. Carlisle</first><last>Scott</last></author>
  <author><first>William J.</first><last>Clancey</last></author>
  <author><first>Randall</first><last>Davis</last></author>
  <author><first>Edward H.</first><last>Shortliffe</last></author>
</paper>

<paper id="1063">
  <title>Computation of a Subclass of Inferences: Presupposition and Entailment</title>
  <author><first>Aravind K.</first><last>Joshi</last></author>
  <author><first>Ralph</first><last>Weischedel</last></author>
</paper>

<paper id="1064">
  <title>Report Of the <fixed-case>ACL</fixed-case> 1977 Annual Meeting Panel on Speech (Stanley R Patrick), Essays on Lexical Semantics Vol <fixed-case>II</fixed-case> (Ernst Von Glasersfeld), Constituent and Pattern in Poetry  (Archibald A Hill), Current Bibliography</title>
</paper>

<paper id="1065">
  <title><fixed-case>ACL</fixed-case> Presidental Address 1977 (<fixed-case>P</fixed-case>aul G Chapin), Editor’s Report 1976, Editorial Board Meeting March 17 1977, Minutes 15th Annual <fixed-case>ACL</fixed-case> Business Meeting (<fixed-case>D</fixed-case>onald E Walker), <fixed-case>ACL</fixed-case> Secretary-Treasurer’s Report, Suggestions for Contributors, Researching Foundations By <fixed-case>J</fixed-case>ames Klevens (<fixed-case>J</fixed-case>ames Klevens), <fixed-case>NSF</fixed-case> Linguistics Programms Grant List, National Institute Of Education Grants and Proposals, National Endowment for the Humanities, <fixed-case>NFAIS</fixed-case> H W Koch President Elect (H William Koch), <fixed-case>NFAIS</fixed-case> Overlap Report, <fixed-case>IFIP</fixed-case> Recent Publicatons, <fixed-case>UNESCO</fixed-case> Spines Thesaurus, <fixed-case>BBN</fixed-case> Speech Understanding At <fixed-case>SRI</fixed-case>, <fixed-case>AFCET</fixed-case> Conference (E Chouraqui J Virbel), Fifth International Joint at Conference (Edward Fredkin), 5th International Congress of Applied Linguistics (Jacques D Gerard), <fixed-case>IFIP</fixed-case> Congress 1977, <fixed-case>MEDIFO</fixed-case> 1977, <fixed-case>C</fixed-case>anadian Linguistics Institute (<fixed-case>R</fixed-case>obert F Bell), Fourth Lacus Forum (Michel <fixed-case>P</fixed-case>aradis), International Seminar on <fixed-case>QA</fixed-case> and Data Base Systems (Pr J C Simon; Pr L Siklossy), Computer Music Conference, Conference Very Large Data Bases, International Computer Symposium, Pattern Recognition and Image processing Conference, <fixed-case>AFIPS</fixed-case> <fixed-case>W</fixed-case>ashington Report, <fixed-case>ACM</fixed-case> Student Competition (J A N Lee)</title>
</paper>

<paper id="1066">
  <title><fixed-case>COLING</fixed-case> 78 Call for Papers (A Zompolli), Metaphor And Thought A Conference, Conference on Algorithms for Image and Scene Analysis (K S Fu; A S Rosefeld), Recent Conferences <fixed-case>ICCH</fixed-case> 3 <fixed-case>IFIP</fixed-case> Congress 77 , <fixed-case>NFAIS</fixed-case> Notes, Northwestern Merges <fixed-case>EE</fixed-case> and <fixed-case>CS</fixed-case> (Stephen S Yau), <fixed-case>NHPRC</fixed-case> Grant Information, <fixed-case>ICCP</fixed-case> Annouces Certificate In computer Programming, <fixed-case>ACM</fixed-case> Employment Register 1978, Marsha the Daughter Of Eliza (John K Cipolard; Nicholas V Findler), <fixed-case>AFIPS</fixed-case> Presidential Address 1976 <fixed-case>NCC</fixed-case> (Dr Anthony ralston), <fixed-case>AFIPS</fixed-case> Press Publicatons 1977-1978, <fixed-case>AFIPS</fixed-case> <fixed-case>W</fixed-case>ashington Report (Pender M <fixed-case>M</fixed-case>c<fixed-case>C</fixed-case>arter), Linguistics Institute 1978</title>
</paper>

<paper id="1067">
  <title>A Goal Oriented Model of Human Dialogue</title>
  <author><first>James A.</first><last>Moore</last></author>
  <author><first>James A.</first><last>Levin</last></author>
  <author><first>William C.</first><last>Mann</last></author>
</paper>

<paper id="1068">
  <title>Aspects Of <fixed-case>E</fixed-case>nglish Sentence Stress (Susan F Schmerling), Annual Review Of Information Science And Technology (Ralph Weischedel), Factors Influencing the Placement of English Adverbs in Relation to Auxiliaries (Ivar Tonisson), Fondazione Dalle Molle Bibliography 1977, New Journal Linguisticæ Investigationes (John Benjamins B V), New Journal Studies in langauge (John Benjamins B V), Arts And Humanities Citation Index (Susan Deutch), Current Bibliography</title>
</paper>

<paper id="1069">
  <title><fixed-case>ACL</fixed-case> Officers 1978, <fixed-case>AJCL</fixed-case> Editorial Board (John L Benmnit; <fixed-case>W</fixed-case>allace Chafe), <fixed-case>ACL</fixed-case> Annual Meeting 1978 (<fixed-case>D</fixed-case>avid L Waltz), <fixed-case>ACL</fixed-case> 78 Session Descriptions, <fixed-case>TINLAP</fixed-case>-2 Proceedings Supplement Canceled (Dr <fixed-case>D</fixed-case>onald E Walker <fixed-case>ACL</fixed-case>), <fixed-case>ACL</fixed-case> Membership List Individuals 1977, <fixed-case>ACL</fixed-case> United States Institutional Member 1977, <fixed-case>ACL</fixed-case> Foreign Institutional Members 1977, Vingt Cinq Annees de recherches en synthesis de la parole  (Andre Malecot), Information * Politics Proceedings of the <fixed-case>ASIS</fixed-case> Annual Meeting Vol13  (Gerard Salton), Taxonomy of Computer Science  (Anthony ralston), <fixed-case>COLING</fixed-case> 78 (A Zampolli), <fixed-case>NCC</fixed-case> 78, Improving Data Base Utility and response Conference (A Reiter), Upcoming Conferences, Natural Language and <fixed-case>AI</fixed-case> At Yale, Pattern Recognition and Artificial Intelligence (T Pavlidis), 1978 Linguistics Institute, <fixed-case>AFIPS</fixed-case> <fixed-case>W</fixed-case>ashington Report</title>
</paper>

<paper id="1070">
  <title>Text Understanding: A Survey</title>
  <author><first>Robert</first><last>Young</last></author>
</paper>

<paper id="1071">
  <title>Spatial Reference and Semantic Nets</title>
  <author><first>Norman K.</first><last>Sondheimer</last></author>
</paper>

<paper id="1072">
  <title>Computational Semantics  (Eugene <fixed-case>C</fixed-case>harniak), Introduction to Contemporary Linguistic Semantics (<fixed-case>J</fixed-case>ames D <fixed-case>M</fixed-case>c<fixed-case>C</fixed-case>awley), Current Bibliography, <fixed-case>BBN</fixed-case> Publications on Intelligent <fixed-case>CAI</fixed-case></title>
</paper>

<paper id="1073">
  <title>What Some Semantic Theories Can’t Do  (Th R Hofmann), <fixed-case>NL</fixed-case> in Information Science (<fixed-case>D</fixed-case>onald E Walker; Hans Karlgren; Martin Kay), <fixed-case>CAL</fixed-case> in Science Education, New Journal Annuals Of the History of Computing (Bernard A Caller), New England Research Application Center, Linguafranca Document Search (<fixed-case>LLBA</fixed-case>), Demonstration Interactive Search of <fixed-case>LLBA</fixed-case>, <fixed-case>NFAIS</fixed-case>/ <fixed-case>UNESCO</fixed-case> Indexing Education Kit, Synmposium Computer Assisted Learning (J J Mathews), 1978 Linguistics Institute Conference And Symopsia, <fixed-case>DATA</fixed-case> Bases Usability and Responsiveness (Dr <fixed-case>A</fixed-case>llen Baiter), Conferences Internal Auditing  (D Eugene Shaeffer), Conferences Breifly Noted (K preston Jr), <fixed-case>NSF</fixed-case> Awards in Computer Science for 1976, <fixed-case>AJCL</fixed-case> A Description, <fixed-case>AJCL</fixed-case> Page Format, <fixed-case>AJCL</fixed-case> Opaque Card format, <fixed-case>AFIPS</fixed-case> <fixed-case>W</fixed-case>ashington Newsletter</title>
</paper>

<paper id="1074">
  <title>Two Papers on Semantic Interpretation in <fixed-case>M</fixed-case>ontague Grammar</title>
  <author><first>Joyce</first><last>Friedman</last></author>
  <author><first>Douglas B.</first><last>Moran</last></author>
  <author><first>David S.</first><last>Warren</last></author>
</paper>

<paper id="1075">
  <title>The Derivation of Answer From Logical forms in a Question Answering System (Fred J Damerau), One More Step Toward Computer Lexicometry (Nicholas V Findler; Shu-Hwa lee; Richard Fritzon), Manifest: The Press At Twin Willows (<fixed-case>D</fixed-case>avid G Hays), Reviews of Micro Hardware and Software to be Published, Publishing <fixed-case>AJCL</fixed-case> (<fixed-case>D</fixed-case>avid G Hays), Conferences <fixed-case>ASIS</fixed-case> And <fixed-case>HICSS</fixed-case>, Linguistic Structures Processing Zampolli ed (Antonio Zampolli), Natural Language in Information Science (<fixed-case>D</fixed-case>onald E Walker; Hans Karlgren; Martin Kay), Description of <fixed-case>AJCL</fixed-case>, <fixed-case>AFIPS</fixed-case> <fixed-case>W</fixed-case>ashington Report June 78</title>
</paper>

<paper id="1076">
  <title><fixed-case>TINLAP</fixed-case>-2 Program and Abstracts, Dictionary Society of North America Special Meeting (Dr Ladisslav Zgusts), <fixed-case>NCC</fixed-case> 79 Personal Computing Festival (Richard Kuzneck; Russell Adams; Jay P Lucas), 1979 National Computer Conference  (Merlin G Smith; Richard E Merwin), Short Notice of Upcoming Conferences (Makato Nagao), Recognition Memory (Rem), Semionics Associates, Screensplitter, The Target Projects Interactive Computerized Multilingual Dictional (John Burga)</title>
</paper>

<paper id="1077">
  <title><fixed-case>ACL</fixed-case> Minutes Of the 16th Annual Business Meeting, <fixed-case>ACL</fixed-case> Secretary-Treasurer’s Report, <fixed-case>ACL</fixed-case> Officers For 1979, <fixed-case>ACL</fixed-case> Officers 1963-1979, <fixed-case>NSF</fixed-case> Support for Computational Linguistics (<fixed-case>P</fixed-case>aul G Chapin), <fixed-case>NEWS</fixed-case> Short Notes, <fixed-case>NEWS</fixed-case> Arist Reprint Request (Martha E <fixed-case>W</fixed-case>illiams), <fixed-case>NEWS</fixed-case> Summer Linguistics at <fixed-case>T</fixed-case>exas, PhD Programs in Computational Linguistics, Journal Computational Linguistics and Computer Languages (T Frey; T Vamos), Journal Discourse Processes (Roy d Freedle), Book Notices (Mel’cuk R Ravic), Yale <fixed-case>AI</fixed-case> Projects Research Reports Available, Summary of Research on Computational Aspects of Evolution Theories (Raymond D Guab), Taxonomy Information Sciences, Machine Aids to Translations a Concise State of the Art Bibliography  (Wayne Zachary), Reviews On Human Communications Jo Ed  (William L Benzon), Abhamgigkeitsgrammatik, Glancing Referring and Explaining in the Dialogue System (W Wahlster; A Jameson; W Hoeppner), A Critical Look at a formal Model for Stratificational Linguistics (Alexander T Borgida)</title>
</paper>

<paper id="1078">
  <title>Language Representation</title>
  <editor><first>David L.</first><last>Waltz</last></editor>
</paper>

<paper id="1079">
  <title>Contexts of Language</title>
  <editor><first>David L.</first><last>Waltz</last></editor>
</paper>

<paper id="1080">
  <title>Inference and Theory</title>
  <editor><first>David L.</first><last>Waltz</last></editor>
</paper>

<paper id="1081">
  <title>Computational Linguistics in the <fixed-case>USSR</fixed-case>: July 1978 (Joyce Friedman), Association for Literary and Linguistics Computing Bulletin Vol 6 Num 2 1978, Association for Literary and Linguistics Computing Bulletin Vol 6 Num 3 1978, Properties of Lexical Relations (Martha W Evens; Raoul N Smith), Models Of the Semantic Structure Of Dictonaries (Kenneth C Litkowski), <fixed-case>AFIPS</fixed-case> <fixed-case>W</fixed-case>ashington Report <fixed-case>F</fixed-case>ebruary 1979, <fixed-case>AFIPS</fixed-case> <fixed-case>W</fixed-case>ashington Report March 1979, <fixed-case>AFIPS</fixed-case> <fixed-case>W</fixed-case>ashington Report <fixed-case>A</fixed-case>pril 1979</title>
</paper>

<paper id="1082">
  <title>A Model for Knowledge and its Application to Discourse Analysis</title>
  <author><first>Brian</first><last>Phillips</last></author>
</paper>

<paper id="1083">
  <title>A Lexicon for a Computer Question-Answering System</title>
  <author><first>Martha W</first><last>Evens</last></author>
  <author><first>Raoul N</first><last>Smith</last></author>
</paper>

</volume>
